In this video we describe how we model the two machine one
buffer line as a Markov process and generate numerical results
from it.
Then we interpret the results.
There are several models in the literature.
Here we're going to focus on the deterministic processing
time, or Buzacott model.
In this model there's a deterministic processing time,
the geometric failure and repair times,
the failures are operation dependent,
and the model is a discrete state discrete time Markov
process.
In my view this is the simplest model that's available.
Other models in the literature have continuous time
or continuous material or more complex
failure and repair behaviors.
Let's remind you of the definition of a Markov process.
The probability that the state has a certain value of time t
plus one given the values of the state at time t and t
minus 1 and t minus 2, and so on is
the same as the probability that the state that
has that value at time t plus 1 given
the value of the state at time t.
So the history of the state before that is irrelevant.
For notation purposes if we write i equals little x of t
plus 1 equals little x of t, the probability that x of t plus 1
equals i given x of t equals j is equal to p i j.
And that's the transition matrix of the Markov process.
And that really summarizes everything
we need to know about it.
Since the buffers are finite the state space
is going to be finite.
An analytical solution is available for Markov process
model of a two machine line.
Here, the state space is given by n alpha 1 alpha 2,
where n is the number of parts in the buffer
and n goes between 0 to capital N. Alpha i
is the repair state of machine i for i equals 1 and 2.
Alpha i equals 1 means machine i is up, or operational.
Alpha equals 0 means machine i is down, or under repair.
Here's some examples of transition probabilities.
Suppose j equals x of t, which is 3, 0,
1 That means there are three parts in the buffer,
the first machine is down, and the second is up.
ni, which is x of t plus 1, is equal to 7,
1, 1 which means that there are seven parts in the buffer
and both machines are up.
Then the transition probability from 3, 0, 1 to 7, 1,
1 is 0 because the buffer level cannot change by more than one
part in one time unit.
Here's another one.
Suppose that at time t the state is 3, 0, 1 again.
And this time at time t plus 1 the state is 2, 0, 1--
that is, there are two parts in the buffer,
the first machine is down and the second is up.
Then the transition probability from 3, 0, 1 to 2, 0, 1
is 1 minus r1 times 1 minus p2 because the probability
that the first machine does not get repaired is 1 minus r1,
and the probability that the second machine does not fail
is 1 minus p2 and the buffer level must go down by one.
And by contrast, if the state at time t
is 3, 0, 1 and the state at time t
plus 1 is also 3, 0, 1, then that transition probability
is zero.
And the reason is that the buffer level
must go down by one.
Here's the state transition graph for the model
that we're looking at.
In this case, we're assuming a buffer size of 13.
n, which is shown along the top here,
is the number of parts in the buffer.
And the alphas represent the repair states of the machines.
0,0 means both machines are down.
0,1 means the first is down and the second is up 1,0
is the first is up and the second is down.
And 1,1 is the first is up and the second is that is up.
This state, for example, represents 3, 0, 1,
the examples that we've been looking at so far.
If the buffer size is capital N then
there are capital N plus 1 buffer levels.
Each machine has two possible states.
So the total number of states is 2 times 2 times
capital N plus 1.
In this case that works out to 56 possible states.
Now, the probabilities of the p's and r's are
relatively small.
So the machine states are more likely to stay the same
than change at a single transition.
But of course, eventually they do change.
When both alphas are the same--
in other words, 0, 1, or 1, 1--
the buffer level does not change.
When alpha 1 equals 0 and alpha 2 equals 1
the buffer level goes down because the first machine does
not put a part in the buffer but the second one
does take one out.
On the other hand, if alpha 1 equals 1 and alpha 2 equals 0,
so the machine states are 1, 0, the buffer level goes up.
The first machine puts a part in.
The second one doesn't take a part out.
There are different colors of the states.
The ones that are colored yellow are internal states
and typical.
They all have the same transition behavior.
Each usually has a pretty small probability.
The other states are boundary states.
The light blue ones are non-transient.
They generally have relatively large probabilities.
The dotted ghostly looking white states are transient.
Those are states with steady state probability of 0.
To obtain the probabilities of all the states
we form the steady state transition
equations and the normalization equation and we solve them.
This gives us the probabilities of all the states.
We use these probabilities for calculating the performance
measures.
Here we briefly describe the steady state transition
equation and the normalization equation.
Here again we remind you of the Markov process analysis.
So pi of ni alpha 1 alpha 2 is the steady state probability
that there are n parts in the buffer
and the machine states are alpha 1 and alpha 2.
To obtain all these pi's, let's let i equals n alpha 1 alpha 2,
and j equals n prime alpha 1 prime alpha 2 prime,
just for notation purposes.
Then the transition equations can
be written as pi i equals the sum if h of pi ij pi j,
or in vector matrix form, pi equals p pi.
We also have the normalization equations.
The sum of all the pi's equals 1.
This is exactly what we discussed in the Markov process
videos, although the specific notation for this system
is a little more complicated here.
It's more complicated because i and j
represent triplets and alpha 1, alpha 2 are not just integers.
So how do we use these probabilities to calculate
the performance measures?
Well, the production rate can be thought of as the probability
that a part can leave the system in any operation time.
In order for that to happen, the second machine has to be up
and the buffer has to be non-empty.
Now let's look at the state space again.
The states that are highlighted in purple are those states.
If the machine states are 0, 1, as long as the first machine
is not empty all of these states allow parts to leave the system
because machine 2 is up.
That's what the one means.
When both machines are up, then we have these states.
And the sum of the probabilities of all the states in purple
is the probability that a part leaves
the system in one time step.
To calculate the average inventory
we evaluate this summation.
This is a standard expression for the average
of any quantity, in particular the average inventory.
So now let's examine how the production
rate in average inventory vary with buffer size.
In this graph the horizontal axis is the buffer size.
The vertical axis is the production rate.
These graphs were drawn using the methods described
in the last two slides.
The situation is that we have to design a two machine one buffer
line to produce at a specified production rate.
I'll tell you what that production rate is later.
We have already chosen the second machine.
It has r2 equals 0.1 and p2 equals 0.01.
We still need to select the first machine
and the size of the buffer.
There are five possible choices for the first machine.
They all have p1 equals 0.01, the same as the second machine.
However, they all have different r1,
which means they have a different mean time to repair.
The versions of machine one with a high r1,
or low mean time to repair, means
they are easier to repair.
The machine designers did a better job
of making it easier to get at the parts that must be changed
more often or maybe they've developed a better failure
diagnostic system.
So what can we observe from looking at these graphs?
First of all, all the graphs are increasing.
This is because more storage space means
that each machine is less likely to force
the other to be idle due to starvation or blockage.
That leads to greater production rate.
Second, all the graphs have upper limit
and approach them asymptotically.
This because when the buffer size is infinite,
we have an infinite buffer line.
The production rate cannot be larger than that of a line with
the same machines and an infinite buffer.
And that production rate is finite
so there is a finite upper bound.
We know that that's the production rate of the slower
machine of the two.
The isolated production rate of the second machine
which is r2 over r2 plus p2, is 0.1 over 0.1
plus 0.01, which is 0.909 parts per operation time.
So let's look at the two slower versions
of machine one, those with r1 equals 0.06 and r1
equals 0.08, the black and the blue graphs.
The isolated production rates are 0.857 for 0.06 and 0.889
for 0.08.
They're both less than the isolated production
rate of the second machine.
So the limiting production rate of a line
with one of those machines as a first machine
is 0.857 and 0.889, respectively.
The asymptotes are shown on the graph.
In the case of the two fastest machines,
the isolated production rates are 0.923 and 0.933.
They are both faster than the second machine
so the limiting production rate of a line with one
of those as the first machine is the speed
of the second machine, or 0.909.
Both of the graphs for these machines
have the same asymptote.
The middle version of the first machine
is the one with the same r as the second machine, 0.1.
Since they both have the same isolated production rates,
a two machine one buffer line with that first machine
has the same asymptote as the lines with the two fastest
machines, 0.909.
In this case, the production rate
approaches that limit much more slowly than the lines
that use the two fastest first machines.
One more observation-- the graphs
with the smaller r1 lie below the graphs with the larger r1.
This is because if we compare the two production lines that
are the same in every respect except r1,
the line with the smaller r1, or larger average downtime,
will most often stay down longer whenever it fails.
Therefore the line with the smaller r1
will produce less in the same time
so it has a smaller production rate, p.
Here's a question for you.
What is the production rate of the line when n equals 0?
Is it zero?
Pause the video if you want to think about it before hearing
the answer from me.
The answer is, the production rate
can be found from the Buzacott formula on slide 36.
It is not zero.
In this graph, the horizontal axis is the buffer size
and the vertical axis is the average inventory
in the buffer.
So what do we observe from seeing this graph?
First of all, again, all the graphs are increasing.
This is because the more storage space you have,
the more stuff you store.
Those of us who own closets will know that very well.
As n approaches infinity the lower two graphs
approach a limit.
This is because the first machine
is slower than the second.
The line is essentially a queuing system
where the first machine determines
the arrival process of the queue, which is the buffer.
And the second machine is the surface process.
The arrival process is slower than the surface process.
So when the buffer becomes very large,
the whole thing acts like an infinite buffer.
That limiting system has a steady state and therefore
a finite average inventory.
The upper two graphs do not approach a limit
as n approaches infinity.
In fact, they both approach straight lines which
are parallel to the n bar equals n line, which
is drawn here as a dashed line.
This is because the first machine is faster
than the second.
If the buffer really was infinite,
there would be no steady state behavior.
When the buffer is finite but large
the buffer is nearly full most of the time, regardless
of the size of the buffer.
In fact, the average amount of space in a buffer
approaches a limit.
When the two machines are the same,
the average amount of inventory is
equal to the average amount of space in the buffer,
whatever its size.
Therefore n bar equals n over 2.
This is shown by the green line for r1 equals
0.1 which is equal to r2.
Now lets design the production line
or at least narrow the possible design choices.
The marketing department has told us
that they need the line to produce parts
at a rate of 0.88 parts per operation time.
What are the best possible choices
of machine one in the buffer size?
The two graphs that we've been studying are shown here.
A horizontal line has been added to the production rate graph
to indicate the production rate target of p equals 0.88.
The feasible choices are at the intersections
of the production rate curves with the target line.
The intersections are shown.
The first thing we notice is that the worst version
of machine one, the one where r equals 0.06,
and the isolated efficiency of the first machine is 0.857,
is not a feasible solution.
There is no intersection with the target production rate.
No matter how big the buffer is, the two machine production line
will never meet the target production rate
if that version of machine one is used.
For the feasible machines, we see
a pattern in the intersections.
The better machine one is, that is the larger r1 one is,
the smaller the buffer that is needed to achieve
the production rate target.
This is the list of the feasible solutions.
Except for the worst feasible version
of machine one, the version where r1 equals 0.08,
the table suggests that the feasible buffer
size is two or three times the mean time to repair.
This is a pretty small sample, but it's not a coincidence.
The purpose of the buffer is to prevent stoppages
from propagating.
Therefore the required buffer size
should be a small multiple of the average downtime.
This is a very crude rule of thumb
but it's a good starting point for design.
The graph on the right is the average inventory graph,
but now with the buffer size indicated
for each version of m1.
We see that the worse m1 is, the more
inventory is needed to meet the target production rate.
The conclusion is that a buffer can
compensate for machine unreliability
but only up to a point.
And the worse the machine is, the more compensation
is needed both in inventory space and an actual inventory.
We have not solved the problem of selecting the optimum buffer
size.
That is because the problem is not fully specified.
In particular, we have not specified the costs--
the capital cost of the different versions
of machine one, the cost of buffer space,
and the inventory holding cost.
But let's assume that the better machine one is,
the more expensive it is.
That means that if we spend more to get a more reliable machine
we can get by with less inventory space and less
inventory.
If we economize on the machine, we
need to spend more on inventory space and inventory.
Exactly which is the best choice depends on exactly what
those costs are.
So here are some questions.
This is the same pair of questions
I've been asking over and over again.
Pause the video if you want to answer the question before you
hear my answers.
First question, if you want to increase the production rate,
which machine should we improve?
We have been ignoring the cost of improvements.
In that tradition, the answer to the first question
is the bottleneck.
What would happen to the production rate
if we improved any other machine?
The answer to the second question
is, improving any machine will increase the production rate.
That is demonstrated on the next two slides.
This slide and the next show that
improving a non-bottleneck machine
could increase production rate.
The green line is the production rate when
the machines are identical.
The blue line shows the production rate
for improving machine one, that is reducing
its mean time to repair.
Now machine two is the bottleneck.
The red line shows what happens when
we improve machine one more-- that is, when we improve a non
bottleneck machine.
There's a noticeable increase in the production
rate when the buffer a small.
The amount of the increase diminishes
as the buffer gets larger because the production
rate gets closer to that of machine two, the bottleneck.
On the other hand, if we need a substantial increase
in the production rate and the buffer is not small
we must improve the bottleneck.
OK, one more question.
Is it better to have short frequent disruptions
or long infrequent disruptions?
Suppose we're designing a line and everything
was decided except the choice of the first machine.
Two versions are available that are
identical in all respects but one.
In particular, they have the same efficiency.
They differ in both the frequency of failures
and the duration of downtimes.
I say they differ in only one respect because in order
for them to have the same efficiency
the ratio of mean time to repair to mean time to fail
must be fixed.
If that machine were the only machine in the factory and all
we cared about was production rate
the versions of that machine would be equivalent.
But which version will give us a higher production
rate when it's in a line?
Which do you think?
Pause this video and try to answer the question before you
listen to the answer.
This graph is the production rate
of a two machine line versus the mean time
to repair of the first machine.
The parameters of the second machine and the buffer size
are shown.
r1 and p1 are chosen so that the efficiency of the first machine
is 0.9.
That means that the mean time to fail
is nine times the mean time to repair.
r1 and p1 are chosen together so that the efficiency
of the first machine is 0.9.
That means that the mean time to fail
is nine times the mean time to repair.
Well the answer is evidently short, frequent failures
because the production rate when r1 and p1 are small
is larger than the production rate when r1 and p1 are large.
Again, pause this video and think about why.
I'll give you the answer when you start it up again.
The reason is that when the mean time to repair and mean time
to fail of the first machine are small
compared to the size of the buffer,
a single failure is not likely to empty the buffer.
In order to empty the buffer, you need a long period
with several failures and repairs
of both machines during which the first machine is down
more than the second machine.
If the mean time to repair and mean time
to fail of the first machine are large then
it's very likely that a single failure of the first machine
can empty the buffer.
The same is true of the second machine
but then we will be thinking about how often
a single failure will fill the buffer
and as a result block the first machine.
Well that's all we have.
I hope you enjoyed this course and I hope
that you'll find it useful.
Part two continues the exploration of the issues
that we've studied in part one, the causes and consequences
of the variability in factories and what to do about them.
I hope you'll come back for part two
and for the rest of the principles and manufacturing
program.
Please feel free to offer comments, criticisms
and suggestions for improvements.
Thank you very much for your participation.