Now, we're going to begin to study
systems that operate in continuous,
rather than discrete time.
The states are still discrete, so they can be numbered 0, 1,
2, 3, and so forth.
Or with multiple indices.
The time, however, is a real number,
defined on the real number line from minus infinity
to plus infinite, or a subset of that-- a smaller interval.
There are important differences from discrete time systems.
Since events can take place at any time,
we have to consider the probability
that an event can take place during an interval
rather than in a specific time.
We do this for very small intervals
so the probability is very small.
This is a little like a density function,
where the probability of an event happening
in a small interval is proportional to the size
of that interval.
As a consequence, the important transition parameters
are not probabilities.
They're rates in units of probability per time.
The probability of a transition from j
to i during the interval t to t plus delta t
is approximately lambda i j delta t,
where delta t is small.
Lambda i j delta t is approximately the probability
of finding the system in state i at time t
plus delta t, given that it was in state j at time t.
And this is true for i not equal to j.
We'll deal with i equals j later.
Let's rewrite that last equation to make
it a little more precise.
Lambda i j delta t is equal to p of x of t
plus delta t equals i given x of t
equals j, plus little o of delta t, for i not equal to j.
Little o is a function that satisfies this limit.
The limit of little o of delta t divided by delta t is 0.
So in other words, little o of delta t
is a function which could be quadratic in delta t
or a higher power.
This is the formal definition of little o of delta t.
This is a standard mathematical expression.
There is also a big O function, which is related
but not the same thing.
If the size of the interval was not small,
the transition probability from j to i
would be a complicated nonlinear function of delta t.
That function would be 0.
That function would be 0 for delta t equals 0.
If we expanded that function into a Taylor series,
the constant term would then be 0,
and the first non-zero term would be the one
that's linear in delta t.
This is the transition graph for a continuous time system.
Compared with the discrete time graph,
there are two important differences.
Lambda is a probability rate.
Lambda i j delta t is a probability.
The labels on the graphs are probability rates, not
probabilities.
The labels on the transition arrows
are probability rates, not probabilities.
And there are no self-loops in the system.
We'll discuss why there are no self-loops soon.
Before we get there, think about what
the labels on the self-loops would be
and what they would mean.
So here's a hint.
We haven't defined lambda i i.
We've only defined lambda i j for j not equal to i.
Compare this graph with a similar discrete time graph
that we talked about earlier.
On this slide, we'll be developing one
of the transition equations.
Take a look at the graph on the previous slide
while we're doing this development.
In the example, we're going to focus on state 5.
So for delta t small, we're going
to look at pi 5 of t plus delta t.
That is approximately this equation.
So let's focus on the first term in the right-hand side
of this equation.
If the system is in state 5 of time t,
when the system is in state 5, its next state
could be 2, 4, or 6.
Or it could simply stay in state 5.
Given that the system is in state 5 of time t,
the probability that the system is
in state 5 of time t plus delta t
is the probability that the system does not leave state 5.
That is, that it does not go to states to 2, 4, or 6.
That probability is the coefficient of pi 5
in the second line of the equation.
The second line is then the probability
that the system does not leave state 5 during the time
interval from t to t plus delta t.
For the third line, we'll notice that the transition
graph shows that the possible previous states from state 5--
the states from which the system can reach 5 directly--
are 2, 3, 6, and 7.
The probability that the system is in state 5 of time t
plus delta t, given that it was in state 2 at time t,
is lambda 5, 2 times delta t.
The first term in the last line of the equation
is the part of the probability that the system
is in state 5 of time t plus delta t, that is due to state 2
being the possible previous state.
Similarly for the other terms.
Then the whole last line is the probability
that the system arrives at state 5 from a different state
previous time.
So this slide is the next step in the development
of the transition equation.
It's equivalent to the second.
We simply separated out pi 5 from the rest
of the second line.
Now we'll subtract pi 5 from both sides of the last equation
and divide both sides by delta t.
In addition, we're going to take the limit as delta t goes to 0.
So this gives us the time derivative of pi 5
on the left side of the equation.
This is the transition equation for state 5.
It would be nice, however, to write
this equation a little more compactly and symmetrically.
To do this, recall that we did not define
lambda i j when i equals j.
So we have some symbols available for a definition
of lambda i i.
To do this, recall that we did not define lambda i j when
i equals j, so we have some symbols
available for a definition, lambda i i.
So why not define lambda 55 as the coefficient of pi 5
in this equation.
So that's what we're doing on this slide.
Notice that I'm saying for convenience.
I did that because this sometimes confuses people.
Since lambda 55 is negative, they
think that we've defined the negative probability,
or a negative probability rate.
We have not.
We have just used an otherwise unused symbol
to make the equation look a little bit nicer.
So now the equation looks like this.
So let's write this in general.
Pi i of t is the probability that x sub t is equal to i.
It's convenient, as we said, to define lambda i
i as minus the sum of lambda j i, where j is not equal to i.
So now the transition equations become
d pi i d t equals the sum of lambda i j pi j of t.
We also have the normalization equation.
The sum of pi i of t is equal to 1.
And just to remind you, that lambda i i is often confusing,
so don't let it throw you.
So let's look at the same equations in vector matrix
form.
So we're going to find pi of t and nu,
as we did earlier for the discrete time case.
Define the lambda matrix--
that symbol, if you're not familiar with it,
is a capital lambda, is the matrix of lambdas.
The transition equations can be written very compactly as d pi
d t equals lambda pi of t.
The normalization equation is new transpose pi equals 1.
That is, the sum of the pi's equals 1.
And we have some other facts.
New transpose p is equal to 0.
That's important because each column of p sums to 0.
The reason that the columns sum to 0
is because of the way we define the diagonal terms.
The diagonal terms are just the negative
of the sum of all the other terms in the column.
Also, pi of t is e to the lambda t pi of 0.
That's a matrix exponential there that e to the lambda t--
if you're not familiar with it, don't worry about it.
We will solve any equations that we come up
with in the usual way, component wise.
Again, we need to worry about the steady state probability
distribution.
So pi i, without an argument, is defined as the limit
as t goes to infinity of pi i of t, if it exists.
And that same issue about whether it exists or not occurs
in the continuous time case.
The steady state transition equations
are obtained by just setting d pi d t equals 0.
So 0 is the sum over j of lambda i j pi j.
Again, we have an alternative form,
which is the steady state balance equations, which
are pi times the sum of lambda i i for all m not equal to i,
equals the sum over j of j not equal to i of lambda i j pi j.
And of course, we have the normalization equation.
That still holds for the steady state equations.
And we're going to have the same issue in which we
have to throw out one of the transition equations
or one of the balance equations and replace it
with the normalization equation.
In matrix vector form, we define pi as the limit of pi of t,
if it exists.
The steady state transition equations
can just be written 0 equals lambda pi.
And the normalization equation is new transpose pi equals 1.
Here are some sources of confusion
in dealing with continuous time models,
if you haven't seen this before.
Never draw self-loops in continuous time Markov process
graphs.
Never write something like 1 minus lambda 14
minus lambda 24 minus lambda 64.
Write instead 1 minus, and then in parentheses, lambda 14,
plus lambda 24, plus lambda 64, times delta t.
Or just simply, minus the sum of lambda 12,
lambda 24, lambda 64.
The reason for that is that the lambdas
are rates, not pure numbers.
Whereas, 1 is a pure number.
So you can have an expression that mixes them both.
So remember, lambda i i, which is minus the sum of lambda j i,
where j is not equal to i is not a rate and not a probability.
It's only a convenient notation.