So in this video of 2.854.1x, we'll go over unit four or week
practice problem three.
So this problem is a little complicated than the last one.
So basically you're at a manufacturing operation.
Parts arrive with a rate of 5 per hour.
But during this operation there is an inspection process.
70% of the parts will pass, 5% of the parts are going to fail,
and 25% of the parts is going to need rework.
So it re-enters this same process.
So let's put this down in a block diagram.
So here is the operation Q. Parts are arriving with lambda
equal to 5 per hour.
Parts pass 70% of the time.
Parts fail 5% of the time.
And parts are going to need rework,
going back, 25% of the time--
rework 25%.
This is 25%.
So let's call this lambda prime, basically
is that rearrival rate if you want to call it that.
So the aggregate arrival rate basically is lambda a,
and that is just lambda plus lambda prime.
So what is lambda prime?
So lambda prime can be determined by whether or not
lambda is the limiting rate or mu is the limiting rate.
So lets take a look at mu.
The service time is 8 minutes per part.
So mu is 60 minutes per hour over 8 minutes, which
is 7.5 parts per hour.
So if lambda a is greater than mu,
then mu becomes the bottleneck of this flow.
So that means lambda prime is depending on mu, 0.25 mu.
So if this is the case, then lambda a is just 5
plus 1.875, which is 6.875.
The mu we said here is 7.5.
So lambda a being 6.875 is actually smaller than mu,
so this scenario cannot happen.
So that means the limiting factor
must be lambda a, meaning that lambda a is less than mu.
So lambda prime is--
now many of you are going to think its 0.25 times lambda,
but you have to include lambda prime in the rearrival process.
So lambda prime is just lambda plus lambda prime time 0.25.
So 0.75 lambda prime equal 0.25 lambda.
So Lambda prime is just 1/3 of lambda, which is 3 over 5--
I mean 5 over 3.
Lambda a is just 5 plus 5 over 3, which is 6.6667.
That's lambda a.
What is the utilization rate?
So this is just a simple formula,
rho equal lambda a divided by mu, which is 6.667 over 7.5.
That's 0.889.
The unexpected number of items are waiting in the queue.
So this is Lq again.
In practice problem two we said the formula for Lq
is just rho squared over 1 minus rho.
That is 0.889 squared over 1 minus 0.889, which is 7.11.
So we're asking about the waiting time in the line,
in the queue.
So Wq-- we'll use Little's law, which is just Lq over lambda
a--
lambda a.
And that is 7.11 over 6.667, 1.066 hours.
The expected sojourn time--
so sojourn time, this is just W, the amount of time people
spend in the system.
And from Little's law we know W is just L over lambda a.
So what is L?
L is just rho over 1 minus rho.
That's 0.889 over 1 minus 0.889.
And that is approximately 8.
So this is just 8 over 6.667.
That's approximately 1.2 hours.
This wraps up practice problem three.
Please leave your questions in the discussion section below.
Thank you.