While probability may seem to be about imprecise uncertain
phenomena, probability calculations are precise
and they can model important features of the real world
very well.
They apply equally well to the frequency and state
of belief interpretations.
This week will be a very short course on the basics
of probability theory.
We will focus on those parts of the theory that
will be useful in understanding random events and factories,
and their consequences.
We'll only be scratching the surface
of a vast body of knowledge.
The axioms of probability are very
important because all quantitative probability
methods are based on them.
Suppose we want to describe an experiment which
has more than one outcome.
We'll define the universe, U, to be
the set of all possible outcomes of the experiment.
The elements of U are called samples.
E1, E2, and so forth, are subsets of U.
A special subset is the null or empty set,
the set that has no elements.
P is a function of sets that has the following property.
First of all, the probability of any subset is between 0 and E1.
The probability of the universe is E1.
The probability of the empty set is 0.
And, if E1 and E2 are disjoint, that
is the intersection is empty, they have no samples in common.
Then P of the union of EI and EJ is
equal to P of EI plus P of EJ.
Technically, P is a measure.
You can think of a measure as a generalization of area
or volume.
If you think of the universe as a big plot of land,
then some of the subsets are small plots
of land inside the universe.
The last two axioms are very natural.
The area of A set of no land is zero,
and the area of A set of land which
consists of two non-overlapping plots
is the sum of their areas.
All right, some notation.
Omega, lowercase omega, is often used
as the symbol for a generic sample,
subsets of U. The E's are called events.
And P of E is the probability of event E.
Technically, P is a measure.
You can think of a measure as a generalization of an area
or volume.
If you think the universe is one big plot of land,
then some of the subsets are smaller plots
of land inside the universe.
The last two axioms are very natural.
The area of a set of no land is zero,
and the area of a set of land which consists of two
non-overlapping plots is the sum of their area's.
So, let's look at some examples.
Throw a single die.
The possible outcomes are 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6.
Omega can be any one of those values.
Here's another example, more closely related
to manufacturing.
Let's say that N of T is the number of parts in inventory
at time T. Then omega is the set of numbers N of 1, N of 2,
and so forth.
That's called a sample path.
An event can be defined by a statement.
For example, E is the event that there
are six parts in the buffer at time t equals 12.
This is the formal notation for that.
So E is the set of all omega, such that N of 12 equals 6.
And that's written in the last line,
which is actually spoken the same way as what I just read.
Here's an illustration of a discrete sample space.
The circles represent samples.
The color of the circles indicates the probability.
Now, imagine that we have a dart thrower who's throwing darts
at this board, and the darts are going to land in these circles.
In fact, let's make it interesting by blindfolding
the dart thrower.
Now, the graphical notation, here,
is that the darker circles represent higher probabilities
and the lighter circles represent lower probabilities.
So when the DART thrower throws his darts,
we get more of them tending to land in the darker circles
and fewer of them landing in the lighter circles.
But it's not uniform, and there's always a probability
that we could get more in some of the lighter circles
than in some of the darker ones.
This is a thought experiment only.
Do not actually try this out.
Do not do this at home.
Venn diagrams are useful to illustrate set theory,
and they work--
and they're useful for here, as well.
A is a subset of U, so that's an event.
A bar is the notation for the set of all elements
that are not in A.
Then, according to the last axiom of probability,
P of A bar is equal to 1 minus P of A.
The last axiom tells us the probability
of the union of two sets, whose intersection is an empty set.
What about two sets that do have some elements in common?
That probability is given by the formulas shown.
We have to subtract off the probability of the intersection
to avoid counting that intersection twice.
Independent events are ones in which the occurrence of one
has no effect on whether the other occurs.
Therefore, the probability of both occurring
is the product of each one occurring.
Here's an example.
In this example, imagine that the dart thrower
is throwing darts at the irregular grid, which is shown
at the bottom of the slide.
Now, the grid is divided in such a way
that the upper left figure shows the probabilities of landing
in vertical strips.
And the upper right shows the probability of the dart landing
in horizontal strips.
But those two are independent of one another.
So, when we threw the dart at the grid,
the probability of it flowing in a specific place,
whether the dark lands in a given
horizontal strip and a given vertical strip is independent.
The probability that it lands in the box shown
is the product of the probability
that it lands in that horizontal strip, and the probability
that it lands in the vertical strip.
The probability of the horizontal strip is 0.179,
the probability of the vertical strip is 0.05,
so the probability of landing in that specific box is 0.0089.
Conditional probability is a very important concept.
If A and B are not independent events,
then knowing that B has occurred affects the probability
that A has occurred.
What is the probability that a dart lands in A, if I know
that the dart has landed in B?
If B is a subset of A, the probability is 1.
If there's a large overlap between A and B,
then that probability is high.
On the other hand, if A and B are disjoint, in other words,
they have no elements in common, then the probability is zero.
Conditional probability is the probability
that A has occurred, given that we know that B has occurred.
In order for the dart to land in A, given
that it has landed in B, it must land
in the intersection of A and B. Therefore,
the probability that it has landed in A,
given that it has landed in B, is the probability
of the intersection divided by the probability of B.
So, here's an example.
Let's throw a die.
Let's call A the event of getting an odd number, 1, 3,
or 5.
And B is the event of getting a number less than or equal to 3,
which is 1, 2, or 3.
Then, the probability of A and the probability of B
are both 1/2.
The probability of A intersection B,
is just the probability of getting a 1 or 3,
and that's one third.
That's two possibilities out of six.
So, the probability of A given B is the probability
of the intersection divided by the probability of B,
which is 2/3.
And, one way of thinking about that,
is that the intersection is 1 or 3,
and the probability of getting A is getting 1 or 3, but not 5.
So, that's 2/3.
The law of total probability deals
with the following question.
Suppose event A can occur in several different ways.
Specifically, A might occur if E!
or E2 or E3, and so forth, occurs.
We know the probability of E1, E2, and E3 occurring.
And we know the conditional probability of A occurring,
given that E1 E2 and so on and so forth, has occurred.
So, what is the probability of A occurring?
So, let's look at the slide.
So we going to build this up simply, from simple cases
to something more complicated.
Let B be this set, which is the union of C and D.
And C and D are disjoint.
They have no elements in common.
In that case, the probability of A given C
is probability of A intersection C, divided by probability of C,
is just the definition of condition probability.
And probability of A given D is the probability--
is the probability of the intersection of A and D,
divided by probability of D.
In addition, the probability of C given B
is equal to the probability of C intersection B, divided
by the probability of B, which is just probability
of C over probability of B. Because C intersection B is
just the same as C. Similarly, the probability of D
given B is just probability of D divided by probability of B.
Now, we can write the intersection of A and B,
as the intersection of A with C union D, which
is A intersection C, union A intersection D. A intersection
C and A intersection D are disjoint.
So the probability of A intersection B
is just the probability of A intersection with C union
D, which is just the probability of A intersection
C plus a intersection D, because of that disjointness.
From the definition of conditional probability,
we can write this equation as P of A given B times
probability of B, equals P of A given C times the probability
of C, plus the probability of A given
D times the probability of D. If we divide through,
by probability of B, then we get the equation shown.
And that turns into probability of A given B equals probability
of A given C, times the probability of C given B,
plus the probability of A given D,
times the probability of D given B.
OK.
That looks nice.
Let's see where we can go from there.
So, a very important case is when
C union D which is equal to B, is just the whole universe.
In other words, the dart could land in C
or it could land in D. No other place.
And so, we're asking whether the dart has landed in A.
So A intersection B is equal to A so probability of A
is equal to probability of A intersection C plus probability
of A intersection D, which finally leads to this equation.
Probability of A is equal to probability
of A given C times the probability of C,
plus the probability of A given D,
times the probability of D. OK.
Let's generalize that and then see what it means.
The generalization is when we have lots of events.
So all of these E events, together
cover the whole set, the whole universe,
and they have no overlap.
And the A event is shown by the circle.
More generally, A and E1 through EK are events.
And EI intersection EJ equals the empty set for all I
not equal to J, and the union of all the E's are
the universal set.
And we typically say that, as the set
of the EJ's is mutually exclusive
and collectively exhaustive.
Then, the sum of all the probabilities of EJ is equal
to 1, but more importantly, probability of A is the sum
of probability of A given EJ times the probability of EJ,
over all the J's.
This can be illustrated by a graph, in this figure.
If I know that EJ has occurred, then there's
a probability that A has occurred,
which is given by P of A given E1, and so forth.
This kind of graph is going to come
up later when we talked about--
when we talk about dynamic processes.
Here's an example.
It's kind of silly, but I think it makes the point.
Let's set A the event that I will have a cold tomorrow.
E1 is the set that it says that it's raining today,
E2 is the event that it's snowing today,
and E3 is that it's sunny today.
So, we're going to assume that those
are all the possibilities, and it can only
either rain or snow or be sunny, and not two of them
at the same time.
So, the event A intersection E1 is the event
that I will have a cold tomorrow and it's raining today.
P of A, given E1, is the probability
I will have a cold tomorrow given that it's raining today,
and so forth.
So, the event that I will have a cold tomorrow
is the same as either the event that I
will have a cold tomorrow and it's raining today,
or I will have a cold tomorrow and it's snowing today,
or I will have a cold tomorrow and it's sunny today.
So, because of all the assumptions that we made.
So, the probability that I will have a cold tomorrow
is equal to the probability that I will have a cold tomorrow
and it's raining today, plus the probability that I
will have a cold tomorrow and that snow today,
plus the probability that I will have a cold tomorrow
and it's sunny today.
So, the probability that I will have a cold tomorrow
is the probability that I will have a cold tomorrow, given
that it's raining today, times the probability that it's
raining today.
Plus, the probability I will have cold tomorrow,
given that it's snowing today, times the probability that it's
snowing today.
Plus, the probability that I will have a cold tomorrow,
given that it's sunny today, times the probability that it's
sunny today, which we can just write this way.
And, so, that's the illustration of the law
of total probability.