The first important example of a continuous time Markov chain
is the exponential random variable.
The exponential random variable T
is the time to move from state 0 to state 1 in this figure.
It is qualitatively and quantitatively similar
to geometric random variable.
We start in state 1 and after some time, we go to state 0.
So you can't have a simpler Markov chain than that.
Let's derive the transition equations
for this simple chain.
Pi of 0 at time t plus delta t is the probability
that you make the transition from 1 at time t to 0 at time t
plus delta t times the probability of being in state 1
at time t plus the probability of making the transition from 0
at t to 0 at t plus delta t times the probability
that the system was in state 0 at time t.
Writing it with a more compact notation, we just have pi of 0,
t plus delta t is mu delta t pi 1, t
plus pi 0, t plus little o.
The transition probability from 1 to 0 in an interval of length
delta t is mu delta t.
That accounts for the first term on the right side
of the equation.
The transition probability from 0 at t to 0 at t plus delta t
is simply 1 in this case, because once you get into state
0, you stay in state 0.
So the coefficient of pi 0t in that equation is simply 1.
So turning that into a differential equation
by subtracting pi 0t from both sides and dividing by delta t,
we get the derivative.
So d pi 0t dt is equal to mu pi 1, t.
Let's develop the equation for state 1.
The probability of being in state 1 at time t plus delta t
is the sum of two terms.
The first one is the probability of finding the system in state
1 at time t plus delta t-- given that it was in state 1 at time
t-- times the probability of it being in state 1 at time t plus
the probability that the system was in state 1 at time t plus
delta t-- given that it was in state 0 at time t--
times the probability of finding the system in state 0
at time t.
That just becomes the right side is 1 minus mu delta
t times pi of 1, t.
That's the first term, because the probability
of going from state 1 to state 1 is the probability
of not leaving state 1.
So that coefficient is just 1 minus mu delta t.
The probability of going from state 0 to state 1 is 0.
You can't do it.
That's the way we define the problem.
So there is no term for pi of 0, t.
So that just reduces down to d pi dt equals minus mu pi of 1,
t.
So let's put them together.
There are the two transition equations.
Note that the sum of the two equations is zero.
The solution to those equations is very simple
if the initial condition is that we start the system in state 1.
So that means pi of 0, 0 equals 0 and pi of 1, 0 equals 1.
Then pi of 1, t e to the minus mu t and pi of 1,
t is equal to 1 minus e to the minus mu t,
and the two probabilities always sum to 1.
Now, let's talk about exactly when that transition takes
place.
What's the probability distribution
of when it happens?
That probability is equal to the probability
that it was in state 1 at time t and state 0 at time t
plus delta t, which is approximately
equal to the probability that the system is in state 0
at time t plus delta t, given that it was in state 1
at time t, times the probability of it being in state 1
at time t, which is just mu delta t times e to the minus mu
t.
The exponential density function is, therefore, f of t
is mu e to the minus mu t for t greater than 0.
And, of course, 0 for t less than 0.
The time of that transition, the transition from 1 to 0,
is said to be exponentially distributed with rate mu.
The expected transition time is 1
over mu, which is the integral from 0 to infinity of te
to the minus mu t.
So the exponential density function
is mu e to the minus mu t, for t greater than
or equal to 0 and 0 otherwise.
The cumulative distribution function--
just the integral of that-- is 1 minus e
to the minus mu t, for t greater than or equal to 0 and 0
otherwise.
We already calculated the mean.
We can calculate the variance, that's 1 over mu squared.
So the standard deviation is the same as the mean, 1 over mu.
So the coefficient of variation is equal to 1.
And here are the graphs of the density and the distribution
function.
Suppose you have a process that you think
is exponentially distributed and you
collect some samples of when the transition takes place.
We'll see sometimes, the transition
takes place very soon.
Sometimes it takes a longer time.
But if we don't take very many samples,
we'll get a histogram that looks like the one in the figure.
That doesn't look much like the exponential distribution,
and that's because we took very few samples.
If we took more, it would look more
like that exponential distribution.
So keep that in mind when you take a small number of samples.
In fact, there's a large number of distributions
that have a density function that sort of qualitatively
look like the exponential distribution.
If you only take a few samples, you
may not be able to distinguish one from the other.
So if you're only planning to take a few samples,
then the exponential distribution
is probably a pretty good stand-in for anything
that has that general shape.
So there are a few properties of the exponential distribution
that you should keep in mind.
The first one is memorylessness.
We talked about this earlier.
The probability that the transition time, T, is greater
than little t plus x, given that it's greater than x,
is equal to the probability that the transition
time is greater than t.
In effect, what we're saying is that if the transition hadn't
taken place by time x, then the time
that it will take place in the future
is distributed just the same as the exponential distribution
starting at time 0.
So you don't remember anything that happened
or that nothing happened before time x.
The time of the transition is given this way.
The probability that the time of the transition is between t
and t plus delta t, given that it hadn't taken place
by time T, is just mu delta t for small delta t.
OK, here's another one.
Let's suppose we have n exponentially-distributed
random variables with parameters mu 1 to mu n.
And we define a new random variable,
which is T, which is the minimum of all those random variables.
So that is the time of the first event that
takes place, the first time that one of those processes
makes its transition.
What's the probability distribution of T?
Well, it turns out the T is an exponentially-distributed
random variable with parameter mu
equals the sum of the mus of each of those individual ones.
Now, that's important when we think about the transition
graph that we started with in this section.
So the time that the system stays in any given state
is exponentially distributed, because it leaves that state
to different other states with times that
are exponentially-distributed.
Let's use the exponential distribution
to describe a model that's a little closer to the mission
of the course, which is to talk about manufacturing systems.
Let's take two exponential distributions
and represent the transitions from up to down
and down to up in a machine.
So the time to make the transition from up to down
is exponentially-distributed with parameter p.
The time to make the transition from
down to up is also exponentially-distributed,
this time with parameter r.
This is going to be similar to the geometric
unreliable machine model.
But, of course, in continuous time.
So again, we invoke the law of total probability.
The probability that the machine is up at time t
plus delta t is equal to the probability
that the machine is up at time t plus delta t, given
that machine is up at time t times
the probability that the machine was up at time t
plus the probability that the machine is up at time t
plus delta t, given that it was down at time t times
the probability it was down at time t plus little o.
And similarly for the other probability
we care about, the probability that the machine is
down at time t plus delta t.
So we'll use this notation, pi 1,
t is the probably that the machine is up at time t.
Pi 0, t is the probability that the machine is down at time t.
So the conditional probability that the machine
is up at time t plus delta t, given that it was up at time t,
is 1 minus p delta t.
That's the probability that it didn't leave state 1.
The probability that it's up at time t
plus delta t, given that it was down at time t,
is just r delta t.
Therefore, that becomes pi of 1, t
plus delta t equals 1 minus p delta t
pi of 1, t plus r delta t pi of 0, t plus little o.
And similarly, for pi of 0, t plus delta t.
We can get ready to create a derivative by subtracting
pi of 1, t from both sides.
Now, we're going to divide by delta t
and take the limit as delta t goes to 0.
So here's the difference quotient.
And we take the limit and we get the pi 1, t dt
is equal to pi of 0, t r minus pi of 1, t p.
And we have a similar equation for d pi dt of 0, t.
Notice again that the two equations add up to 0.
We can solve that system of two linear differential
equations and two unknowns and we get pi of 0,
t equals p over r plus delta t plus a quantity
in brackets times e to the minus r plus pt.
And pi of 1, t is 1 minus pi 0, t.
So in the limit, as t goes to infinity,
pi of 0, which is the probability
that the machine is down, is equal to p over r plus p.
And pi of 1, the probability that the machine is up,
is r over r plus p.
And again, that fraction r over r plus p is important.
The mean time to fail is 1 over p
and the mean time to repair is 1 over r.
Now, this is in natural time unit, it's not operation times.
Natural time units means minutes and seconds and hours
and so forth.
If the machine makes mu parts per time unit
on the average when it's operational,
the steady state average production rate
is just mu times r over r plus p, which is mu over mean time
to fail over mean time to fail plus mean time to repair, which
is mu e.
And e, which is r over r plus p, is
the efficiency of the machine.