This week, we go into great depth about single part
manufacturing systems.
Such systems are economically important in themselves.
In addition, they allow us to study some important properties
of manufacturing systems without lots of messy complications
that exist in most real world factories.
We'll study flow lines, also known as production,
or transfer, lines.
In such systems, we have machine,
followed by buffer, followed by machine, followed by buffer,
and so forth.
The machines are unreliable.
The buffers are finite.
In many cases, the operation times are constant and equal
for all machines.
The reason that buffers are present
is to prevent the stoppage of one machine
from forcing the other machines to be idle.
This graph is the production output
from a simulation of a transfer line.
The horizontal axis is the time in weeks.
The vertical axis is the output in a week.
The parameters of the line are comparable to an industry
line making small auto parts, like piston rods.
The customer for this product may be an engine assembly
plant.
As you can see, the average weekly output
is about 3,000 parts.
But notice that the best week's output
is about twice that of the worst week during the two year
period.
If their customer is an assembly plant that
needs 3,000 parts a week, every week,
there must be a buffer of at least 1,000 parts
between this plant and that customer.
This simulation shows that, for these two year period,
there would not be an interruption of production
in the assembly plant if there were a buffer of that size.
Note that in a supply chain, upstream inventory is usually
less expensive to hold than downstream inventory.
It takes up less space.
Most products are assemblies, and there's usually
a lot of error in an assembly.
The first case we'll look at is pretty simple--
a single unreliable machine.
If the machine is perfectly reliable,
and its average operation time is tau,
then its maximum production rate is 1 over tau.
Keep in mind that sometimes the term Cycle Time is used
instead of Operation Time--
but be careful because Cycle Time has at least two meanings.
The other meaning is the time a part spends in a system.
If the system is a single reliable machine,
then the two meanings are the same.
But if it's anything more complicated, they're not.
Now, let's look at a single unreliable machine.
We'll be concerned with interruptions
due to machine failures.
Actually, the interruption could be
anything that could be modeled in a similar way.
A machine is up, or operational, or down-- being
repaired or maintained.
The Mean Time to Fail is the average time
between the completion of a repair and the next time
the machine fails.
It's also called Average Up Time.
The Mean Time to Repair is the average duration of a downtime,
including the time until the repair, or maintenance,
people show up--
also called Average Downtime.
The Mean Time Between Failures-- the MTBF--
is the average duration of an up-down period.
Sometimes people confuse Mean Time to Fail
and Mean Time Between Failures because Mean Time to Repair
is often much less than Mean Time to Fail.
If a machine is unreliable, and its average operation
time is tau, its Mean Time to Fail is MTTF.
Its Mean Time to Repair is MTTR.
Then its maximum production rate, or capacity,
is 1 over tau times MTTF, over MTTF plus MTTR.
We saw this formula in one of the Markov process videos.
Then we assume that the up times and down times
are geometrically distributed.
Now we will show that this formula
is true without having to make that assumption,
although we will return to that assumption later.
This represents a timeline of events at a machine.
The green bars represent the periods when the machine is up,
and the red bars represent when its down.
The average production rate, while the machine is up,
is 1 over tau.
The average duration of an up period is MTTF.
So the average production during an up period
is MTTF divided by tau.
The average duration of an up-down period
is MTTF plus I'm MTTR.
The average production during the up-down period
is MTTF over tau because the production
during the down period is 0.
The average production rate is the average production rate
during an up-down period divided by the average length
of an up-down period.
Therefore, the average production rate
is MTTF over tau, over MTTF plus MTTR--
or 1 over tau times the fraction MTTF over MTTF plus MTTR.
That fraction-- MTTF over MTTF plus MTTR--
is e, the efficiency of the machine.
e is the fraction of time the machine is up.
e can be thought of as the production rate in units
of parts per operation time, or the actual production
rate divided by what the production rate would
be if the machine never failed.
e is a dimensionless quantity.
Now, we're going to be more specific.
We will assume that the machine has
geometric up and down times.
This is the same model we discussed during the Markov
process videos.
The assumption is that the operation time was constant.
Failure and repair times are geometrically distributed.
Whenever we analyze systems with machines
that have geometric up and down time,
we will treat the operation time as the time unit.
This will simplify notation.
As a consequence, MTTR MTTF will be measured in operation times.
p is the probability that a machine fails during any given
operation.
Then MTTF is equal to 1 over p.
r is the probability that M gets repaired during an operation
time when it's down.
Then MTTR is equal to 1 over r.
The average production rate of M,
and parts per operation time, is then
e, which is equal to r over r plus p.
Since we assume that the operation time is the time
unit, the production rate is the same
as the machine's efficiency.
I will be using those terms interchangeably
whenever I make the geometric up and down time assumption.
The capacity of a machine is its maximum possible production
rate.
The machine really has three capacities.
One, when it's up.
And remember that the time unit is the operation time,
so 1 means 1 part per operation time.
0, when it's down.
And r over r plus p, on the average.
We care about short-term capacity
when we're thinking about real time scheduling,
and we care about long-term capacity
when we're thinking about designing a manufacturing
system.