In this video, we will start a discussion of flow lines
with finite non-zero buffers.
The behavior of these lines is more
complex than that of lines with infinite or zero buffers.
In particular, the production rate
is a function of both the mean time
to repair and mean time to fail of the machines and not just
the machines efficiencies, which are functions
of the ratios of mean time to fail to mean time to repair.
The mathematics is also more complex.
For that reason, we will talk about two machine lines now,
and longer lines in the second part of the course.
The motivation for having buffers
is to increase the production rate beyond what the production
rate would be with zero buffers, but it comes with costs.
One cost is the in-process inventory, and also
the increased lead time that in process inventory leads to.
Second is the floor space that we have to dedicate to this.
And third is the material handling mechanism.
Let's compare the consequences of disruptions
in systems with different kinds of buffers.
A line with infinite buffers has delayed downstream propagation
of disruptions in the form of starvation
and no upstream propagation.
Zero buffers have essentially instantaneous propagation
of disruptions in both directions,
upstream and downstream.
Finite buffers have a delayed propagation in both directions,
and there's a new phenomenon which we call a blockage.
Machine, Mi, is blocked at time, t,
if buffer, Bi, is full at time, t.
Buffer, Bi, is the buffer downstream of a machine, Mi.
the difficulty with this is that no simple formula
for calculating production rate inventory levels or performance
measures exist.
To get around that there are various solutions.
One is simulation.
Simulation can be accurate, but it's statistical,
and it can be slowed for doing optimization with.
Analytical approximations, analytical
means that there are equations that can be solved
for the quantities we need.
We can get exact numerical solutions for short lines,
and a special case is that we can
get an exact analytical solution for two machine lines.
From now on, we're going to focus on two
machine finite buffer lines.
The parameters are P1, the probability
of machine one failing while doing an operation.
One over P1 is the mean time to fail of machine one.
R1 is the probability of machine one
getting repaired during an operation time when it is down.
P2 and R2 are similar for the second machine,
and N is the number of parts of the buffer can hold,
the buffer size.
The next four slides are going to show
graphs of N of T, the number of parts in the buffer of a two
machine line.
The parameters of each example are
chosen so the lines have different than hopefully
interesting behaviors.
In example one, both machines are the same
and the buffer is small.
Example two has the same machines as in example one,
but now the buffer is much larger.
Example three is the same as example two,
except that the first machine fails more often.
And example four is the reverse of example three.
It's the same as example two, except now the second machine
fails more often.
Here's the graph of example one.
The horizontal axis is time.
The vertical axis is the number of parts
in the buffer at each time.
The behavior of the buffer level is driven
by the states of the machines.
When the first machine is up and the second is down,
the buffer level increases.
When the first machine is down and the second is up,
the buffer level decreases.
When the machines are in the same state, both up
or both down, the buffer level stays constant.
We can't tell whether the machines
are both up or both down by looking at the graph.
When the buffer level zero, that is when the buffer is empty,
the first machine must be down and the second must be up.
The second one is start.
When the buffer level is 10, in this case, when the buffer is
full, the first machine must be up and the second must be down.
The first machine is blocked.
Note that many of the failures lead
to a blockage or starvation.
This is because the mean downtime of both machines
is 10, since R is equal to 0.1 for both.
Therefore, a large fraction of downtimes
will be greater than 10.
Keep in mind that the buffer size is 10.
So if the first machine fails and stays down
for 10 or more operation times, and the second machine
stays up, the buffer will become empty.
Similarly, if the second one fails and stays down
for more than 10 operations times,
and the first stays up, the buffer will become full.
Here's example two.
In this case, the buffer size is 100,
which is 10 times the mean downtimes of both machines.
The machines are the same as in example one.
As a consequence, starvations and blockages are much rarer.
Most downtimes are much less than the buffer size
when we measure downtimes and operation time.
A single failure rarely lasts long enough
to fill or empty the buffer.
Note that the scales on both the axes
are different from those of example one.
For the buffer to become empty, for example,
there must be a period starting with the buffer level
being 50, in which machine one is down more than 50 operation
times more than machine two is down.
This is rare.
Increasing the buffer size has the effect
of increasing the production rate,
because the fraction of the time the buffer is full or empty
decreases.
Increasing the buffer size also makes the average amount
of inventory increase.
Here's the graph of example three.
This example is similar to example two,
except machine one fails twice as often as machine two.
Machine one is the bottleneck.
This graphs looks similar to that of example two,
except that the buffer level rarely goes above 50.
During the period shown, the buffer
is often empty, but never full.
What would be the effect of increasing the buffer size?
If the marketing department told us
that we have to meet a significantly higher demand,
could we hope to meet it by increasing the buffer size?
Pause the video at this point if you
want to check your intuition.
My answer is coming next.
The answer is, of course not.
During the period of 10,000 operation times,
the buffer is never full.
If we ran the same simulation with the same sequence
of failures and repairs into the larger buffer,
we would see exactly the same buffer level
history, and therefore, exactly the same production rate
and average inventory.
To summarize, increasing the buffer size in this case
would not change the production rate.
But it would increase the cost of buffer space.
It would also have no effect on the average inventory.
Here's example four.
This example is the same as example three,
but the machines are switched.
Now machine two is the bottleneck.
The buffer quickly fills up, after that,
it stays close to full for much of the time.
It drops down to zero once, and it
goes below 50 far less time than it is above 50.
Let's consider the following situation.
Suppose the marketing department tells us
they need us to ramp up the production rate substantially.
We consider increasing the buffer size from 100 to 200.
What would be the effect on the production
rate and the average inventory if we did that?
Let's make a possibly unfair self-assessment quiz question.
Don't worry.
Your performance on this will not affect your course grade
in any way.
We're going to give you two multiple choice questions.
Please try to answer the questions for yourself
before advancing the video.
The video provides an answer, so stop the video
after the second question.
The first question is, what will the increase
do to the steady state production rate?
A, it will double it.
B, it will increase it substantially,
but less than double.
C, it will increase it, but only by a trivial amount.
D, it will have exactly zero effect.
And E, none of the above.
The second question is, what will happen
to the average inventory?
A, it will increase it by something very close to 100.
B, it will double it.
C, it will increase it substantially,
but less than double.
D, it will increase it, but only by a trivial amount.
E, it will have exactly zero effect.
And F, none of the above.
OK.
Pause the video.
Think about these questions.
The answer is coming next.
To answer these questions, we ran the simulation.
Here, we're seeing the results of the simulation
as they emerge.
This is a simulation of two cases.
One is just like example four.
The other is the same, but with a buffer size of 200.
Let's call the first one, example 4-100,
and the second one, 4-200.
The following three slides have static graphs of the simulation
over different time scales.
The initial buffer levels of both are 50,
and initially the states of both machines are up.
The machines go up and down at random.
To do this comparison experiment,
we've contrived to have almost the same sequence of failures
in repairs for both sets of machines.
The sequences differ slightly because of the operation
dependent failure assumption.
If the buffer of one of the lines is full,
but the buffer of the other one is not,
it's possible that the first machine
in the line with the non-full buffer might fail.
But the first machine in the line with the full buffer
will not.
This won't happen very often, because the buffers are
almost always full and non-full at the same time.
In this graph, the purple line is the number
of parts in the buffer, 4-100.
The green line represents the level of the buffer in 4-200.
The sample paths of both simulations
are exactly the same until the buffer
levels of both reach 100.
That's why you see only one line between time 0 and time 228.
As a consequence, the production rates and average inventories
of both lines are exactly the same between time 0 and 228.
At time 228, however, the buffer in example 4-100
becomes full, and then stays full, or close to full
for a long time.
The reason for this is that, when the buffer level in 4-100
reaches 100, and machine 2 is down, machine one is blocked,
and no part enters the buffer.
On the other hand, the buffer in 4-200
keeps growing until time 240.
Machine one is not blocked in 4-200 at this time,
so parts are allowed to go in, and they go into the buffer.
There brief downtimes of machine one
and machine two at 240 and 242.
Then both machines are up until time 254.
The buffer in 4-100 drops down to 99
because of some uninteresting details about the buffer model,
and stays constant.
The buffer level of 4-200 is constant at 111.
Between this time and time 479, a pattern emerges.
When machine one is down, and machine two is up,
both buffer levels fall.
If the buffer level in 4-100 is below 100,
the two graphs move in parallel.
If the buffer level in 4-100 is equal to 100, it stays at 100,
and the leveling 4-200 rises.
This kind of behavior persists, with both buffers
increasing and decreasing until time 479.
Until that time, whenever machine two is up,
the output processes of both lines are the same.
At time 479 both buffers are full.
After this, the amount of space in the buffers of the lines
are the same, and they will stay the same
as long as the buffer in 4-100 is not empty.
That is the quantity 200 minus N200 of T
will be equal to the quantity 100 minus N100 of t.
As a consequence, the output processes of both lines
are the same.
The buffer in 4-100 reaches zero for the first time
at time 43,650, and that is the first time the output
processes of the lines differ.
That buffer stays empty for only a short time.
This reflects the fact that the production rate of the two
lines will differ, but only by a small amount.
For one run of the simulation of 500,000 to operation times,
we found that the buffer 4-100 was empty for 417 time steps,
and the buffer in 4-200 was never empty at all.
Consequently, line 4-200 produced
417 more parts than 4-100 did.
As a consequence, the production rate of line 4-200 was 0.8317,
and that of 4-100 was 0.8309, a very small difference.
On the other hand, the average inventory in 4-100
was 83.41 parts, and that of 4-200
was 183.39 parts, a difference of almost 100 parts.
Therefore, if this simulation is typical,
and I think it is, you get an unofficial A if you decided
that the answer to the first question
was C. It will increase the production rate,
but only by a trivial amount, and that the answer
to the second was A, the buffer level
will increase by something very close to, and less than 100.