Now, we're going to analyze the behavior of the M/M/1 queue
by Markov process modeling as we have described
in general terms earlier.
The transition graph is shown here.
In this graph, the circles, as usual,
represent the states of the system,
which are the number of people in the queue at any time.
The arrows, as usual, represent the transitions.
And the Greek letters on them represent the rates.
Lambda is the rate of arrivals.
So the rate at which the queue length will increase is lambda.
Mu is the rate of service or departures.
So the rate at which the queue length decreases is mu.
There's an infinite stage space.
So n can go to infinity.
This is because we've assumed an infinite waiting room.
This means that they are going to be
an infinite number of equations and an infinite number
of unknowns to solve.
This means there will be an infinite number of equations
to solve for an infinite number of unknowns.
The state is the event that there's
a given number of people in the queue at any time.
All the states are connected with the neighboring states
in the same way, except 0.
0 is connected to only one other state.
When n equals 0, n cannot decrease.
Also can't be reached from a state
with fewer parts or customers.
This means that all the transition equations
will look the same, except for the equation for state 0.
So let's define pi of n, t to be the probability
that there are n parts in the system at time t.
Then for n greater than 0, we have this transition equation.
So the probability of the system is in state n
at time t plus delta t is the probability that it was
in state n minus 1 at time t.
And there was an arrival plus the probability
that it was in state n plus 1 at time t.
And there was a departure plus the probability
that the system was in state n at time t.
And there was neither an arrival nor a departure.
So the first term is pi of n minus 1, t, lambda delta t.
Lambda delta t is the probability
that there's an arrival between t and t plus delta t.
And the other terms are interpreted similarly.
Here's the special equation for n equals 0.
The way that you can get to 0 at time t plus delta t
is either from 1 at time t with a departure
or 0 at time t with no arrival.
So let's analyze these equations by turning them
into differential equations.
Let's analyze these equations by turning them
In the first one, we'll subtract pi of n, t from both sides
and then divide both sides by delta t.
In the second one, we're going to subtract pi of 0,
t from both sides and divide both sides by delta t.
So the first equation becomes this, the derivative
of the probability over time of pi of n,
t given by the right-hand side.
And the special case for n equals
0 is given by this equation.
If a steady state distribution exists,
it satisfies these equations which
are the same as the ones above where
the derivatives are set to 0.
Why do I say "if a steady state distribution exists?"
Well, let's consider a couple of cases.
Suppose that it takes 10 minutes on the average for the server
to take care of each customer.
If customers arrive once an hour, there's no problem.
The server will be idle for most of the time.
Most of the time, there'll be no more
than a handful of customers.
If we watch the system for a long time,
there will be more than, say, 30 customers in the system
for very, very infrequently.
On the other hand, suppose customers
arrive once every five minutes.
It takes 10 minutes on the average to serve a customer.
So for every customer that departs,
two arrive on the average.
Consequently, the number of customers in the system
grows by one every 10 minutes on the average.
This is not a system in steady state.
The mean of the probability distribution changes over time.
In this simulation, the arrival rate exceeds the service rate.
The graph is drawn a bit differently because we
know what's going to happen.
The number of people in the queue
is going to grow very large over time.
So we have a larger vertical scale.
In addition, we know the basic behavior.
So the average number in the queue is not a constant,
but it's something which is increasing over time.
So you can see that the simulation graph roughly
tracks the average.
But it's not exactly on top of it.
As you know, there's a lot of randomness in the system.
So this shows that you need to have the arrival rate less
than the service rate.
As we said earlier, we're defining rho as lambda over mu.
The equations on the previous slide
are satisfied by this equation, pi of n
equals 1 minus rho times rho to the n for n greater than
or equal to 0.
If rho is less than 1--
now you can see immediately that if rho is greater than one,
that doesn't make any sense.
We get negative probabilities.
And we're not allowed to have negative probabilities.
From this, we can calculate the average number of parts
in the system, which is rho over 1 minus rho,
or lambda over mu minus lambda.
From this, you can see that if lambda equals 0,
then rho equals 0.
And the number of people in the system are going to be 0.
On the other hand, if lambda approaches mu,
then rho approaches 1 and n bar approaches infinity.
So mu is the upper bound for lambda to make any sense.
In other words, for this system, mu
is the capacity, the maximum rate of flow
that the system can handle.
Rho is called the utilization of the system
because rho represents the fraction of time
that the system is busy.
In the next set of slides, we're going
to examine this relationship and look
at the qualitative behavior that it implies
about the behavior of a queuing system,
and see if we can extract some lessons about how
to manage your factory.