In the set of slides, we examined several graphs
to look at the sensitivity of the optimal inventory
to the parameters of the news vendor problem.
We have a set of base values for all the parameters.
We vary the parameters one at a time
to see how x star changes with them.
There are two base cases and we'll switch back and forth
between them.
In example one, the sale price of the papers is $1.
And the price the vendor pays to the publisher
is $0.25, for each paper.
The salvage price is zero.
The mean demand is 100.
And the standard deviation demand
is 10 newspapers in a day.
An example to all the parameters are the same
except the price that the vendor pays to the publisher is $0.75.
We assume that the demand is distributed normally.
This assumption gets us into a little trouble in some cases,
as we will discuss shortly.
This kind of exercise is useful for at least three reasons.
First, we see if the behavior makes sense intuitively,
that is, if it seems reasonable.
If it does, great.
If it doesn't, we have to examine both the model
and our intuition.
If we can't find any problems in the model of the analysis,
then we have to ask ourselves if our intuition is correct
and think hard about what the graphs tell us.
Second, we may not have any intuition
at all about the problem we are considering.
In that case, if the model seems correct
we can develop new intuition.
Third, it helps us to find limitations of the model
or of the analysis.
In this graph, the horizontal axis is the sale price r.
And the vertical axis is the optimal purchase amount, x
star.
Other than r, all the parameters are
fixed that the values at the top of the slide.
We see that x star increases monotonically in r.
This makes sense given the assumption of the problem.
The higher the sale price for the papers
the more the vendor should be willing to buy
from the publisher.
In fact, x star would continue to increase to infinity
as r increases to infinity.
However, this reveals some of the limitations of the problem
formulation.
The model has no mechanism for varying the demand
as a function of the sale price.
We assume that mu and sigma are fixed.
Clearly if the price of the newspaper rose to $100,
sales would drop off.
The only way to allow the demand to be a function of the sale
price in a model like this would be
to make the mean and possibly the standard deviation
of the demand functions of the price, r.
But that would raise another question, exactly how does
the demand depend on the price?
That does not make the model useless.
Its behavior as a function of r is reasonable
given the assumptions.
This gives us some confidence that its behavior
as a function of other parameters is also reasonable.
Also, the demand probably changes
very little over a limited range of r.
In that case, the model would be accurate.
And marketers have tools for predicting demand changes
for small changes in price.
These tools could be incorporated in the model.
One more observation about this graph,
x star rises very steeply in the neighborhood of r equals $0.25.
This is because the sale price r, in this range,
is only slightly greater than the cost, c, which is $0.25.
For example, suppose the sale price were $0.26,
then the vendor would make one penny for each paper sold
and would lose $0.25 for each paper unsold.
That is, for every unsold paper on a bad day,
the vendor loses the profit made by selling
25 papers on a good day.
Consequently, there is great incentive to be cautious
and that keeps x star low.
As the sale price increases, the number
of papers sold on a good day for every paper unsold on a bad day
decreases rapidly at first and then more slowly
as r increases.
The vendor can be less cautious.
That is, when r is not to a much greater than c, x
star increases rapidly with r.
This graph is also x star versus r.
The only difference is that here, is that the publisher
price here is $0.75.
It looks like the same graph as the previous shifted
on the horizontal axis.
In this graph, we look at the effect of different values
of c on x star.
The horizontal axis is c.
r and all the other parameters are held constant.
c is the discounted price that the vendor pays
the publisher for the papers.
When c is very small, the vendor takes
on very little risk for each paper bought
from the publisher.
Consequently, the vendor is willing to buy a lot of papers.
As the price, c, goes to zero, x star goes to infinity.
On the other hand, when c approaches r,
there is very little profit in the sale of each paper
and a lot of loss for each paper not sold.
Consequently, there is little incentive for the vendor
to invest in very many papers.
As c goes to r, x star goes to zero.
This graph shows the effect of s, the salvage price on x star.
s equals zero in all the other cases but it's non-zero here.
x star increases with s, because larger s
means that there's less risk.
As s approaches c, the risk disappears.
If s were equal to c, the price that the vendor pays
the publisher for newspapers, it would
mean that the vendor could do no worse than breaking even.
Consequently, as s approaches c, x star approaches infinity.
Here again, we have x star versus s.
In this case, c equals $0.75.
The graph is similar to the previous one.
In this graph, we vary mu and look at x star.
We will discuss shortly why this graph looks linear.
It is linear, but the graph is actually not quite right.
We'll discuss that as well.
See if you can figure out what the problem is, if you can,
before you look at slides 41 to 44,
which is where we discuss this.
It shows that the optimal amount to buy from the publisher
increases with the mean of the demand.
This makes sense.
The more papers people want to buy,
the more the vendor should provide.
This graph is very similar.
It's also x star versus mu.
This times c is $0.75 whereas c was
equal to $0.25 in the previous graph.
In this graph, we consider the effect
of the standard deviation of demand on x star.
Similarly, the graph is linear but really it shouldn't be.
And we'll explain why shortly.
In this graph, the publisher's price to the vendor
is $0.25 per paper.
This graph shows that as the standard deviation
of the demand increases, the more papers the vendor
should buy.
But before we develop an intuitive explanation of this,
we should look at the next graph.
Here we also have x star versus sigma.
The graph is also linear as it was in the previous
but it is not similar to the previous one,
Here, c equals $0.75.
This star suggests that x star decreases
with the standard deviation of demand.
Why is this different from the previous one?
To understand why x star is linear in mu and sigma,
lets recall what x star is.
It's the solution to this equation.
x star is the solution to this equation, the distribution
function evaluated x star is equal to r
minus c over r minus s.
Let's assume that the demand is normal, with means--
Let's assume that the demand is normally
distributed with parameters mu and sigma,
then for any demand, w, the distribution function
evaluated at w is simply the standard normal evaluated
at w minus mu over sigma.
Therefore the standard normal evaluated at x star minus mu
over sigma, is equal to r minus c over r minus s.
Or we can write it this way by just inverting
the standard normal.
And finally, this becomes x star equals
mu plus sigma times the inverse of
the standard normal evaluated at r minus c over r minus s.
So this explains why x star is linear in mu and sigma.
Should x star actually be linear in mu and sigma?
The answer is yes and no.
Yes if we accept the assumption that the demand is normal.
But no in reality, because the demand cannot be normal.
It cannot be normal because the demand cannot be negative.
In fact, the demand is more realistically modeled
as a truncated normal.
So then for what values of mu and sigma
is x star closest to linear in mu and sigma.
The answer is when mu is much greater than sigma.
If so, the normal distribution predicts
a very small probability for w being negative.
Therefore, the normal is a good approximation
for the truncated normal in that range.
Another question that arises from the graphs
is, what determines whether x star increases or decreases
in sigma.
To answer that, note that the standard normal--
note that the inverse of the standard normal
is positive if it's evaluated at a quantity which
is greater than 0.5.
And it's negative if it's evaluated at a quantity which
is less than 0.5.
Well, since x is equal to mu plus sigma
times the standard normal inverse of r
minus c over r minus s, then x star
must increase with sigma if r minus c over r minus s
is greater than 0.5, and decrease with sigma
if r minus c over r minus s is less than 0.5.
The next question is, can we extend this strategy
to manage inventory in other settings?
Specifically suppose the stock remaining at the end of the day
can be used in the future.
In other words, we don't have a news vendor problem,
we have a true inventory problem.
Because is the result that we found of the news vendor
problem suggests a possible heuristic extension.
Heuristic here means it seems like a pretty good idea
but we don't have a rigorous proof that it really is.
Well, the answer is yes.
Build enough inventory to satisfy demand
100K% of the time for some k, where
k is given by that fraction.
Compare this with a discussion on slide 28.