OK, we'll now look at some discrete time models.
We're going to start with the geometric distribution.
We already discussed the geometric distribution.
We're now going to show how it relates to the simplest
possible Markov chain.
So here's a very, very simple graph, only two states.
The system starts in state one.
Somebody flips a bias coin or spins a spinner.
If it shows heads with probability p,
the system goes to 0.
If not it stays at 1.
Using the results that we've already seen,
we can calculate the probability that the system is
in state one or state two at any time greater than
or equal to 1.
So p is the conditional probability
that the system is in state 0 at time t
plus 1, given that it's in state 0 at time t.
Then formally little p is the probability
that alpha of t plus 1 equals 0 given alpha of t
equals 1, where alpha represents the state of the system.
Let pi of alpha comma t be the probability of being
in state alpha at time t.
Then we have this transition equation.
So what does this say?
It says that pi of 0t plus 1, that's
the probability of the system being in state 0
at time t plus 1, the probability
of finding the system in state 0 at time t plus 1
is equal to the sum of 2 terms.
The first one is the probability that we went from 1 to 0.
So it's the probability of being in state 0 at time t
plus 1, given that it was in state 1 at time t,
times the probability it was in state 1 at time t.
Plus the second term, which is the probability
of going from state 0 to state 0 in one time step.
That's the probability that the state is 0 at time t
plus delta-t given that it was 0 at time t,
times the probability was 0 in time t.
Well, the probability of being in state 0 at time t plus 1,
given that it was in state 1 at time t is just p.
That equation becomes the first equation of the pair
that I've written here.
That first transition probability,
p of alpha t plus 1 equals 0 given alpha of t
equals 1 is just lower-case p.
The second, the probability of going
from 0 to 0, that probability is just 1.
Once you're in 0, you don't leave 0.
So the first equation is just the transition equation
for state 0.
The second equation, derived similarly,
is the transition equation for state 1.
The probability of being in state 1 at time t plus 1
is equal to the probability of being in state 1
at time t times the probability of not leaving state 1, which
is just 1 minus t.
And the probability of going from 0 to 1 is 0.
So these are the two transition equations.
And of course there's the normalization equation pi
of one comma t plus pi of 0 comma t equals 1.
So let's assume that pi of 1 comma 0
equals 1-- that is that with probability 1
the system is in state 1.
We can solve those equations and we get pi of 0 comma t
equals 1 minus 1 minus p to the t.
And pi of one comma t is just 1 minus p to the t.
So clearly those two add up to 1.
Normally we don't try to calculate
time-varying solutions of transition equations.
For more complex systems this is a very hard calculation.
So here are the graphs of pi 0 comma t and pi 1 comma t.
Notice that we're approaching a steady state.
As t gets larger and larger, both of those probabilities
approach finite values.
Pi 1 comma t approaches 0, and pi 0 comma t approaches 1.
We've shown that the probability that the state goes from 1 to 0
at time t is just p of t equals 1 minus p
to the t minus 1 times p.
The mean time to go from 1 to 0 is then
t-bar which is the sum of tp of t,
t going from 1 to infinity, which is the sum of t times
1 minus p to the t minus 1 times p sum from 1 to infinity.
It's not hard to show that t-bar is simply 1 over p.
So the average time to go from state 1 to state 0
is the inverse of that transition probability.
So if the transition probability of leaving state 1
and going as they 0 is 0.1 in a given step,
then the average time to go from 1 to 0 is 10.
The next example is the unreliable machine.
So this is a generalization of the geometric process.
Because now the system can go from 1 to 0 and 0 to 1.
This is the simplest model of an unreliable machine where
state 1 means the machine is working
and state 0 means that the machine is under repair.
We're making lots of simplifying assumptions in this model.
For example, there are always parts available for the machine
to work on, and there's always space
to put the parts after the operation.
Another assumption is that when the machine is
operational or up, it produces one part per time unit.
In other words, we use the operation time
as the time unit, and we assume it is constant.
During a time unit when the machine is working on a part,
it will fail with probability p and go to state 0.
From the analysis of the previous model,
the time from when it arrives at state 1
to when it goes to state 0 is geometrically
distributed with parameter p.
The average time between arriving at state 1
and leaving state 1 is 1 over p.
When the machine is in state 0, it
is not operational and is undergoing a repair
or it's down.
We assume that the probability that that repair is
completed in a time unit is r.
The average time it takes to complete the repair as 1
over r.
The probability distribution satisfies these two equations.
It's not hard to show that these two expressions are
the solutions of those equations.
One thing you should notice about them
is that they both involve 1 minus p minus r to the t.
Since p and r both between 0 and 1,
that quantity is between minus 1 and plus 1.
When we raise it to the power t as t gets large,
that quantity gets smaller and smaller.
So eventually both probabilities approach limits.
Those limits are pi of 0 comma t, which
is the probability that the machine is down approaches
p over r plus p and pi of 1 comma t approaches
r over r plus p.
These expressions from pi 0 and pi 1 and the limit
are exactly the solutions of the steady-state transition
equations which are written below.
If a machine makes one part per time unit
when it's operational, it's average production rate is just
pi of 1, the probability that it's
in state 1, which we've said is r over r plus p.
This quantity is called the efficiency of the machine.
If the machine makes one part per time unit
when it's operational, it's average production rate
is 1 over tau times are r over r plus p, or 1 over tau times e.
We can also write that e is equal to MTTF over MTTF
plus MTTR, where MTTF is the mean time to fail,
and MTTR is the mean time to repair.
We will show later that this formula does not
depend on the assumption of geometric up times
and geometric down times.