Consider a special case of the system
that we've been discussing, in which alpha i
equals 0 for all nodes i.
That means that there's nothing from the outside world that
enters the system.
p i 0 equals 0 for all nodes, and that means
that nothing exits the system.
In that case, since nothing is entering
and nothing is departing from the system,
the number of items in the network is constant.
So the sum of the n i's of t is equal to n, a constant,
for all t.
The system is closed because nothing gets in or gets out.
This model is useful in analyzing two
kinds of manufacturing systems.
The first is those in which there
are a limited number of pallets or fixtures
to carry parts throughout the system.
Parts enter and leave, but the number
of fixtures in the system stays constant.
As we'll see, the performance of the system
depends on the number of fixtures.
If there are too few, performance suffers.
Think about the food court example,
and assume there are only a finite number of trays
shared by all the vendors.
If there are only two trays, to be extreme,
all the vendors would go out of business very soon.
Ideally, there would be enough trays
so that it would be very rare for a customer not to have one.
Food court trays are cheap, but fixtures in a factory
can be expensive.
There's a trade-off between the financial benefit
of each fixture and its cost.
The benefit from increasing the number of fixtures
is increased production rate.
But there's an upper bound to the production
rate, which is reached asymptotically
as the number of fixtures is increased.
On the other hand, the cost of the fixtures
is linear in the number of fixtures.
So there's no upper bound to the cost of fixtures.
Second, is where there are virtual fixtures.
A card can be attached to each part that enters this system.
The part travels with the card, which is then
detached when the part leaves.
The card is then recycled for another part entering.
Such cards are called kanbans.
Kanban is a Japanese word.
The kanban approach originated with the Toyota production
system.
The number of cards is finite.
They never leave the system, and no new ones come in.
The closed queueing network model
may be useful for predicting performance.
Cards are not expensive, but inventory is.
The number of parts in the system
is always less than or equal to the number of cards,
so the number of cards regulates the inventory.
The number of cards is chosen so that the factory meets
its production rate requirement with the least
amount of inventory.
The mathematics is a little different
here from in the more general case.
That's because lambda equals p lambda does not
have a unique solution.
This means that a different solution approach is
needed to analyze the system.
That solution is used in the example that follows.
A flexible manufacturing system is an automated system
that is capable of operating on a variety of different part
types.
It includes a set of machines, a transportation
system, a control system for dispatching parts to machines.
Different part types require different tools or fixtures
for metal cutting, or different temperatures for ovens,
or different chemicals or paints,
or other features needed for specific products.
Flexibility refers to the variety of different tools,
fixtures, chemicals, et cetera that the system
provides for operations on different part types.
Most importantly, it also refers to the time
it takes to change a machine from being set up
for one operation on a part type to an operation on another.
The less time, the more flexible.
There are many issues in the design of such systems.
Many of them are physical, such as the nature
of the machines, the mechanical problems of transportation
in fixed rings, and so forth.
And we will not be dealing with them here.
The system's design issues include
determining what part type should be manufactured
at the same time in the same FMS,
designing the system for a given set of part types
and the demands for those part types,
and designing the system for possible future part types.
Operation issues include determining
which parts to dispatch to which machines,
and when to dispatch them.
In the next set of slides, we describe
a model of a flexible manufacturing system.
Like all models, it's an approximation of reality,
and is appropriate for a limited set of uses.
That is, it can be helpful for making some design
decisions, but not all.
This model is intended to help make some early design
decisions, and in making preliminary evaluations
of some proposed designs.
Specifically, the purpose of this model
is to estimate the capacity, or the maximum production rate,
of a proposed FMS design.
This capacity is a function of the operation
times of the machines, the number of pallets required,
the mix of parts, and the speed of the transportation system.
It can also assist in estimating the amount
of in-process inventory the system
will contain on the average.
However, it does not take into account everything that's
important.
It does not include the changeover times of a machine
from one part type to another.
It assumes that the changeover times are all 0.
While it accounts for the total number of pallets,
it does not account for the possibility
that different parts might require different pallets.
It assumes infinite storage space.
Consequently, this model is useful
for the evaluation of early rough designs,
and for providing preliminary estimates of required machines
and transportation speeds, the number of pallets,
and the work-in-process inventory.
Systems designers can then use those preliminary estimates
to create a more detailed design.
At that point, they must use a more detailed model, preferably
a simulation--
probably a simulation-- to make estimates of the performance
of the system.
In this model, there's a load-unload station,
a transportation system, and n minus 1 machines.
The transportation system is treated as the n-th machine.
There are n pallets.
Part types are not distinguished.
Instead, the set of parts is treated as a single homogeneous
population.
Instead of modeling the detailed routing
through the system of each part type,
it sends parts to each machine randomly,
in the proportions determined by the processing
requirements of the set of parts that will be produced.
Parts enter the system at the load-unload station.
There, they are attached to pallets
and sent to the transportation system.
They wait in a queue for the transportation system
to bring them to one of the machines.
The probability that a part goes to machine i is q i.
The part goes to the load-unload station with probability qM.
So recall the definition of pij.
piM equals 1 means that parts go to the transportation station
after receiving an operation at a workstation.
pMj equals qj is the probability that when
a part leaves the transportation system, it goes to station j.
pij equals 0 means that no part goes directly
from one machine to another.
Parts go from machine to transportation system
to machine.
The service rate at station i is mu i.
That means the average operation time for a part at station i
is 1 over mu i.
The input data is the set of numbers that
describes a particular case.
We've already described M, N, qj, and mu j.
One more thing is sj.
We're analyzing multiple machines at each station,
and those queues are analyzed with the M/M/s model
that we described earlier.
The output data, the production rate, the average time a part
spends in the system, and the utilization
per machine of station j is the information
that we're trying to get out of the model.
These are the performance measures.
In the following graphs, these are the default values
of all the parameters.
We will vary one parameter at a time,
and see the effect of that variable
on some of the performance measures.
In the first graph, the horizontal axis
is the number of pallets, N. The vertical axis is the production
rate.
P increases monotonically with N,
and reaches an upper limit asymptotically.
We will see similar graphs later for other kinds of systems.
It has this shape because of the infinite buffer assumption.
In reality, if the storage space were limited,
the production rate would increase and then
start to decrease when the number of pallets
gets very large.
This will happen because of blocking and traffic congestion
in the system.
In this graph, the horizontal axis
is still the number of pallets.
The vertical axis is now the average time
a part spends in the system.
The graph is monotonically increasing.
As N increases, the graph looks more and more
like a straight line, and goes to infinity
as the number of pallets goes to infinity.
As the number of pallets increases,
the queues at some or all of the stations
increase without limit.
This causes parts to have to wait longer at some queues.
So the total average time in the system increases.
Again, it has this shape because of the infinite buffer
assumption.
If buffers were finite, there would
be an upper bound to the waiting time for the parts
that get into the system, but some parts would not get in,
or would have to wait in a very long queue outside the system.
In this graph, the horizontal axis
is still the number of pallets, N.
The vertical axis is the utilization of the stations.
All graphs are monotonically increasing.
This is because as the number of pallets grows,
the fraction of time that a station has an empty queue
decreases.
As a consequence, the utilization increases.
The ratios of the utilizations are constant.
That is because the processing needs of each part
stays constant no matter how many pallets there are.
All the graphs have asymptotes.
The upper limit for station 2 is 1, or 100% utilization,
and the upper limits for all the others are less.
Why is that?
The reason is that the parts need to go to station 2
more often than the other stations,
or they need to spend more time there.
As N increases, the only limit on the utilizations
of the stations is 100%.
Station 2 reaches that limit because it's
the most highly utilized.
This means that as N increases, there
will be a longer and longer queue at station 2,
and parts will spend increasing amounts of time there.
Since the utilizations of all the other queues
are less than 1, their queues will approach the M/M/s
steady state performance.
Almost all the time in the graph in the previous slide
is spent waiting in the queue for station 2.
Now, the horizontal axis is the operation time of station 2.
The vertical axis is the utilization
of all the stations.
The utilization of station 2 is increasing,
and the utilizations of all the others are decreasing.
When station 2 is very fast--
that is, when its operation time is very short--
it can satisfy the needs of all the parts
with very little of its time.
Consequently, it goes to 0.
This allows the system to produce at a higher rate,
as we will see in the next slide.
Consequently, the other machines have more work to do,
so their utilizations are high.
As station 2 gets slower, it needs more time
to work on the parts, so it's busy more of the time,
and, therefore, its utilization goes up.
This reduces the rate at which it can do its work,
so that the production rate goes down.
This causes the other machines to have less work,
so their utilizations go down.
When station 2 is very slow, it's
the limiting factor on the production rate,
as the next graph shows.
As a consequence, its utilization approaches 100%.
On this graph, the horizontal axis
is still the operation time of station 2.
The vertical axis is the production rate of the system.
This graph is monotonically decreasing.
As station 2's operation time increases,
its production rate goes down, and this reduces the production
rate of the system as a whole.
When its operation time is close to 0,
the production rate of the system does not go to infinity.
This is because a different station
becomes the limiting factor on the production rate.
Again, on this graph, the horizontal axis
is the operation time of station 2.
The vertical axis is the average time
a part spends in the system.
As station 2 gets slower, we've seen
that its utilization goes up.
This causes the waiting time in its queue to increase.
When the utilization approaches 100%,
the waiting time in its queue goes to infinity,
so the average waiting time in the system goes to infinity,
as well.