The first week of this course is devoted
to an overview of manufacturing systems engineering.
We'll start off with a case that illustrates some of the issues.
Inkjet printers were introduced in 1993,
they were much better than the dot matrix printers that were
all that was available before.
They had much better print quality,
they could print graphics as well as text,
and they were much faster.
The demand for inkjet printers was large and it grew rapidly.
Market share is very important to companies
when new technology is introduced.
Customers are thought to have brand loyalty.
Once they get accustomed to one brand of a product
they stay with that brand when they replaced that product
with a new model.
In addition, printer customers don't just buy printers,
they also buy ink cartridges.
This is also a lucrative market.
Consequently, companies are often
willing to forego initial profits for greater profits
later.
Manufacturers could sell all they could produce.
Demand was much greater than production capacity.
Hewlett-Packard was designing and producing its printers
in Vancouver, Washington near Portland, Oregon.
Their initial production was done manually.
They decided to increase their printer production rate.
In deciding how to increase their production rate,
they had to satisfy certain constraints.
First constraint was that they had to keep quality
at a high level.
Quality does not just refer to the way printed pages look,
it also refers to the reliability of the product.
The printers have to last long enough to satisfy customers.
It was not enough to increase production rate
to keep up with demand.
To increase market share they had to increase production
at a greater rate than demand.
Their production target was 300,000 printers per month.
The capacity with existing manual assembly
was only 200,000 printers per month.
In addition, they also had to meet profit and revenue
targets.
To increase market share however,
they had to keep costs low to attract customers.
Keeping costs low is also necessary for profitability.
They wanted to have a stable workforce,
they did not want to have to hire people
when demand was high and then lay them off
when demand dropped.
HP invested $25 million in Eclipse, a new system
for automated assembly of the print engine.
This is a diagram of the whole production process.
Raw materials are fed into the mechanical assembly
cell, which we're going to focus on-- the Eclipse.
The completed print engine went into a storage buffer,
and from there it went to final assembly
with the rest of the printer, and then
to packaging and shipping.
Altogether, two of these Eclipse systems were installed.
This is a representation of the Eclipse automated assembly
system.
There are about 100 steps in the manufacturing process.
It was a main loop and several sub-assembly lines feeding it.
The base was assembled in the first sub-assembly line
and additional sub-assemblies were added to it later.
The main loop had 30 workstations.
When the base entered the main loop,
it was attached to a pallet which would carry it
through the assembly process.
This reduced possible damage to the product
from being clamped at each station.
Each such clamping risks damage.
Clamping the pallet causes no damage to the product.
When the assembly process was complete,
the engine was detached from the pallet
and then sent to a storage area to await
final assembly of the printer.
The empty pallet was sent back to the first assembly station
to get a new base to carry into the main loop.
At the time when this was all happening,
the American industry consensus was
that inventory was bad and should be eliminated.
As a consequence, the system was designed with very little room
for inventory.
As we will see, inventory is a necessary evil
if there's variability in the manufacturing process.
And there's always variability in the manufacturing process.
Some assumptions were made about the system.
Efficiency is the fraction of time
that machines are available for production--
not needing or undergoing repair or maintenance
or any other activity like that.
We'll describe that in more detail later.
The operation times at each station
were estimated to be nine seconds and constant.
Consequently, the total production rate
was estimated to be about 370,000 units per month.
But after the first two stations were installed,
data was collected and it was found that efficiency
was less than 99%.
Operation times were variable, often
greater than nine seconds.
In that case, actual production would
be about 125,000 units per month a very disappointing result.
They then face the problem--
how to modify the system to increase production rate?
And how to make the changes happen in a very short time?
The reason for the drastically reduced production
is the effect that the failure of one machine
has on all the others.
In this animation, the third sub-assembly line fails.
While it is out of action, the upstream part of the main line
keeps operating for a short time.
But the parts accumulate on the transportation system.
They create a traffic jam and all of the upstream machines
have to stop because they have nowhere to put their completed
parts, they are blocked.
At the same time, the parts that were downstream of the failed
machine are processed until they leave the system.
At that point, the machines downstream
of the failed machine have nothing to work on.
And so they have to stop, they're starved.
When the failed machines are repaired production resumes.
But perfectly operational machines
were forced to be idle because of the failure of one machine.
This is a loss of productive capacity.
Simulation is a modeling technique
for predicting performance of a complex system.
HP tried to analyze the system by simulation.
They consulted a vendor but the project
appeared to be too large and complex to produce
useful results in time to effect the system design.
This was because they tried to include
too much detail in the model.
Some conceivable changes were out of bounds,
they could not add labor and they could not
redesign the machines.
A visiting researcher proposed a feasible change--
adding a small amount of buffer space within the Eclipse.
Here's a graph that shows the relationship between buffer
space, N, and production space, P.
The horizontal axis is buffer space,
the vertical axis is the production rate.
The graph shows that when there's very little buffer
space, adding a little can increase production rate
by a lot.
This is not true when there there's a lot of buffer space
already.
The underlying design and analysis tools
will be described in the second part of this course.
Here's a diagram of the modified system.
There's an empty pallet buffer, there's
work in process space between some assembly
lines and the main line, there's work
in process space on the main line,
and the buffer sizes were large enough
to hold about 30 minutes worth of material.
This is a small multiple of the mean time
to repair of the machines.
30 minutes represents about 200 parts.
Here's the old system and the new system side by side,
you can see the difference.
When this was implemented, it led
to increased factory capacity to over 200,000 units per month.
The increased space on the system
is what allowed the increase in production rate.
Now, if a machine fails more time
must elapse before the upstream traffic jam occurs.
This allows the upstream machines
to work longer before they are blocked.
Similarly, if there are more ports downstream
of the failure, the downstream machines
can process more parts before they're starved.
Consequently, less productive time
is lost due to the single failure.
The capital cost of the changes was about $1,400,000.
The payoff was great, the incremental revenues
were about $280 million.
The labor productivity increased by about 50%.
This was successful because there was early intervention--
that is the analysis was done before too much of the system
was built and already in place.
The rapid response was possible because much
of the relevant research work had already been done.
The HP managers were quite flexible,
possibly because of the crisis they were facing.
The new analysis tool was fast, easy to use,
and was at the right level of detail.