In this set of slides, we're going
to talk about queueing theory, some elementary models.
Before we do that, though, we should
talk about the Poisson process, which
is going to be used in that.
Imagine a process that repeats over and over again
and it happens at random times.
So the first time it happens is at time T1, which is here.
The next time is a time T1 plus T2, which is here, and so on.
So the time between the events is T1, T2, T3, T4,
and so forth.
What we're interested in is counting
the number of events that have happened up to a certain time.
So at this time, the number of events that occurred is zero.
At this time, exactly one event occurred.
At this time, we have three events have occurred.
And after this there would be four times.
So to be formal about it, we're going to say Ti--
i equals 1, 2, 3, and so forth-- are
a set of independent exponentially distributed
random variables with parameter lambda.
Each random variable may represent
the time between occurrences of a repeating event.
The kinds of events that we're going to be mostly talking
about we're going to call customer arrivals at a queue
at a line waiting for service.
But there's also clicks of a Geiger counter
and lots of other examples.
The time required for n such events is the summation from i
equals 1 to n of Ti.
So for example, that's what this time is,
T1 plus T2 plus T3 plus T4.
So informally, the number we're interested in,
the Poisson process, is N of t.
That's the number of events that occur between 0 and T.
Formally, we'll define it this way.
N of t is equal to 0 if T1 is greater than t.
That is, the time of the first event is greater than t.
And it's n such that the sum up to n is less than t
and the sum up to n plus 1 is greater than t.
So then N of t is called a Poisson process
with parameter lambda.
Here's a graphical view of the way the Poisson process looks.
The horizontal axis is time and the vertical axis
is N of t, which is the cumulative number of events
that have happened between 0 and t.
And you can see that it looks like a step function,
but with random steps.
Each step, the vertical is always 1.
But the horizontal is random.
OK, so let's talk about a queuing system.
A queuing system consists of a server that
provides some kind of service that takes time,
let's say the customers that arrive
at different times in an area for the customers to wait in.
Queuing theory is the mathematical theory
of such systems.
Its main purpose is to evaluate performance measures
such as waiting times and the number of people waiting.
The informal terminology refers to people getting service.
But it has been used in many contexts,
including inventory and factories,
calls waiting at call centers, data packets in computer
networks, and others.
The purpose of queuing theory is to evaluate
performance measures.
The motivation for the discussion
here is to develop some intuition about capacity
utilization and storage.
So in this figure, customers are arriving at random times.
The service time is random.
And so there's a random number of people
in the system at any given time.
In the M/M/1 queue, we have exponentially distributed
inter-arrival times.
The arrival time is a Poisson process with parameter lambda.
1/lamda is the average time between arrivals.
Lambda is the arrival rate, because lambda
is the average number of arrivals
in time period t divided by t.
Each time there's an arrival, one customer
joins the queue and so the queue size increases by one.
The arrival rate is constant.
It's independent of time and of the number
of people in the queue.
Service is provided in the system.
The service time is exponentially
distributed with parameter mu.
1/mu is the average service time.
Each time there's a service, one customer
departs so the queue size decreases by one.
The mu is the service rate, because mu
is the average number of services
in a time period of length t divided
by t as long as the queue is not empty during that period.
The arrival and service processes are independent.
There's one server.
There's an unlimited waiting area.
No customer is turned away, although some
may have to wait in the queue for a very long time.
This simplifies the mathematics, but it limits
the usefulness of the model.
In many real-world systems, limited weighting
or storage space causes disruptions
in the part of the system that generates the arrivals.
We'll discuss that later.
Here, we're still going to be assuming infinite waiting area.
The designation M/M/1 queue is an old-fashioned kind
of terminology, but it's frequently used.
The M in both cases refers to Markovian, which in this case
means exponential.
Sometimes this is referred to as an M/M/1 infinity queue
because of the infinite waiting area and because people have
also studied M/M/1/N queue, where N refers to the size
of the waiting area.
We are going to be defining the utilization
rho as lambda over mu.
And the motivation for that will be coming soon.
This is a graph of the number of customers
in a queue at any given time.
The horizontal axis is time.
The vertical axis is the number of people in the queue.
Every time the line jumps up, it means
that a customer has arrived.
Every time the line goes down, a customer
departs because its service has been completed.
The flat areas in the graph are where the queue length is not
changing.
Those are the times between arrivals and services.
The number of people in the queue
goes up and down at random times,
and that's the essence of what we're going to be looking at.
By contrast, here's a different system called the D/D/1 queue--
not a very interesting system, but it makes a point.
D here refers to deterministic.
The time between arrivals is a fixed length of time.
It's constant, doesn't change over time.
The second D refers to the service time,
and it's constant, or deterministic.
You'll see that it's important that the service time be less
than the time between arrivals.
In this graph also, the number of customers in the system
goes up when there's an arrival and goes down when there's
a departure, but it's not a very interesting-looking graph
because of this deterministic nature.
There's never more than one person in the queue.
And between the completion of a service
and the arrival of the next customer,
there are zero people in the queue.
Besides the fact that the D/D/1 queue is all deterministic
and the M/M/1 queue is all random,
the really important difference between the two of them
is that in the M/M/1 queue, arrivals and services are not
synchronized.
As a consequence, the number of people in the queue are random.
In the D/D/1 queue, the number of customers
is never greater than 1.
The important lesson here is that in the absence
of variability, the queue length can be short.
This is important.
Queues are expensive.
In factories, queues are really inventory in storage.
And in order to have large queues,
we need to leave large amounts of space, which cost money.
And the inventory itself costs money.
So therefore, it's desirable to remove all the variability
we can from the system.
In this course, we're taking the amount of variability
as given and looking at the consequence
of that amount of variability.
So let's look at a longer time period for this queuing
system for the M/M/1 system.
So customers are now going to arrive in a Poisson process
with average inter-arrival time one minute.
And the service time will be exponentially distributed,
with average service time equal to 54 seconds.
It will turn out that the average number of customers
in the system is 9.
We'll show that shortly.
Here's a graph of the number of customers
in the system for a short time period.
The system starts empty and increases and decreases and so
on.
Notice that over this short time period,
it never reaches the long-term average number in the system.
Now let's look at this same system
over a longer period of time.
This is actually the same system as before,
and the first 100 times steps are the same as what
was on the previous graph.
This graph shows the simulation of the number
of customers in that same M/M/1 queue for a long time.
The last slide is the first 100 time units of this slide.
Notice that the largest number in the system
is almost 30 times larger than in the D/D/1 queue.
The average is sometimes exceeded by quite a lot.
The highest value that the queue achieves during this time
period is over three times the average,
the long-term average in the system.
This is why factory managers and operators
want to remove as much variability
in the system as possible.
It costs money to have inventory,
it costs money to provide space for inventory,
and customers do not like to wait, especially
for random lengths of time.
Here's an animation of that same queuing system.
You'll see now that the largest queue is larger
than it was on the graph that was on the slide.
It's much higher than the average
that we expect to see over the long-run.