In this set of slides, we'll discuss production smoothing.
The purpose of production smoothing
is to diminish or control quantity variation
in a production line.
It includes smoothing of total production quantity
and smoothing of each model's production quantity.
However, production must respond to variable demand.
If production is always done at a perfectly constant rate,
it will not be synchronized with varying demand.
Therefore, there must be some variation in production rate,
but that variation must be controlled.
Production rate due to internal factory events,
such as machine failures and other stoppages,
must be diminished as much as possible.
The just-in-time idea applied to sales
is supplying products in saleable quantities only.
That means that production must adapt promptly
to demand changes and doing this eliminates excess inventories
of finished goods.
Production rate variation due to internal factory events
must be diminished.
If demand increases, hire temporary workers,
add shifts, and so forth.
If demand decreases, dismiss temporary workers,
transfer workers to lines with increased demand,
decrease overtime, or fill up workers time with quality
control meetings, setup practice, maintenance,
and so forth.
Note that the last item's activities are all productive.
They're not just time fillers.
Our system has a maximum production rate, its capacity.
When demand is less than that maximum, capacity is wasted.
Smoothing production can reduce the required maximum.
However, when demand is greater than capacity,
there will have to be inventory or lost sales.
There's a trade off between inventory and lost sales,
just as in the news vendor problem.
But there are lots of differences
between what we're talking about now and the news vendor
problem.
Cars are sold over a long period, not just one day.
Sales are not lost like they are when the product is
today's newspaper.
Instead, the sale prices of cars go down over time gradually.
Also, the price of a car is not fixed, it's set by the market.
The goal of production smoothing is
to minimize the variance of total output during a period.
Ideally, produce the same amount every day,
if demand is constant.
The amount produced in a day is the total for a planning
period, such as a month, divided by the number of days
in that period.
The planning period should be as short as possible.
Consider an engine line that normally produces
a hundred engines per day.
An assembly plant requests lots of five,
with withdrawal kanbans.
Withdrawals normally occur 20 times per day.
Suppose demand is reduced to 90 per day,
then withdrawals occur 18 times per day.
The production process is stopped
after 90 engines are produced.
If demand is increased to 100 per day,
withdrawals occur 22 times per day.
The additional engines are produced in overtime.
If the engine plant did not alter their work hours,
they would either build inventory
or starve the assembly plant.
The purpose of mixing models is to minimize inventory,
to maximize utilization, and to minimize variability.
The next slides describe the effect of mixing models
on the amount of inventory.
This is a completely made-up example.
Over a period of 168 working hours,
which is eight hours a day for 21 days,
there's a constant demand for 56 a items, 56 b items,
and 56 c's.
a items have a 50 minute operation time.
b items require 60 minutes, and c items
have a 70 minute operation time.
Suppose they're produced with all 56 a's, and then 56 b's,
and then 56 c's every month.
In that case, the production rate of the line
changes over time.
For 46 hours and 40 minutes, it makes a items
at a rate of 1.2 items per hour.
For the next 56 hours, it makes b items
at a rate of one item per hour.
And then for the remaining 65 hours and 20 minutes,
it makes c items at a rate of items.
86 items per hour.
These graphs show the cumulative production
and cumulative demand for all three part types
over the course of that month.
In all the graphs, the horizontal axis
is the time in hours, the vertical axis
is cumulative production and cumulative demand.
The assumption is that demand is constant,
and the items are delivered in a steady stream.
The line produces a's for the first 46 and 1/3
hours at 1.2 parts per hour.
Then it stops producing a's and starts
producing b's for 56 hours at one per hour.
And then, finally, it stops making
b's and starts producing c's for 65 and 1/3
hours at 0.857 parts per hour.
Over a period of 168 hours, we've produced 56 a's, 56
b's, and 56 c's.
The production rate of a's, which
is the slope of the red line, is greater than the demand rate,
which is the slope of the green line,
until the month's requirements are met.
After that, there is no more a production,
so the red line becomes flat.
At that point the production of b's starts.
If you look at the graph, you'll see
that the line is flat until the time
when the a production is done, and then the b production
takes off.
It rises at a rate which is steeper than the demand rate,
and then the line flattens out because all the b's
have been produced.
Finally, the production of c starts at about hour 102,
and that continues until the end of the month.
These graphs are displaying the surplus as a function of time.
Time, as usual, is on the horizontal axis,
and surplus is on the vertical axis.
The surplus is the difference between cumulative production
and cumulative demand.
When surplus is negative, it's called backlog.
What's the consequence of having such surpluses in backlogs?
There are two cases to consider.
One case is where the customer, the next production stage,
operates the same way that this stage did,
and the two stages synchronize their production.
The downstream line would never be starved,
and there would be no inventory accumulation between them.
In that case, there would not be a problem.
But we intend to talk about constant demand,
and what I've just described is not constant demand.
So suppose the demand is constant.
That could happen in various ways.
There could be three customers, not one.
One customer only for a's, one only for b's, and one only
for c's, and they all have constant demand rates.
Or there could be a single customer,
but that customer needs to mix products and produce them
according to abc, abc, abc.
The third is that the product is going to the general market
where demand comes from many independent customers,
and the demand rate is constant for each.
In that case the b and c customers
would not be served for much of the month
without an accumulation of inventories.
So let's provide some inventories.
They're the same is the surplus graph, except we've
added enough inventory to b and c graph
so that the graph is never less than zero.
Now, we've produced large inventories
by doing things this way.
Let's contrast that with a situation
in which the items are produced abc, abc, abc,
and demand is constant.
So we're producing three parts every 180 minutes,
or one part an hour, on the average.
But to do that, we're making the assumption that the setup
change time is extremely small, essentially
that the machines are flexible.
As a result the surpluses and inventories are all small.
But this is only possible if the machines and the people
in this factory are flexible.
But now let's suppose that they're not so flexible,
and the setup change time from one part to another
is one hour.
In that case, making a batch of 56 a's
and then a batch of 56 b's and then 56 c's would
take 171 hours.
The 168 plus 3 for changeovers, assuming that the cycle
is going to repeat every month.
171 hours.
On the other hand, suppose we mix the parts making one a,
one b, and one c, and then repeating that.
In that case, it would take six hours
to make one set of three parts, and 56 times 6 and 336 hours
altogether to make 56 sets of three parts.
This is almost double the time for the three large batches.
In other words, this would cut the production rate
by about 50%.
In general, smaller batches lead to less inventory, but a lower
production rate for the same operation time and setup time.
A batch size of one is ideal, but it can only
happen if this technology is such that the change over time
is minimal, and there's enough capacity to meet the demand.
One more example.
A plant produces 10,000 Toyota Coronas in a month.
It produces 5,000 sedans, 2,500 hardtops, and 2,500 wagons.
So for example, one month is 20 eight-hour shift.
Production is divided equally.
In every shift, we have to make 250 sedans, 125 hardtops,
and 125 wagons, for a total of 500 cars.
An eight hour shift is 480 minutes,
therefore the unit cycle time is 480 over 500,
or 0.96 minutes, which works out to be 57 and 1/2 seconds.
On the average, then, once sedan must be generated every one
minute and 55 seconds, one hardtop
must be generated every 3 minutes and 50 seconds,
and one wagon must be generated every 3 minutes and 50 seconds.
The possible sequences to do this
is a sedan, wagon, sedan, hardtop, sedan, wagon, sedan,
hardtop, and so forth.
And that is mixing of models.
As long as there's no setup cost,
the sequence like this is desirable
because minimizes inventory.
But machines and people must be flexible for this.
The next set of slides will start off
with a discussion of setup times.