Last week we introduced variability
and discussed its impact on the performance
of manufacturing systems.
This is the first of three weeks that we'll discuss randomness.
This is important because most variability
is due to randomness.
And we need to be able to quantify it and its effects
on system performance.
The approach in this course
is to provide intuition about randomness and variability,
not primarily to teach mathematics,
but some math will be needed.
We define probability precisely and define such concepts
as independence, conditional probability,
the law of total probability, random variables, and others.
We introduce some widely used probability distributions
for discrete and continuous random variables.