The notation to talk about Markov processes
with discrete states and discrete time is to say x of t
equals i is the event that the random quantity,
the random variable, x of t has value, i.
For example, in the graph on slide seven, x of t
is any state in the graph and, i is some particular state.
We're going to define pi i of t as the probability that x of t
equals i at time, t.
And this is important and you see that notation a lot.
The pi's have to satisfy the normalization equation, which
is the sum over all the pi's at time t equals 1.
That is to say, x of t has to have
some of the possible values of i,
and the sum of the probabilities of all those possibilities
equals 1.
So let's look at the transition equations.
How do we quantify the event that we go from one state
to another?
Here's a detail of the graph on slide seven
and I'm focusing on states five and four.
To be in state four at time t plus 1,
the system must have been either in state five at time t
or in state four at time t.
So the probability of being in state four at time t plus 1
is equal to the probability that the system was in state five
at time t and made a transition from five to four,
plus the probability that the system was
in state four at time t and did not
make a transition to any of the other possible states
it could have gone to-- one, two, or six.
And just to remember that notation,
P 4,5 here is probability x of t plus 1 equals 4 given x of t
equals 5, and so forth.
Here's another one.
Let's focus on state two.
The system could be in state two at time t plus 1
if it was in one or four or five or two at time t.
So the probability that it's in state two at time t plus 1
is equal to the probability that it's in state two
at time t plus 1, given that it was in state one at time t,
times the probability that it was in state one at time t;
plus the probability that it's in state two at time t plus 1,
given that it was in state two at time t times the probability
that it was in state two at time t, and so forth.
This looks a lot like that equation of total probability
that describe the probability that I
was going to have a cold tomorrow given
the weather conditions today that we talked about some time
earlier.
We've defined P ij as the probability
that the system is in state i at time
t plus 1 given that the system was in state j at time t.
To summarize what we've done before
and put it in compact notation, the transition equations
say pi i of t plus 1 is equal to the sum over j of P ij times pi
j at time t.
This is an application of the law of total probability.
We also have the normalization equation:
sum over i of pi i of t equals 1.
So to go through this exercise with state two
from the definitions, we have the transition
equation for state two, which is pi 2 of t plus 1
equals P 2,1 pi 1 of t plus P 2,2 pi 2 of t plus P
2,4 pi 4 of t plus P 2,5 pi 5 of t.
And remember that P 2,2 is equal to 1 minus P 5,2.
So we're going to take the equations
that we wrote on slide 13 and now we're going to put them
in matrix vector form.
So pi of t will be the vector of the pi's at time t.
P is the matrix of the P ij's, and we're
defining a vector new which is a vector all of whose components
are one.
We can now write the transition equations as pi of t plus 1
equals P pi of t, and the normalization equation
is new transpose times by of t equals 1.
Other facts that we should know is that new transpose P
equals new transpose, which is a complicated way of saying
that each column of the p matrix sums to one.
The reason for that is the way we defined the diagonal entries
of the matrix P 1,1 is 1 minus the sum of P 2,1 up to P n,1.
We can also calculate pi at time t from pi at time 0
by iterated matrix multiplication.
So P to the t means matrix P by itself t times.
This is a graph of the probabilities
of all the states in the transition
graph in slide seven.
So now let's make an assumption that the non-zero transition
probabilities, other than the self loop probabilities,
are all very small on the order of 0.01.
That means that the average time between transitions
is on the order of about 100.
Suppose the system is in state one at time 0.
Then at time one, it's still most likely in state one
because the probability of transition is very small.
With small probabilities, it could be in stage two or three,
but it's impossible for it to be in any other state
because it needs more than one transition to get there.
At times two, three, four, and a little while after that,
it's very unlikely that a transition will take place
so the system will still very likely be in state one.
After about time 30, as you can see on the graph,
the probability that the transition has taken place
already is not small, so the system
might be in state two or three as well as one, or even
others with small probability.
After about time 50, it's unlikely
that it has not left state one.
It might still be in two or three,
but it could have left them and moved on to five or seven.
Actually, it could be in any state,
but except for states one, two, and three,
the probabilities are still small.
After more time, the system could be found
in any state in the system.
The probability that the system is in any given state
depends on the transition probabilities,
the initial state, and how long the system has been running.
Now let's think about the system at around time 150.
We watch the system for a while and we observe the fraction
of time that the system is in any given state
and we observe that that fraction is not changing.
In fact, the fraction of time that the system is in any given
stated time 200 is about the same as at time 150.
In that case, we can say that the system has reached
steady state at time 150.
So formally, a system is in steady state
when it approaches a limiting probability distribution
as time goes to infinity.
And we'll call pi i the limit of pi i of t
as t goes to infinity, which is also
the limit as t goes to infinity of p to the t times pi i of 0.
But notice that now I'm saying if it exists,
so it might not exist.
Why would it not exist?
Let's go take a look at another example.
Remember the number of heads after t coin flips.
What we found is that the state will eventually
progress to larger and larger numbers over time.
There's no steady state in this one.
The probability that h of t equals 10, for example,
is 0 for t equals 0 one to nine, but it's
non-zero for t greater than or equal to 10.
As t increases, that probably first increases and then
decreases.
It approaches 0 as t goes to infinity,
but it is not zero for any finite t.
As a consequence, there is no steady state probability.
Some systems with an infinite number of states
do reach stead state, others do not.
This has practical importance as we're going to see later.
Remember that models are approximations of reality.
Everything in the real world is finite,
but sometimes infinite state models
can help us to understand some features of finite systems.
The steady state transition equations are just pi i of t
is the sum over j P ij pi j.
So this is the same as the non-steady state equations,
except that we've eliminated the t arguments.
So before we had pi i of t plus one on the left and pi j of t,
but now we just have pi vectors.
We're going to use the steady state transition
equations to calculate these probabilities,
but there's another way that we can
do things, which is the steady state balance equations.
I've written them formally here, but in the next couple
of slides I'll explain what it all really means.
We're going to also need the normalization equation in order
to define the steady state probability vector.
OK, we'll use state four to illustrate the balance
equations.
What the balance equations say is
that the probability at any time of crossing
that circle, the dotted line circle, from the outside
to the inside is equal to the probability of crossing
that circle from the inside to the outside.
This is only true in steady state.
There's no transition equation analog
of this when we are not in steady state.
So the probability of going from outside to inside
is the probability of being in states one, two, or six.
There's only one way of going from outside to inside,
and that is that we were in state five,
and then we make the transition from five to four.
So the probability of making the transition from five to four
is P 4,5 pi 5.
The probability at any time of going
from state four outside state four
is the sum of the probabilities of the states
where the system can reach from state four times
the probability of being in state four.
So that's just P 1,4 plus P 2,4 plus P 6,4 times pi 4.
So here's what I said before.
Intuitively, it means that the average number of transitions
into the circle per unit time equals
the average number of transitions
out of a circle per unit time.
The reason for all this fuss about probability transitions
and Markov chains and so forth is
that we're going to need that probability
distribution to evaluate the performance of certain systems.
So we need to calculate the steady state probability
distribution pi.
So how do we do that?
Well, let's start off by assuming that the system has
n states and n is finite.
We assume there's a unique steady state probability
distribution.
The transition equations form a set of n linear equations
and unknowns.
The normalization is also a linear equation.
So that means we have n plus one equations and n unknowns.
Is that a problem?
We're not supposed to have n plus one equations and n
unknowns.
Well, it turns out there is not a problem.
One of those transition equations is redundant
and that's because each column sums to one.
We can throw out any one of those transition equations
and replace it by the normalization equation.
And then we solve that resulting system of linear equations
and unknowns.
We can solve it by hand if it's a small enough system
or we can use various computer programs that will help us
if it's larger than that.
A system that has a unique steady state probability
distribution is called ergotic.
The probability distribution as a function of time
approaches that limit, no matter what the initial probability
distribution was.
For systems that have more than one steady state solution,
the limiting distribution depends
on the initial probability.
The balance equations can be used
to find the limiting distribution instead
of the transition equations.
As before, one equation has to be replaced
by the normalization equation.
Which to use?
The balance equation or the transition equation
is a matter of convenience and taste.
If a system has an infinite number of states,
and it has a steady state probability distribution,
there are two possibilities for finding it.
It might be possible to solve the equations analytically.
We're going to see an example of that.
Otherwise, we have to truncate the system.
That means solve a system with a large but finite number
of states.
If you understand the system, you
can get which are the highest probability states
and you keep those.
Throw out the rest.
Solving that will provide an approximate solution
to the steady state transition equations.