The last thing we discussed was how
to calculate the average amount of inventory in an M/M/1 queue
or the average number of customers.
That's important.
What's also important is the average amount of time
that a customer spends in a queue or a piece
of good spends in a factory, and that relationship
is Little's Law.
This is a very important law, which
is true in general for most systems, and not just M/M/1
queues.
It applies only for systems in steady state.
In this law, the way it's usually written,
L is the average number of customers in the system,
and W is the average delay experienced
by a customer in the system.
The relationship is, L equals lambda W. Remember,
lambda is the arrival rate.
In factories and warehouses, L is the average amount
of material in storage, and W is the expected time
an item in inventory remains in storage.
People actually use Little's Law all the time
without thinking it's anything special.
Typically, a manager will say something
like, "we have two weeks worth of inventory,"
rather than saying, "we have 2,000 units in inventory."
However, they're equivalent if the demand
rate is 1,000 units per week.
In the M/M/1 queue, we had the formula for n bar
in the previous slide.
So from that, we find that W is equal to 1
over mu minus lambda.
Now, what does the equation say?
First of all, it says that if lambda equals 0,
then W is 1 over mus.
1 over mu is the average service time.
So what that really means is that if there is very,
very light traffic-- so lambda is very, very small--
then when a customer arrives at a queue
that customer will be served right away,
and the average amount of time that that customer spends
is therefore the average amount of time
that it takes to do a service, which is 1 over mu.
On the other hand, as lambda approaches mu,
then we see that the denominator of that fraction is going to 0.
So the average waiting time is going to infinity.
Here's a graph of W versus lambda, when mu equals 1.
This graph shows the phenomena that I just described.
W goes to 0, as lambda goes to 0,
and W goes infinity as lambda goes to 1.
In this case, mus is equal to 1.
Mu is the capacity of the system.
We've already seen that if lambda is greater than mu,
the system breaks down.
If lambda is less than mu, the system is stable,
and waiting time remains bounded.
If mu is greater than 1, the waiting time grows over time,
and there is no steady state.
So that's why the whole graph is blank on the right side of it.
Suppose that for the demand that we have mu
equals 1 is not enough.
What can we do?
Well, we can increase capacity by increasing mu.
So we can replace our machine with a faster machine.
This also decreases delay.
If you look at the amount of delay in the area
where lambda is less than mu, but close to it,
you can see that the green line is very far below the red line.
In other words, by increasing the capacity
of the factory or the queue, we've
decreased the waiting time.
Even though we had enough capacity to handle the demand,
if lambda is less than mu, but close to it,
we still have plenty of capacity to handle the demand.
However, the waiting time and the amount of inventory,
or the number of customers, goes up when lambda is close to mu,
but even less than that.
And that's shown by the red line.
By increasing the capacity of the factory, in this case,
replacing a machine by another machine which is twice as fast,
we've not only given ourselves more capacity,
but we've also reduced the waiting time,
even when there was sufficient capacity
for the demand earlier.
There are plenty more single-stage queuing models.
Things get more complicated when there
are multiple servers, which we're about to talk about,
when there's only finite space for queuing,
not an unlimited amount of space,
when the arrival process is not Poisson,
and the service process is not exponential.
In some cases there are formulas that we can use,
that are exact or approximate for some cases,
but not for all cases.
A relatively simple extension is the s-Server Queue.
In this picture, we have s equals 3.
There is three servers in this queuing system.
If the demand is too great for a single server,
and we can't increase the speed of that server,
we can have multiple servers.
One way of doing that would be to have multiple queues.
So each server has a queue accumulating in front of it.
When customers arrive, they must choose the queue
and stay on it until they are served.
However, a better plan is to combine all of those queues
into a single queue.
So now we have a single queue with three servers.
The average time for one combined M/M/s queue is better
than s/M/M/1 queues, because in the M/M/s queue,
all servers are busy when there are more than s customers.
When we don't combine the queues,
there may be times when some queues--
if we don't combine the queues, there
will be times when some servers are not busy,
because their queue is empty, but the other servers are busy
and they have queues.
The question is, is this a good idea?
Is it better to have three servers in parallel
rather than one server three times as fast?
Here's the transition graph for the M/M/s queue.
Now, the arrival process is the same in all states.
So the transitions from n to n plus 1
haven't changed from the previews,
but the service processes or departure processes do change.
When there are k, which is greater than s customers
in the system, the departure rate
is s mu, since all servers are always busy in that case.
When there are k less than or equal to s customers
in the system, the departure rate
is k times mu, since only k of the servers are busy.
That leads to a somewhat more complicated set
of transition equations.
For your information, we can get an analytical solution to this.
Don't worry about it.
It's complicated and not necessary to work out.
Here's the formulas for the probability distribution.
Pi 0 is a normalizing constant.
We have two different formulas, one for k less than s
and one for k greater than s.
Here row is equal to lambda over s mu,
and that has to be less than 1 for the same reason
that row being less than 1 was required before.
We can draw some graphs from these formulas.
These are graphs of the waiting time versus the arrival
rate for four different cases in which the capacity
of the system are all four.
For the lowest graph, there are four servers,
each operating at rate 1.
For the next to the lowest, there
are two servers, each operating at rate 2.
For the next one, there are four servers,
each operating at rate 1.
And for the highest one, there are eight servers,
each operating at the rate 0.5.
The graphs all go to infinity as the arrival process approaches
the capacity, which is four.
But notice that the waiting time for a large number
of slow servers is greater than that
for a small number of fast servers,
especially when the arrival rate is low.
From this graph, we can see that a single fast machine provides
better performance in terms of reduced waiting
time than several machines in parallel,
especially if the demand rate is low.
But it is often true that the single fast machine
is more expensive to own and operate
than several parallel machines with the same total capacity
and the same performance in other respects.
So it's probably a good idea to have several slow servers
rather than one fast one when the system is
operating near capacity.
When the system is near capacity the performance
is pretty much the same, but the cost of equipment may be lower.
Going back to the graphs that we looked at earlier,
here's the effect of replacing the single slow machine
by either one fast machine or two slow machines.
To increase capacity or reduce delay
we can increase mu, which is the green graph,
or we can add servers in parallel, in the red graph.
But when we add the servers in parallel,
that will not reduce the delay as much
as the single fast machine.
Two more points before we leave this brief introduction
to single queuing systems.
We've made some very specific assumptions
about the queuing systems we've looked at:
a Poisson arrival process; an exponentially distributed
service process; the arrival and service processes are
independent; and there are no limits on the number of items
in the queue.
We saw that the shape of the graph of waiting
time, W versus arrival rate, lambda,
has certain characteristics.
The waiting time is small for lower arrival rates.
It increases monotonically as a function of arrival rate,
and it goes to infinity as the arrival rate approaches
the service rate.
We also saw that if the arrival rate exceeds the service
rate, that is to say, the demand exceeds the capacity,
then the queue grows and never reaches steady state.
The graph of waiting time versus arrival rate
has those same characteristics for all reasonable assumptions
about arrival and service processes for queues
with unlimited waiting room, and the same thing
is true for average queue length, or n bar,
as a function of arrival rate.
Systems with finite room for waiting customers
behave a little differently than the ones we've been looking at.
In this case, there's another performance measure
of interest-- the fraction of people or parts
that don't get in, that are turned away.
In systems that deal with people that
arrive from the outside world, customers
are turned away if they arrive when the storage area is full.
Those people just don't get service at all.
Material or work orders that arrive at a full storage area
from other machines are forced to wait at the workstation
where they came from.
As a result, those parts are stored there.
That station could be forced to be idle.
It is said to be blocked.
The average waiting time for customers that do get in
does not go to infinity as the arrival rate approaches
the service rate, and this average queue length certainly
does not go to infinity.
It is bounded by the limited waiting room.
Instead, the fraction of customers that
don't get service approaches 1.
This is, again, true for all reasonable assumptions
about arrival and service processes.