In this video, we consider lines without buffers,
or buffers of size zero.
This is the opposite extreme as the infinite-buffer case.
Inventory is as small as it can be.
But eliminating all possibilities of inventory
will certainly reduce the production rate.
The question is, by how much?
This analysis provides a lower bound for the production
rate of a line.
If you have to design a line to meet a specified target
production rate and you calculate that you can meet it
without buffers, you don't need to consider buffers
any further for the production rate of the line.
You might possibly have to think about them for other reasons.
As we will see, the calculation is pretty easy.
If any one machine fails or takes a very long time
to do an operation, all the other machines must wait.
Therefore, the production rate is usually less, possibly
much less, than the slowest machine of the line.
The first case that we're going to consider
is a line with constant unequal operation times and perfectly
reliable machines.
The operation time of the line is
equal to the maximum operation time of all the machines.
So the production rate of the line
is the inverse of the maximum operation time.
Line balancing is the assignment of tasks
to machines in a way that minimizes the maximum operation
time.
Since there's no advantage to having any machine faster
than any other machine, they should have
about the same operation time.
Parts produced on transfer lines generally require many tasks.
Line designers are limited in the numbers of machines
or workstations at which to perform those tasks because
of space considerations and because some costs can
be reduced by having tasks at the same location.
Line balancing is the problem of allocating those tasks
to workstations to minimize the maximum operation time.
It is complicated by various constraints.
Some tasks must be performed before some others.
Some tasks must not be performed at the same machine
at the same time.
The part must be oriented in a certain way for some tasks
and then rotated for others, and so forth.
This is a challenging combinatorial optimization
problem, but we will not discuss it further in this course.
Now we'll consider zero-buffer lines
with unreliable machines and constant equal operation times.
We will look at two ways of calculating the production
rate of this kind of line based on two different failure
models.
First, we'll make the assumption of time-dependent failures.
Remember, time-dependent failures
means that machines can fail even if they're idle.
The operation time is the time unit.
The efficiency is the probability
that machine Mi is operational in any time unit.
EI is the efficiency and isolation
of machine's production rate and parts per operation time
if it were the only machine in a factory.
But since it can fail regardless of the states
of the other machines, it is the probability
that that machine is up.
A part is produced as often as all the machines are
operational.
We assume that if any machine fails, the line stops.
This is certainly correct if there
is a mechanism that shuts the whole line when
any machine fails.
If not, the formulas we derive may not be exactly correct.
For example, the machines downstream of the failure
can still work if there are parts in those machines
and the transfer mechanism keeps operating.
Those machines can do productive work
until those parts leave the system.
However, if that happens, some or all
of the machines downstream of the failure
will have no parts at the time that that machine is repaired.
For that reason, those machines will
be idle after the repair for the same length of time
as they were working after the failure.
So the following formula is probably not too bad.
Since machines fail independently
of the states of the other machines,
the probability that all machines are operational
is just the product of all the efficiencies.
Therefore, the production rate of the line
is E TDF equals the product of all the efficiencies measured
in parts per operation time.
We use the capital E symbol because it's the production
rate per operation time.
It's also the line efficiency-- the fraction
of the production rate of the line if it never failed.
When the operation time is constant and 1,
we use P and E interchangeably.
Well, that's it for that.
Now let's look at operation-dependent failures.
I may forget to say so, but I will always
be assuming operation-dependent failures
unless I say otherwise.
And I don't plan to say otherwise anymore.
The operation time is the time unit.
The assumption is that failure and repair times
are geometrically distributed.
Each machine is the kind of machine
that we described in the discrete-time Markov chain
video.
pi is the probability of a failure of Machine I
during an operation.
ri is the probability of repair during an operation time
when Machine I is down.
We'll be deriving Buzacott's zero-buffer line formula
shortly.
But first, let's think about this.
Which do you think has a higher production
rate, a line with time-dependent failure machines
or a line with operation-dependent failure
machines with the same parameters?
Before we derive it, I want to point out
that this formula reduces to the earlier formula when
k equals 1.
According to the new formula, the isolated production rate
of a single machine MI is 1 over 1 plus p1 over r1,
which is equal to r1 over r1 plus p1, which
is the same as the earlier formula when the operation time
tau is equal to 1.
The approximation that we're going to make is that, at most,
only one machine can be down at a time.
This is not too bad an assumption.
The only way that two machines could be down at the same time
is if they both fail simultaneously.
Here's something to think about.
Do you think that the formula that we're deriving
overestimates or underestimates the production rate
as a consequence of this approximation?
Whichever it is, it won't be by much.
Consider a long time interval of length T operation
times, during which machine MI fails mi times.
The green bars are the times when all the machines are up.
The red bars are the times when one machine is down.
It won't be the same machine every time, of course.
In fact, the down machine is indicated above each red bar.
Notice that machine M3 failed twice during this period.
Without failures, the line would produce T parts.
The line is down for 1 over ri operation times on the average
each time machine MI fails.
And machine MI fails little mi times.
So the amount of downtime due to machine MI
is little mi over ri, and the total amount of downtime
is just the sum of that over all the machines.
The total up time is given by this formula, which is simply
U equals T minus D. U is the number of operation times
in which all machines are up.
Since the system produces one part per time unit
while it's working, it produces U parts
during the interval length T.
Each time machine MI is up, it has a probability pi
of failing.
It's up U times, so the expected number of times it fails
is pi times U. But we already have a name for the expected
number of times machine MI.
Fails.
That's called mi.
So we have this relationship.
Plugging that back into the last formula we calculated,
we have this.
This is from replacing MI with pi
U in the equation on slide 40.
If we rearrange the terms, we find this equation.
And that's really what we've been looking for.
This is the formula we set out to prove.
Note that P is a function of the ratio Pi over ri, and not
Pi or ri separately.
The same statement is true for the infinite-buffer line.
However, the same statement is not
true for a line with finite non-zero buffers.
This is why it's hard to develop intuition
for, and solution of mathematical models of, systems
with finite buffers.
So let's deal with the improvement questions again.
If we want to increase production rate,
which machine should we improve?
And what would happen to the production rate
if we improved any other machine?
So here's another chance to test your intuition.
Pause the video before you listen to my answers.
So here's the first question again.
If we want to increase production rate,
which machine should we improve?
We should improve the machine with the largest ratio
Pi over ri because that is the largest
term in the denominator of the formula for the production
rate.
Improving it means reducing P or increasing r.
If there were buffers, we would call that machine
the bottleneck.
The second question is, what would
happen to the production rate if we improved any other machine?
Reducing any term in the denominator
of Buzacott's formula will increase the production rate.
Therefore, improving any machine could be useful.
This is important because it might
be very expensive to improve the least reliable machine
and relatively cheap to improve other machines.
Let's take a look at some graphs.
This is the graph of the production rate
of a line as a function of the failing probability of one
of the machines.
It comes from Buzacott's zero-buffer formula.
The horizontal axis is pi.
The horizontal axis is pi, the failing probability
of Machine I. It doesn't really matter which machine.
The vertical axis is the production rate.
Clearly, as that machine gets bad,
the production rate goes down.
This graph compares a line with machines
that have time-dependent failures and one
that has machines with operation-dependent failures.
The observation that we make from this graph
is that the operation-dependent failure line
has greater production rate than the time-dependent failure
line.
And the difference increases as the line gets longer.
The reason for that is that when one machine fails,
all machines stop.
The operation-dependent failure assumption
prevents the other machines from failing while they're idle.
On the other hand, time-dependent failures
allows the other machines to fail.
Therefore, when the machine whose failing caused the damage
is repaired, we could discover that some other machine
is down.
This graph compares the production rates
of an infinite-buffer line with that of a zero-buffer line.
All machines are the same.
As the length of the line increases,
the production rate of the zero-buffer line decreases.
The production rate of the infinite line
stays exactly the same.
This provides a motivation for finite buffers,
because we can't install infinite buffers,
to increase the production rate to somewhere
between that of zero buffers and infinite buffers.