This set of videos is a brief overview and summary
of some of the key elements of the Toyota Production System.
The references for this set of videos
are Toyota Production System, a book by Yasuhiro Monden,
and Decoding the DNA of the Toyota Production System
by Steven Spear and Kent Bowen, Harvard Business Review,
September, October 1999.
There are very many books, articles,
and websites that describe the Toyota Production System.
The Toyota Production System was developed by Toyota
after World War II.
In the postwar period, the west--
especially the United States-- was relatively prosperous.
It was important to US manufacturers
to satisfy high postwar demand.
The price of goods was not as important as the production
of large quantities at high production rates.
Japan was poor.
Cost minimization and efficiency were most important
to Japanese manufacturers.
Toyota Production System is low-tech, not dependent
on computers when they came available in the 1960s.
All required actions had to be easily understood and executed.
The Toyota Production System has been highly influential
and widely imitated.
Many Japanese words have entered the manufacturing vocabulary
due to the Toyota Production System.
Knowing my limitations, I will make no claim
to pronouncing any of them correctly.
The Toyota Production System is concerned
with all aspects of manufacturing business,
not just factory design and operation.
It deals with the people in the company-- both the ergonomics
and psychology.
It discusses how to implement its methods,
considers material handling, information handling,
improvement activities, its relationships with car dealers
and parts suppliers.
People spend years studying it.
Many people make a nice living as consultants helping
companies to implement it.
We will only deal with a very small part of this.
The goal of these videos is to make
you aware of some of the most important aspects of it
and to focus on manufacturing systems' engineering issues,
but there's a lot more to it.
First, we'll discuss the goals of the Toyota Production
System.
The goal of a business is to make profits.
This would appear to be obvious, but people in factories
often lose sight of this.
One reason is that people focus on their local subset
of the factory.
People are given quantitative performance
goals which are intended to help them contribute to factory
performance, but such goals could actually
reduce performance if not chosen wisely and updated as needed.
Toyota's primary goal is cost reduction and the improvement
of productivity.
By cost, they mean cash outlay for the purpose
of making a profit.
Cost includes manufacturing costs,
sales cost, administrative cost, and capital cost.
So the first element is profit through cost reduction.
The second is elimination of waste.
Waste includes excessive production resources.
Excessive production resources includes excessive workforce
which increases cost through salaries.
It includes excessive facilities which
creates cost by depreciation and financing and many others.
The problem is to figure out what is excessive.
Another source of waste is overproduction.
That's continuing production when products are not
currently needed.
Toyota sees this as the worst kind of waste.
Excessive inventory, of course, comes from overproduction.
We've discussed this in previous videos.
Inventory, in addition to its other costs,
requires manpower to manage it, people to transport it,
clerks to keep track of it, and so forth.
Unnecessary capital investment is another source of waste.
It's not just the production equipment, but also
forklifts to move around unnecessary inventory,
areas to store unnecessary inventory, and so on.
Additional elements of the Toyota Production System
include quality control, which is to adapt production
to daily and monthly fluctuations
in quantity and variety, quality insurance, which is the effort
to ensure that each process supplies only good products
to the next process.
This is not just rejecting bad products by inspection
or reworking them.
It's improving production quality in the first place.
And respect for people--
recognition that people are what make the factory work
effectively and that if there's poor morale,
profits are reduced.
This is not just a slogan.
There's lots of detailed discussion
of this in the Toyota Production System.
People have to actively participate
in all concepts and goals of the Toyota Production System.
People's ideas and observations must be considered seriously.
People must be convinced and won over, not just
ordered to obey Toyota Production System rules.
Some more elements of the Toyota Production System
include just in time, which means
to produce necessary units in the necessary quantities
at the necessary times.
This leads to minimal inventories.
Autonomation, or jidoka-- this is autonomous defects control.
This is never allowing defective items to enter and disrupt
subsequent processes.
Just in time and jidoka lead to continuous flow of production.
Flexible workforce means varying the number
of workers as demand changes.
Creative thinking includes capitalizing
on worker suggestions.
Let's talk a little bit now about just in time.
In the assembly of car subsystems
and in the final assembly of a car,
the parts and subassemblies arrive
just when they are needed.
This is the goal of just in time.
If parts arrive too early, we have inventory.
If they arrive too late, there's starvation and idleness.
Just in time is hard to enforce in many factories,
because people hate to appear idle
or to let machines be idle, so they produce inventory.
Inventories are therefore not needed.
In reality, there are inventories.
They have a role, but inventories must be minimized.
Just in time cannot be achieved by central planning.
In many organizations, detailed management and scheduling
is often done centrally, but this
makes it impossible to respond to events as they happen.
Central planning exists in Toyota Production System,
but it does not micromanage.
Analogies are never perfect, but lets try one.
The role of management is more like that
of a coach of a sports team than the conductor of an orchestra.
Both make sure that their players know
the goal of the organization and their parts in it,
but orchestra conductors generally
try to remove all random elements
while sports teams must accept that they occur
and try to minimize their bad effects.
Also, people in each process withdraw
from the previous process only what they need,
and people at each process produce
what is necessary to replenish what has
been taken by the next process.
The kanban system is how Toyota Production System
works toward this goal, which we'll
talk about in the next video.
A push system is one in which production and material
flow are based on anticipated demand.
Detailed schedules are calculated centrally
and sent to each production unit.
The reasoning behind this is that everything
will be coordinated.
However, as soon as one production unit deviates
from its schedule due to a disruption, all
those that send it material or receive material from it
must deviate from their schedules.
Consequently, the disruption propagates
throughout the production system.
The Toyota Production System is intended
to be a pull system in which there is
no detailed central planning.
Central planning determines high-level goals for a month
or a week for each production unit,
then each unit determines what it
needs from its upstream units on a daily or more frequent
schedule.
This limits the propagation of disruptions
and the amount of inventory.
The technique they use to make this happen
is kanban, to be discussed shortly.
This is a list of some of the systems
and methods of the Toyota Production System.
We'll be discussing some of them in this set of videos,
including kanban, production smoothing, reduction of setup
time, standardization of operations,
machine layout, visual control.
And there are many more that we won't be discussing.
Spear and Bowen observed Toyota, and they
summarized what they saw as the core of the Toyota Production
System.
In their DNA paper, they say, "we
found that, for outsiders, the key
is to understand that the Toyota Production System creates
a community of scientists."
I find it very interesting that they used the term "scientist."
They mean that each worker must understand
the system and his or her part of the factory
and that when things go wrong, they
must use the scientific method to determine what went wrong.
Then they correct it.
A function of managers is to guide and support this effort.
They observed that people obey four rules.
First, all work shall be highly specified
as to content, sequence, timing, and outcome.
Second, every customer supplier connection must be direct,
and there must be an unambiguous yes or no way
to send requests and receive responses.
Third, the pathway for every product and service
must be simple and direct.
These first three rules are intended
to eliminate all possible ambiguities, misunderstandings,
and miscommunications.
Any improvement must be made in accordance
with the scientific method under the guidance
of a teacher at the lowest possible level
of the organization.
They observed that there was a common vision in the Toyota
Production System.
The output of an ideal person, group of people,
or machine is defect-free, providing
features and performance the customer expects.
It can be delivered one request at a time--
in effect, a batch size of one.
It can be supplied on demand in the version requested.
It can be delivered immediately.
It can be produced without wasting any materials, labor,
energy or other resources such as costs
associated with inventory.
And it can be produced in a work environment that
is safe physically, emotionally, and professionally
for every employee.
This is the ideal.
You must always work to approach it.
Another common theme is the elimination of variability
and the reduction of sensitivity to variability.