This week we build on the probability basics
from last week to discuss random dynamic systems, which
is what factories are.
In a stochastic process, the state of a system
evolves randomly over time.
And the present state influences the future.
We focus on Markov processes, a class of stochastic processes
that is very useful for modeling real world systems.
We study both discrete time and continuous time Markov
processes.
We develop transition equations, and we
show how to use them to calculate performance
measures of complex systems.
We model single unreliable machines
and relate their production rates to their failure
and repaired behavior.
We will use these ideas later to study variations
of inventory levels over time in production lines that
consist of many machines.