This is a schematic diagram of a two-card kanban system.
It is very highly simplified.
Now there are two WIP buffers and two kanban buffers.
In a two-card kanban system, there
are production-ordering kanbans and withdrawal kanbans.
In this picture, the green represents the flows
of withdrawal kanban, and the red
shows the flow of production-ordering kanban.
The withdrawal kanbans are like order
slips from the downstream stage, telling the upstream stage
what they need.
It is often used when there's a long distance
between operations or work cells.
If the squares represent factories,
there's a truck traveling between them.
If they are two stages that are not adjacent to one another
in the same large factory, there may be a forklift
doing the transportation.
It's also used when parts are delivered to the machines
in different sized batches.
To summarize the next few slides, on the upstream side,
there's a limited number of production-ordering kanbans.
When a part arrives and there's at least
one production-ordering kanban, the part gets an operation,
and the kanban is attached.
If there are no production-ordering kanbans
in the kanban buffer, no operation takes place.
All those kanbans are in the upstream output
buffer attached to parts.
If there's a withdrawal kanban in its buffer,
it's swapped with the production order in kanban.
The production order in kanban goes to its buffer,
and the part, with the withdrawal kanban attached,
is transported to the input WIP buffer
of the downstream machine.
The part waits in that buffer until the machine
is ready for it.
When it is, the withdrawal kanban goes to its buffer,
the part gets an operation, and then moves on.
OK, now for some details.
First, the upstream side.
These pictures are very highly simplified, as I said.
We're only showing a single part and one or two kanbans.
The parts are blue, the production-ordering kanbans
are red, and the withdrawal kanbans are green.
The upstream machine does an operation
when its previous operation or downtime is completed,
and there is a production-ordering kanban
in the production-ordering kanban buffer,
and a part is available.
After the operation, the kanban is attached to the part,
and they move to the output WIP buffer of the upstream machine
together.
The upstream cycle repeats.
If the withdrawal kanban buffer is not empty,
the production ordering kanban is
removed from a part in the output WIP
buffer of the upstream machine and moved
to the production-ordering kanban buffer.
A withdrawal kanban is attached to that part.
The part is made ready for transportation.
Transportation occurs according to some specific protocol.
There may be a transportation batch size, where there may
be a transportation schedule.
If parts are being transported a long distance,
they might have to wait for a scheduled departure,
or a departure may only take place
when there's a certain number of parts to transport.
When the previous operation or downtime
of the downstream machine is completed and is not blocked,
the downstream machine takes apart
from its input WIP buffer.
The withdrawal kanban removed from the part.
The withdrawal kanbans are transported
to withdraw buffer according to a transportation protocol.
Several withdrawal kanbans may accumulate
before they're sent upstream.
The downstream machine does an operation on the part,
and the part is sent to its next step.
The downstream cycle repeats.
So what happens when there's a machine failure
or other stoppage of a machine?
The withdrawal kanban are not added
to the upstream withdrawal kanban buffer.
The ones that are there are removed from that buffer
and attached to parts as the upstream machine does
operations A part in the output WIP
buffer of the upstream machine gains a withdrawal kanban
and is transported to the input buffer of the failed machine.
This continues until the upstream withdrawal kanban
buffer is empty.
No parts are added to the output buffer of the failed machine.
The parts that remain in the output buffer of the failed
machine have their production-ordering kanbans
replaced by withdrawal kanbans, and the parts
are moved to the input WIP buffer
of the downstream machine.
This continues until the output buffer of the failed machine
is empty.
When the failed machine is repaired,
the normal cycle resumes.
There are other kinds of kanbans.
The supplier kanbans are the same as withdrawal kanbans,
except they go to an external supplier.
Signal kanbans are similar to the production-ordering kanbans
but sent to a production station when inventory goes down
to a reorder point.
A material requisition kanban is also
similar to a production-ordering kanban,
but it's sent to a material storage area
when local inventory goes down to a reorder point.
And there are plenty others.
This is a summary of the kanban discipline.
It only works if everybody follows it.
Each process withdraws the necessary products
from the previous in necessary quantities
at the necessary time.
To enforce this, workers must first be won over.
This is partly out of respect for people,
and partly because if people don't
see the value in this discipline,
they will follow their instincts.
And their instincts tell them that it's
natural to keep making parts because those parts will
be needed eventually.
Kanbans must be attached to product.
Each process produces only what is withdrawn
by the subsequent process.
Defective products are never moved to the next process.
This is very important.
They should be reworked if possible.
If not, they should be scrapped.
Otherwise, they waste the time of all the machines and people
that operate on them later.
Also, they may escape the factory
and be delivered to a customer.
That is very bad.
In addition, the machine that did
the operation that made the part bad
should be investigated and repaired.
The number of kanbans should be minimized,
and the kanban system should be used
to adapt to small fluctuations in demand.