Let's add some realism to the model we just discussed.
We will consider two new issues.
First, the factory orders were material,
but it does not arrive until some time has
passed-- the lead time.
If everything were deterministic,
this would not be a problem.
Just order a bit earlier than we would have, otherwise.
But the second issue is that demand is random.
The problem is that the demand that
occurs between when the order is placed
and when the goods are delivered might be large enough
to cause a stock-out.
A stock-out of a make-to-stock product
occurs when a customer arrives and finds that none
of the product is available.
There are other possible issues.
Lead time could be random, production quantity
could be random, and lots of other things could happen.
But we're not going to be discussing that.
This is a graph of the inventory and inventory
position versus time for a deterministic system.
The horizontal axis is the time and days.
The vertical axis is the raw material inventory and units.
The raw material inventory position
is defined as the inventory in the factory,
plus the inventory that has been ordered but not yet arrived.
In this graph, we ignore the time
from when the supplier gets the order and when it ships.
That is we assume that the material is
shipped immediately.
The graph ignores all randomness.
For that reason, the factory order's
just enough so that the factory can exactly
meet the total customer demand between the time
the order arrives and the next time the inventory goes to 0.
One way of dealing with these new issues
is called the QR Policy.
We assume a fixed ordering costs,
like in the EOQ problem, a random demand,
like in the news vendor problem.
But the inventory retains its value.
It's not scrapped.
The inventory problem was really a one-day problem
that was repeated every day.
Now, we're dealing with one problem
that continues indefinitely over many lead times.
If there is raw material left just before the next shipment
arrives, that material can be used for future customers.
That makes this a true inventory problem.
The product is a make-to-stock product.
There's no advanced ordering by customers.
The policy is when the inventory level
goes below R, order a quantity Q. The problem is
to find Q and R to minimize the ordering plus holding costs
while not losing too many sales to stock-out.
Here's a graph of inventory and inventory
position as a function of time.
This is a graph of inventory and inventory position
versus time under the conditions for the new problem.
The horizontal axis is time and days.
The vertical axis is raw material and units.
The red line is the actual inventory in the factory.
The blue line is the inventory position--
the material in the factory plus the material in transit.
Lines are not straight due to daily demand randomness.
The lead time is 50.
The demand has a very large daily variance.
In this graph, R is equal to 150, and Q is 300.
That is when the inventory falls below 150, the factory
orders 300 from the supplier.
The time between orders is not fixed because it depends
on the demand, which is random.
The object in choosing R was to keep inventory non-negative.
But you can see that the policy failed
to do so between about day 125 until about day 140.
We need to determine Q and R. First,
we describe how to choose R. Let L be the number of days
between when the order is placed and when the shipment arrives.
The order lead time, L, is constant.
Let D be the total demand that arrives
between when an order is placed and when the shipment arrives
that sell days.
D is the random variable.
The order is placed when the inventory level goes below R.
The factory would like R to be greater
than the demand that arrives before the raw material
arrives.
But since the demand is random, the best we can do
is choose R, such that the probability that D is greater
than R is less than epsilon, where
epsilon is a small number.
The value of epsilon is a management decision.
Management has to decide how conservative they want to be.
If epsilon were small, it would be rare for a customer
to be disappointed.
But that would mean that R would be large.
That is there would be lots of inventory.
If management is not willing to carry a large inventory,
epsilon will have to be large.
And that means many customers will not
get what they want when they want it.
It's convenient to write the last equation in this form.
If L is large enough, the central limit theorem
says that D is approximately normal,
regardless of the distribution of the daily demand.
In that case, we assume that D is normal with mean u and stand
deviation sigma.
The probability distribution of the demand
is given by this formula where phi
is the standard normal probability distribution.
Then we choose R to satisfy this inequality.
The smallest value of R that satisfies this
is given by this last equation.
Recall that in the EOQ formulation,
lambda was the yearly demand.
Here mu is the mean demand for L days.
Therefore, mu is equal to L lambda over 365.
We might want to adjust that in leap years.
A graph of R star is a function of epsilon
with mu equals 1,000, and sigma equals
100 is on the next slide.
The horizontal axis is epsilon, the fraction
of customers and that management is willing to let be unhappy.
The vertical axis is R. R is the reorder point.
As soon as the inventory drops below R,
we order more raw materials.
The graph shows that R decreases with epsilon.
Now we describe how to choose Q. It's almost the same as
in the EOQ formulation.
The expected time between orders is T equals Q over lambda.
The expected number of days in a year is lambda over Q.
Therefore, the expected ordering cost in a year
is S lambda over Q.
Assume that the holding cost for material in transit
is the same as for inventory in the factory.
This is not actually an important assumption.
The average inventory position is R plus Q over 2.
And the average inventory holding cost
is h times R plus Q over 2.
Therefore, we choose Q to minimize
the approximate expected annual cost, which
is given by this equation.
But since R is constant for this purpose,
this is essentially the same as the EOQ problem
for determining Q, which is Q is equal to the square root
of 2s lambda over h.