Before we get into discussing continuous random variables,
I think there are some philosophical issues
that we want to talk about.
When do we use continuous and when do we
use discrete random variables?
The temptation is to say that when the system that we're
analyzing is discrete, we use discrete random variables,
and when it's continuous, we use continuous random variables.
However, we don't have to be ruled by that.
All models are only approximations of reality.
Mathematically, continuous and discrete random variables
are very different, and they're analyzed very differently.
However, quantitatively, some continuous models
are very close to some discrete models.
As a consequence, there may be times
when we have a choice, because the purpose of modeling
is to make predictions, quantitative predictions,
about what's going to happen.
So which kind of model we use for any given system
can be a matter of convenience and not
dictated by the nature of the system in a very rigid way.
For example, if we're looking at a factory in which we're
making small metal parts, such as nuts and bolts and washers,
et cetera, things like that, then it
might be better to model this as a continuous flow
rather than a large number of discrete parts.
For example, instead of counting the parts,
we might simply weigh the number of parts that we have
or look at the volume of the number of the parts
that we've made.
Now continuous random variables have to be treated differently
because they can take on an infinite number of values,
whereas the discrete random variables
take on a finite or a discrete infinity number of values.
So to talk about that, we'd have to talk
about probability density.
The probability of a two-dimensional random variable
being in a small square is the probability density
times the area of the square.
The definition is similar in higher dimensional spaces,
where we talk about volumes.
In this figure, we've represented the high density
areas with dark colors and the low density areas
with light colors.
You might want to compare this with slide 14, which
is a similar figure involving discrete random variables.
Now what does this actually mean?
So let's make up a story about a blindfolded dart thrower.
He's throwing darts at that same rectangle
that we had on the previous slide.
But we don't know exactly where the darts are going to land.
In fact, we don't even know if they're
going to land on the rectangle, but let's assume that they do.
Wherever each one lands is random, and for our purposes,
unpredictable.
But one thing that we do know is that if he
throws a lot of darts, then a large number of them
will end up in the darker areas and a smaller number will
end up in the lighter areas.
The probability that a dart lands in a little square
is equal to the probability density
where that square is times the area of that square.
So the probability density is higher in the upper left corner
and lower in the lower right corner.
Continuous random variables can be
defined in one, two, three or even infinite
dimensional spaces and in finite or infinite regions
of those spaces.
They can have probability measures
with the same dimensionality of the space or even
with the lower dimensionality of the space
or a mix of dimensions.
We'll give you examples of that soon.
So now let's think about what happens
as an example in a set of make-believe tanks
with make-believe water flowing through them.
In this case, we have two tanks.
Water can flow into the first tank,
and then from the first tank into the second,
and then out of the second.
There's a valve at the entrance of the first tank,
another valve between the first tank and the second,
and finally, a third valve at the end of the line.
The analogy to manufacturing is that these valves represent
machines, which can fail or be operational,
and the tanks represent storage or inventory
between these machines.
Here's the system starting empty.
There's no water in any of the tanks,
and the valves are all open.
If the valves stay open for a while,
we still basically have no water in each of the tanks.
In fact, there'll be a little bit of splashing.
But let's not worry about that.
So let's watch what happens.
First of all, notice that the third valve is closed.
And as a consequence of that, the second tank
is starting to accumulate water.
The first tank stays empty, because as soon as water
goes in, it goes right out.
So let's watch what happens.
Notice that the tank is starting to fill up.
The second tank is starting to fill up.
Eventually, we can see that the second tank actually gets full.
And when that happens, the water has no place
to go after the first tank.
So the first tank level starts going up.
Now notice what happens.
The middle valve has closed.
Now with the middle valve is closed,
the second tank stays full.
The first tank continues to increase.
So now we have the first valve open
and the next two valves closed.
Now notice that the third valve has opened.
The first tank is continuing to accumulate water,
but the second tank is starting to lose its water.
There's no flow between the first tank and the second tank
because that second valve is full.
Now the second valve opens up.
Now all three valves are open, and both tanks
stay at the same level.
Uh-oh.
Looks like the first valve closed.
Now no water gets into the first tank.
But water can still flow from the first tank
to the second one.
So the level of the first tank is going down,
whereas the level of the second tank stays constant.
The valves are still staying open.
But now notice that the first tank has completely
emptied out.
Now there's no water entering the second tank.
Water is leaving it.
So as a result, the level of the second tank goes down.
And finally, the second tank becomes empty.
OK.
This graph represents the space of the water tanks,
which we're labeling with Bs now,
which represent buffers, which represent
storage areas in the factory.
Now the arrows in this graph represents how the water
can flow in the two tanks.
For example, when the first valve is open
and the last two valves are closed,
we're symbolizing that as one, zero, zero.
That means the first thing is open-- that's a one--
and the other two are closed-- those are zeros.
What happens then is that the first tank starts filling up,
but the second tank stays at the same level.
And for that reason, the arrow is moving to the right.
Another condition would be that the first two valves are open
and the last valve is closed.
In that case, the water in the first tank stays constant,
but the second tank starts going up until it becomes full.
When the second tank becomes full,
that's where the first tank starts accumulating water.
And that keeps going until it reaches the upper right corner.
You can imagine other scenarios.
OK.
So this is after the animation.
Now if we look at what happens, we'll
notice that some parts of the space get darker.
Other parts stay lighter.
Those that are darker represent the higher density states.
Notice, though, that when a tank becomes full,
it tends to stay full for a while.
When it becomes empty, it tends to stay empty for a while.
So what we have is that in the interior of this space,
we really have a two-dimensional density,
where we can only describe the probability
by looking at the probability of being in a small area.
The edges of the rectangle, we actually
have one-dimensional densities, because when a tank becomes
full, it stays full, although the other tank can gain or lose
material.
Eventually, some of the corners have actual probabilities, not
densities at all anymore.
You can think of probabilities as zero-dimensional densities.
So we have a probability, for example,
of both tanks being full--
the probability of the first tank being full
and the second tank being empty and so forth.
If we looked at the discrete system,
the state space would look like this,
where the size of the dots represent the probabilities
of each of those states.
So we have integer numbers of parts in the first tank,
integer number of parts in the second tank,
and different probabilities.