Let's continue our discussion of the Newsvendor problem.
We've expressed the profit as a function of x and w.
x is the unknown we're looking for,
and w is a random variable representing the demand.
The problem is to find x, the number of papers
that the vendor should buy from the publisher that
maximizes the expected profit.
To find that number, we have to do two things,
express the expected profit as a function of x,
and then find the x that maximizes that expression.
The math is going to get a little more intense now.
Please have a copy of the slides handy.
I will be discussing expressions on previous slides that
are not on the slide I will be explaining.
The profit has one expression for w less than x
and another one for w greater than x.
Therefore, we have two terms.
Here's the first one for w less than x.
Here's the second one for w greater than x.
Now we separate the first integral into two parts,
so we have three terms.
Let's take a look at the three terms one by one.
Notice that the integrals in the second and third terms
are just integrals of the density
function f of w, one from minus infinity to x and the other
from x to infinity.
We can't do too much with the first term.
So let's look at it after dealing with the others.
The integral in the second term is just
f of x, the distribution function.
And the integral in the third is 1 minus f of x.
To find x to maximize EP of x, we have to be sure that EP of x
has a maximum.
For it to be interesting, we want
the maximum expected profit not to occur at x equals 0.
In other words, the newspaper business is only a game
worth playing if it's not smarter to sit it out.
Recall that the density and distribution
functions are both 0 when x is less than or equal to 0.
Therefore all three terms are 0 when x equals 0.
So the expected profit is 0 when x equals 0.
That makes sense.
If you don't play, you won't win, and you won't lose.
In order for the game to be worth
playing, EP of x must be positive for some x.
In order for this to be a realistic model of a business,
EP must be negative for some x.
In other words, it's possible to make a bad decision that
will cost you money.
When x equals 0, EP is 0.
That's because the density is 0 for x less than or equal to 0,
and the distribution function is 0 at x equals 0.
OK, let's look at the other extreme.
Let x go to infinity.
The first term goes to a finite constant, r minus s
times the expected value of w.
The middle term goes to minus infinity
because it is negative, x goes to infinity, and capital F of x
goes to 1.
The last term goes to 0.
This may not be obvious, because x goes to infinity, and 1 minus
f of x goes to 0.
But 1 minus f of x goes to 0 faster than 1 over x.
And this means that the last term goes to 0.
Therefore, when x goes to infinity,
the expected profit goes to minus infinity.
This makes sense.
If you buy a vast quantity of newspapers,
you're not going to be able to sell them all,
and you'll probably lose a lot of money.
So let's summarize what we know so far
about the graph of EP of x.
EP of 0 equals 0.
EP of x goes to minus infinity as x goes to infinity.
But we don't know what happens to EP of x, when
x is positive but not large.
There are two reasonable possibilities.
Either EP is always negative for x positive,
or EP has a positive maximum for x greater than 0.
So we have to figure out which is going to happen.
Here's the expression for EP of x again.
Let's take its derivative with respect to x.
It's just the integral of wf of w evaluated at w equals x.
The derivative of the second term of EP of x
produces two terms, and the derivative of the third term
also produces two terms.
So collecting like terms and simplifying
gives us this expression.
If we can find an x that sets this expression to 0,
we have a candidate for the x that maximizes EP.
The second derivative is given by this expression.
The second derivative is negative for all x positive.
Therefore, EP of x is a concave function and has a maximum.
The first derivative is positive, greater than 0
when x equals 0.
This means that EP is increasing at x equals 0, so EP of x
is positive for some x.
Since we know that EP of x is negative for some x, EP of x
has a maximum, which is greater than 0 for some x
equals x star, which is greater than 0.
x star satisfies the EP dx of x star equals 0.
The gaps in the graph of EP of x are now filled in.
The equation for x star comes from the DPD x
equals 0 equation on slide 25.
Notice that the fraction r minus c over or minus x
is between 0 and 1.
Also, the distribution function, f of x,
also is between 0 and 1.
Therefore, there is an x star that satisfies this equation.
So the policy is buy the quantity that satisfies
that equation every day.
Some days demand is higher.
Some days it's lower.
But this amount is the best to buy every day in the long run.
Recall the definition of the distribution function f,
f of x star is the probability that w is
less than or equal to x star.
So the equation in the box means,
buy enough stock to satisfy demand, 100 times
k percent of the time, where k is equal to r minus
z over r minus s.
To say it in other words, if you buy that quantity every day,
then the demand will be less than that quantity
for that fraction of a the days.
Here's one way of looking at this graphically.
The graph, of course, is the density function, f of w.
The area of the shaded region is the probability
that w is less than x star.
That is, that the demand is less than the quantity
we calculated to be the optimal amount to buy.
Here's another view of it.
This is a graph of the distribution function,
as a function of x.
And it says the same thing.
x star is the quantity such that r
minus c over r minus s, of the time,
the demand will be less than x star.
There's one more way of looking at this.
Notice that the density function at x star
is equal to r minus c over r minus s,
which we can write as r minus c over r minus c plus c minus s.
r minus c, which is positive, is the marginal profit
when x is less than w.
That is, it's the increase in profit
that you would get if you bought one more copy of the paper
from the publisher if the demand was greater than the number
that you bought.
c minus s is the marginal loss when x is greater than w.
The marginal loss is the decrease
in profit from buying one more copy of the paper
from the publisher if the demand was less
than the number you bought.
So the rule is choose x star so that the fraction of time
you do not buy too much is the marginal profit divided
by the marginal profit plus the marginal loss.