This week we described some quantitative models
of single part type flow lines.
We start from a model of a single unreliable machine
and then study a long line with several machines
and infinite buffers.
We introduced the concept of a bottleneck
and calculate the production rate of that line.
We use simulations to observe inventory accumulation.
Then we consider a line with several unreliable machines
and no buffers.
We calculate the production rate of that one.
These are two extremes, zero buffers having zero inventory
and low production rates and infinite buffers
with large inventories and high production rates.
Finally, we studied two machine lines with finite buffers.
These models show how buffers affect production rate
and inventory.
They also show how the frequency and duration of disruptions
affect these performance measures in ways that cannot be
predicted by machine efficiencies alone.
We will continue this subject in the second part of the course.