Hi everyone.
Welcome back to 2.854.1x, Intro to Manufacturing Systems.
In this recitation video, we will solve practice problem two
for week three.
So here's the problem.
This is our transition matrix.
This is a pretty simple discrete-time Markov chain.
So in this problem we solve for the three states.
So the first thing I do is to take this matrix
and put it into equation form.
So here we go, 0.3 pi one plus 0.1 pi two plus 0.6 pi three
equals pi one.
So the second equation is pretty simple.
That's just 0.7 pi two equal pi two.
Then we can throw out the third equation
and replace it with the normalization equation.
So that's simply pi one plus pi two plus pi three equals 1.
Now the second equation, the only way 0.7 pi two
can equal to pi two is if pi two equals 0.
So we could drop this term and drop this term since pi
to is 0.
So now we have 0.3 pi one plus 0.6 pi three equal pi one.
And just rearrange this equation, we get 0.6 pi three
equals 0.7 pi one.
So that means pi three is simply 7 over 6 pi one.
OK, now we substitute into the normalization equation.
We have pi one plus 7 over 6 pi one equal 1.
So 13 over 6 pi one equals 1.
So this means pi 1 is just 6 over 13.
And then since we know that pi one plus pi three must equal 1,
that means pi three equals 7 over 13.
And that's it.
Hopefully this can help you solve future problems.
Like always, leave your questions or comments
in the discussion section below.
Thank you.