OK.
Welcome to the third recitation video of 2.854.1x.
This recitation video will be on week five,
practice problem two.
OK.
So you guys probably read over the problem all ready.
So in summary, basically, there are two guys selling lunches
out of a truck at MIT.
We're given six different time periods
with six different arrival rates of customers,
assuming each customer buys one lunch.
OK.
So part 1, it asks what is the expected sales?
This is a relatively simple question.
Basically, it's just your discrete [? expectation. ?]
So we have six different arrival rates.
So you have lambda 1 is 0.4.
Lambda 2 is 0.8.
Lambda 3, 2.4.
Lambda 4 equals 1.6.
Lambda 5 equals 2.4.
Lambda 6, which equals 0.4.
OK?
So the six different time segments
are all 30 minutes long, and since lambda
is arrivals per minute, it's a simple multiplication
to get the expected sales for each one of those time
intervals.
So the expected sales of time interval one--
that is just 0.4 times 30, which is 12 lunches.
OK?
And similarly, we do it for the next six.
So you have 0.8 times 30--
the next five I meant.
2.4 times 30, 1.6 times 30, 2.4 times 30, 0.4 times 30.
And they are just 24, 78, 36, this is 1.2, sorry, 78, and 12.
So the total expected sales is just the sum
of the six time intervals.
And that is just 180.
So you're mu equals 180 for this problem.
The next part, basically, asks us to find the optimal quantity
that we should order, given certain criterias.
So we're getting a little bit of information.
So each sandwich is sold for $6.00.
So r equals 6.
It costs $2.00 to make, so c equals 2.
It costs $1.00 to dispose, so s equals negative 1.
And I think that's all we need.
So when you're given this information,
the first thing you should solve for is the critical ratio.
So critical ratio is just r minus c over r minus s,
which is just 4 over 7 in our case.
Now, we know that mu equals 180 and the standard deviation
is one third of the mean.
So that is just 180 divided by 3, which is 60.
And this is a normal distribution
with mean at 180, a standard deviation of 60.
OK?
So a couple of different ways to find the optimal x.
So we know that the standard normal distribution is just
x minus the mean divided by the standard deviation.
And that is just equal to the standard normal.
So we want to find the inverse of this.
How do we do that?
So you could use the z-table and look up
what the inverse should be, but a simpler way to do
this is just to use Excel.
So if you have Excel, just simply enter normsinv 7,
and that will give you 0.180.
OK.
So now, we know that x minus 180 divided by 60 equals 0.180 plus
x equal 190-ish.
OK?
190.8.
OK.
Another way to do this, instead of going through this ordeal,
just simply type in equal norminv.
It's going to ask for the probability.
That is just your critical ratio, the mean, which is 180,
and the standard deviation of 60.
If you do this, it should just output 190.8, exactly.
It's a much simpler way to solve for the optimal quantity.
OK, part 3 we are asked to solve the expected profit.
This is probably the most complicated part
of this problem.
Before we start, one of the parameters of the problem
has changed.
So now, sigma is just 30.
We still have our mu, which is equal to 180.
Since this is a symmetrical triangular distribution,
that is just our m, which is equal to a plus b divided by 2,
since it's symmetrical.
So that means a plus b equals 360.
OK, so sigma squared is equal to b minus a squared over 24,
which equals to 30 squared.
So b minus a is equal to 30 squared times 24.
And the square root of that--
so if you solve this equation--
in this equation, we get a equal 106.525, and b equals 253.485.
OK.
So in practice problem 1, we were
given the cumulative distribution of a symmetrical
triangular distribution.
And since we know the critical ratio is 4 over 7,
that means f of t is 4 over 7.
So now, we have to figure out if t
is between a and m or m and b.
In the interest of time, I'm just
going to tell you that it's between m and b.
You could try it for a and m, and you're
going to see that the function is not going to work out.
So this means 4/7 is equal to 1 minus 253.485
minus t squared over 73.475 146.96.
So I think-- this is just b minus m, b minus a.
OK.
So all of this--
what does this equal to?
OK.
So t will equal to 253.485 minus the square root of negative
of 4 over 7 minus 1 times 73.475 times 146.96.
So our t is 185.458.
And we said to round to the nearest integer,
so that it's just equal to 185.
So now, we know that our optimal water quantity, let's just
call that Q star, is 185.
Now we're asked to solve for the expected profit.
So in the lecture slides, I believe
it's slide 12, we said expected profit of Q star
is equal to r minus s times negative infinity to x.
Omega-- f of omega, d omega plus s minus c x f of x plus r minus
c x 1 minus f of x.
OK.
So these two, here, you could--
I'm not going to do the algebra because it's pretty long,
but these two is a simple substitution.
Now you should be able to just carry it out.
So s minus c is [INAUDIBLE] value minus costs,
so that's negative 3.
And our x, which is just our Q right here times 185 times
f of 185.
You could just substitute that in.
And for this part, r minus c is just 4 times 185 times
1 minus f of 180.
OK.
So now, let's dig into this part.
So we know f is a triangular-- is a probability density
function of the triangle distribution.
And it's an integral from negative infinity
to x, but, however, remember on the triangular distribution,
here is a, here is b, here is n.
Anything less than a is just 0, right?
So we don't actually need this negative infinity, here.
We could actually just replace it by 0 to x.
And x is just 185.
So this is actually two separate integrals
from a to 185 and from 8m, which is 180, and from 180 to 185.
So let's write that down.
So this part, I'm just going to bring it down here,
is equal to a equals 106 to 180.
We could just write x dx plus 180 to 185 x fx and dx.
So if you do the integral, here, there
are some things we can move around.
So first step into the integral, so there is a r minus
s out here.
OK.
So this is now just 2 times r minus
s divided by 253 minus 106--
I'm skipping the decimal so I don't
have to keep writing on this.
180 minus 106.
Multiply it by the integral, 106 to 180.
We'll make it squared minus 8 omega--
oh, sorry.
We said we're going to use x. x squared ax dx plus 180
to 185 bx minus x squared dx.
So I think, here, it's pretty straightforward.
You just have to finish this integral.
I'm not going to write out the details,
but, basically, this piece is just one third x cubed minus 8
over 2 x squared, evaluated 180 and 106.
And this part is b over 2 x cubed minus 1/3 x cubed,
evaluated 185 over 180.
OK.
So the sum of this and this gets multiplied by this quantity,
right here.
And then, adding this quantity, right here.
And you should have your solution.
So the expected profit at 185 units ordered,
should just be $635.51.