This course has a message and that
is, that manufacturing systems can
be understood like any complex engineered system.
There are two views about factories
that are very widespread.
One is that factories are huge messes that cannot possibly be
understood, and at the best that anyone can do is to overbuild
them and then, react to unwelcome events as they
happen.
The other is that factories can be understood, but only
designed and operated using common sense,
non-quantitative methods.
The message here is that we can treat factories
with quantitative engineering approaches and methods.
Engineers must have intuition about these systems
in order to design and operate them most effectively.
To be a good engineer, you must have
intuition about the kinds of things you work on.
You must have a rough idea of how the value of each parameter
affects the performance of a system.
And how different components combine to affect performance.
Intuition is not enough for design
because it is not precise so quantitative tools are needed.
But good intuition can provide a good starting point for design.
That starting point can be refined
by using quantitative techniques.
Such intuition can be developed by studying
the elements of the system and their interactions.
A goal of this course is to provide you
with some such intuition, especially about
the effect of randomness on manufacturing systems.
Using intuition and appropriate design tools
can have a big payoff.
In the HP case described in the previous video,
is an example of such a big payoff.
The goals of the course are to explain important measures
of system performance.
To show the importance of random, potentially disruptive
events in factories.
To give some intuition about the behavior of these systems.
Describe and justify some quantitative tools and methods.
But not to describe all current common sense approaches.
The approach is to focus on important factory
phenomena that can be analyzed quantitatively.
We will look at some of these phenomenon
in a very fundamental way.
Also, to develop or describe mathematical models
of these phenomena.
Mathematical modeling and analysis
is a very important part of the course.
In the next few weeks, we'll be reviewing basic probability
because we'll be focusing on randomness in factories.
To study the required mathematics, only as deeply as
needed.
This is not a math course, but some math is needed,
and it might feel like a math course at some times.
There are some problems in the field of manufacturing system
engineering.
First of all, it's not as advanced as other branches
of engineering.
Not as advanced, in particular, compared with aerospace,
computers, and so forth.
The hardware-- the machines, and processes,
and material handling systems-- are just as advanced,
but the overall factory design and operation
is not quite so advanced.
Practitioners are sometimes, encouraged
to rely on slogans or black boxes.
An example of a slogan is, inventory
is waste or zero inventory.
Those were current at the time of the HP project.
The black box is a computer program
that you put numbers into, and you get numbers
out of without knowing or possibly
even caring how it works.
A gap exists between theoreticians
and practitioners.
The research literature is incomplete,
in that there are lots of important problems
that researchers have not touched not.
But practitioners are often unaware of what does exist.
Terminology, notation, and basic assumptions
are not standardized.
Different factories or companies use different terms
for the same thing and sometimes, the same terms
for different things.
I will point out some of these during the course.
There is typically a separation of product, process, and system
design.
They really should be done simultaneously
or iteratively, but not sequentially.
We'll talk about this shortly.
Another problem for practitioners
is that there's often a confusion about objectives.
Should they try to maximize capacity?
Or minimize capacity variability?
Or maximize capacity utilization?
Should they minimize lead time?
Or minimize lead time variability?
Or maximize profit?
And there are lots of others that people think about.
This diagram shows the relationship
between manufacturing systems engineering and other aspects
of manufacturing.
To bring a product from a designer's idea to something
useful that you can sell, takes a lot of steps.
First of all, somebody has to design the products.
Then, somebody has to design the processes
by which you make the products.
Then, you have to think about the manufacturing system.
First, you have to think about the structure of the system--
the architecture-- and we'll give some examples of that
later.
Then, we have to choose the machines that will actually
implement the processes and buffers that will store
material between machines.
Finally, we have to choose an operating policy--
decisions that we have to make in real time, in response
to random events that take place,
such as unexpected machine failures.
Once all of these decisions have been made,
then we have to predict the performance of the system.
This is done by some kind of modeling technique,
specifically simulation or mathematical modeling.
And we'll talk more about that in the rest of the course.
Once you evaluate this design, the question
is, are the performance and cost satisfactory?
If yes, you're finished, and you can start building the factory.
If no, you have to go back and make some changes.
And changes may be required at any or all of the stages
that we just went through.
The process is iterative, and we may
have to go through this process many times,
until finally, we get to yes.