Hi, everyone.
This is Jack here.
In this recitation video, we're going
to go over how to solve parts one and two of the week four
graded problem two.
So here's the problem--
Youngjie's machine job.
Basically, there is a buffer station in one machine.
The buffer station could hold up to two parts.
The machine could hold for hold one part.
So the total number of parts that's possible in the system
is three.
Now, there was quite a bit of confusion over this problem
because lambda in parts one and two
is either greater than or equal to mu.
So that means if this is typical MM1 system,
there won't be a steady state.
However because the queue is not infinite,
you cannot just use the MM1 formula.
So I think this is where a lot of the confusion came from.
So when you arrive at a problem that
doesn't fit a prescribed set of formula,
it's best to derive it from the transition inclusions.
So in this recitation video, I will show you
how to set up the transition diagram, the Markov
matrix, and then steady-state probability equations.
OK, so in part one of the problem, basically
the issue is lambda is equal to mu.
So the system has four states.
It could either have zero parts in the system,
one part in the system, two parts in the system,
and three parts in the system--
so a total of four states.
And parts are arriving at a rate mu.
So that means-- parts are arriving at lambda, sorry.
So the transition diagram looks something like this, right?
And then when they get milled, it
returns to a previous state at a rate mu.
So here is the transition diagram.
It's a pretty simple one for this problem.
Now, how do we set up the transition matrix or the Markov
matrix?
Well, this is a continuous-time Markov chain.
And in the recitation video in week three,
I demonstrated how to set up that matrix.
I'll do it again here.
So here's a matrix.
And like I did before, I like to put the states here.
1, 2, and 3, 0, 1, 2, and 3.
So let's fill in the transitions.
So to go from state 0 to 1, we are at rate lambda.
0 to 1.
1 to 2 lambda.
2 to 3 lambda.
OK, so 3 to 2 mu.
2 to 1 mu.
And 1 to 0 is mu.
So you have a lower diagonal and an upper diagonal.
And we know that each row has to sum to 0,
so let's just fill them out.
So you have negative lambda.
Over here, you have negative lambda plus mu, negative lambda
plus mu, and negative mu.
And like we did before, so here are
the steady-state probabilities.
P0, P1, P2, P3.
And that equals to 0.
So really, all you have to do is solve for the null space
of this matrix.
It's simple to do because you know that lambda equals mu.
So you could either replace lambda with mu or mu
with lambda.
But I will set up the steady-state equations.
So the first equation is negative lambda P0 plus mu
P1 equal to 0.
And we have lambda P0 minus lambda plus mu P1 plus mu
P2 equal to 0.
Lambda P1 minus lambda plus mu P2 plus mu P3 equals 0.
And lambda P2 minus mu P3 equals 0.
Here are our four equations.
And then, we also have our normalization equation.
So P0 plus P1 plus P2 plus P3 equals 1.
OK, 5 equations and 4 [INAUDIBLE]..
So we just throw out one of the equations.
I always throw out the one with three terms,
so let's just throw out this one.
Now, this equation is actually a lot easier
to solve because lambda equals to mu.
So negative-- I'm sorry, so mu P1 equals lambda P0.
Since lambda equals to mu, they just cancel.
So P1 equals P0.
Let's go to the next one, OK?
So lambda P2 equal to mu P3.
And once again they cancel, so P2 equals P3.
So this equation becomes lambda P1
minus 2 lambda P2 plus lambda P2, which equals to 0.
So this term-- this 2 cancels.
So what do we have?
P1 equals P2.
OK, so if P1 equals P2, and P1 also equals P0,
but P2 equals P3, that means P1 equals P2 equals P3 equals P0.
So this means that P0 plus P0 plus P0 plus P0 equals the 1.
So P0 equals 1/4, which equals P1 equals P2 equals P3.
So this is how you solve for the steady-state probability.
OK, so the question asked us to solve for L. L is the expected
number of parts in the system.
This is just basically, the expectation
of a discrete probability.
So you have 0 times 1/4 plus 1 times 1/4 plus 2 times
1/4 plus 3 times 1/4.
And this is just equal to 1.5.
And that's the solution to part one.
So part two really is the same thing.
Instead of lambda equal to mu, we have lambda equals 2 mu.
So really, you just have to solve the same set of equations
with this substitution instead.
So I'm going to fast forward a little
bit and just get to the substitution.
So basically, we have P1 equals 2 P0.
So that means 1/2 P1 equals P0.
And P2 equals 1/2 P3.
Now, let's make the substitution here.
So 2 mu P1 minus 3 mu P2 plus mu P3 equals 0.
So let's substitute 1/2 P3.
Let's substitute this.
So 2 mu P1 minus 3 mu over 2 P3 plus 2 mu over 2 P3 equals 0.
OK?
So this term cancels.
So 2 mu P1 equals mu over 2 P3.
So let's cancel the mu.
So P1 equals 1/4 P3.
So I'm going to put everything in terms of P0.
So 2 P0 equals 1/4 P3 because of this right here.
So P0 equals 1/8 P3.
It's also 1/8 P1.
Now, P2 is equal to 1/2 8 P3.
So this is just 4 P3.
Sorry, this is a P0, my bad.
OK, 4 P0.
OK, so everything is in P0.
So P0 plus P1.
And P1 is just 2 P0.
P2-- P2 is 4 P0.
Plus P3, 8 P0 equals 1.
This comes from here, just flip the 8.
So 8 P0 equals P3.
It comes from this equation.
So P0 just equal to 1/15.
And now, we substitute P1 equals 2/15, P2 4/15, and P3 is 8/15.
The last part, once again, asks us to solve for L. So
it's just 0 times 1/15 plus 2 times 2/15 plus--
sorry, this is 1.
2 times 4/15 plus 3 times 8/15.
That is 2.26.
And there you have it.
So once again, if you have any questions, shoot me an email
or leave a comment in the discussion below.
Thank you.