Welcome back to 2.854.1x.
In this video, we'll go over week 4, practice problem 2.
OK.
So here's the problem.
Basically, it's about Jane who moonlights in the food court.
I guess she's a servicer in the food court.
And customers arrive at her counter
at a rate of 10 per hour while it takes her, on average,
four minutes to serve a customer.
So the arrival process is a plus on the arrival process
and the service time is exponentially distributed.
So in part one, we are asked what type of queue is this.
So since there is no mention of how long the line can be,
we assume it's infinite.
And since there is only one server
and we're told of a Poisson arrival
time and exponential service rate,
then the model is an [? MM1 ?] system.
Now what is lambda?
Well, lambda is given.
So basically at a rate of 10 per hour,
lambda is 10 customers per hour.
So what is mu, the service rate?
So if she serves four--
it takes her four minutes per customer,
then that is basically 0.066 hour per customer.
So we take the inverse.
That is 15 customers per hour.
And that is our mu.
OK.
So here's part 2.
What percentage of the time is she serving customers?
So this is basically just the utilization rate.
Rho is simply just lambda over mu.
So that is 10 over 15, which is 0.66.
So 66% of the time, she is expected to be busy.
So what percentage of time she is idle?
That's simple, right?
That's basically the percentage of time
when there are no customers in the line or in the service.
That's just 1 minus rho and that is 0.33.
What is the queue length?
So we had some confusion in this part.
A lot of students thought the queue length
is the same thing as the number of people in the system.
It's different.
It's basically the number of people waiting.
So it does not include the person being served.
So if we think back, L, which is the number
of people in the system, is just rho over 1 minus rho.
So what is this?
That's 0.666 over 0.33.
That's just two, right?
So on average there are two people in the system.
But what is Lq?
Lq is the number of people waiting in line.
So if the system--
if 66% of the time the system is busy, 33% of the time
there are nobody in the system, than the expected line
is just 2 times 0.66 plus 0 times 0.33, which is 1.33.
And that is basically the formula for Lq.
Lq is just rho squared over 1 minus rho.
It's the same thing.
We basically dropped this part, because 0 times anything
is just 0.
What is the average time that a customer takes in the system?
OK.
Well, we use Little's Law here.
Average time in the system is w, which
this equals L over lambda.
Right.
In the last section, we said L equals 2, so it's 2 over 10,
which is one fifth.
[? Hour ?] that is the--
and that is just 12 minutes.
So what is the probability that the customer waits at least
four minutes in the system?
OK.
So service time is four minutes per customer.
Right?
So that means if there's one person in the line,
the second person has to wait at least four minutes.
So this probability is really just the probability of n
is greater than or equal to 2.
There are two or more people in the system,
then somebody has to wait at least four minutes.
And that is just 1 minus the probability of n equals zero
and minus the probability of n equal 1.
So in our notation, that's just 1 minus pi is 0, minus pi 1.
OK.
The probability when there are nobody in the--
of when there's no one in the system,
we said in one of the earlier parts
that is just one minus rho.
Now if we go back to the lecture,
the probability of when there is only one person in the system
is actually quite simple.
And in the lecture notes, we say that it
is one minus rho times rho.
This is rho.
So if you plug everything in, the probability
of m greater than or equal to 2 is just 4 over 9.
OK.
So when Jamie is not busy, she is grading papers.
So how many papers can she grade while working
in the food court?
So when she does grade papers, it
takes her about five minutes for each assignment.
So mu is just one third.
This is when she is not busy.
Proportion of when she is not busy times
how long it takes her to grade a paper, which is 60 over 5.
So that means she could do four papers per hour.
That wraps up this problem.
Like always, if you have any questions or comments,
please leave it in the discussion section below.
Thank you.