Hi, everyone.
Welcome to this recitation video.
In this video, we'll go over MicroMaster's Practice Problem
1 for Unit 4.
So the problem is basically talking about AGVs
in a factory that are breaking down.
The repair crew is situated in a single location.
So really, it's just one crew of people repairing these AGVs.
And the AGVs are breaking down at a mean rate of one per hour.
The time required to fix an AGV has
a negative exponential distribution for any crew size.
And the time required by one worker to fix the AGV
is 2 hours.
So because the crew is located in one location,
this is an M/M/1 system.
Now because you could have different sized work
crew, the more people you have, the faster it is to repair.
So mu, the repair rate is a function
of k, the number of people--
a times k. a is the proportionality constant.
And lambda is just one per hour.
And that is given.
So the first question asks us so if each crew member
costs $10 an hour and the cost of having a AGV down
is $40 per hour, what is the optimal crew size?
So let k equal the number of repair crew,
n be the number of broken AGV.
So what we know right now is this is an M/M/1 system.
mu is a times k.
So if it takes one guy 2 hours to fix it,
that means he could repair 1/2 each hour.
So that means 1/2 equals a times 1.
So a equals 1/2.
That's our proportionality constant.
So that's mu equals 1/2k.
And lambda is just 1.
Now on average, how many AGVs will be broken?
Since this is an M/M/1 system, we just apply the formula.
That N bar equals lambda over mu minus lambda.
So that's directly taken from the lecture slides for an M/M/1
system.
So that just means 1 over 1/2k minus 1 is N bar.
If you multiply the top and bottom by 2,
you have 2 over k minus 2.
So the expected cost is so $10 per crew member
per hour plus $40 per AGV per hour, multiply
by the average number, which is this guy right there,
[INAUDIBLE] down, which is 2 over k minus 2.
So we're looking for the minimal cost.
So we're looking for an optimal number here.
To get the optimum, we have to find the derivative
of the cost with respect to k.
So de, dk-- we just differentiate--
equals 10 plus 10.
Actually, minus 80 over k minus 2 squared.
We set the derivative equal to 0.
Now we solve for k.
k is just 4.8.
And the problem asks us to round to the nearest whole number.
So we call it 5.
So given mu equals 1/2k, the optimal number of repair crew
is 5.
For Part 2, we're saying mu is 1/2 square root of k.
So everything else is pretty much the same.
We just run through the same process, same formula.
So N bar equals 2 over square root of k minus .
2 and the expected cost is just 10k
plus 80 over square root of k minus 2.
Once again, we look for the derivative.
de, dk equals 10 minus 80 over square root
of k minus 2 squared, multiply by 1 over 2 square root of k.
We set the derivative equal to 0.
You can solve this on your own.
k is just 9.8, or we round it to 10.
So that wraps up this recitation video.
If you have any questions, please send me an email
or leave a comment in the discussion section below.
Thank you.