Up to now, we've been discussing a single queuing system.
This could represent a machine in a factory
with work orders coming in from elsewhere in the factory.
We've seen how the waiting line grows and shrinks as orders
arrive and jobs are completed.
We've also seen the relationship between the demand
on the machine and the waiting time at that machine.
But now, we can ask another question.
Where are these work orders coming from,
and where are they going?
In most cases, manufacturing requires multiple operations
on parts at different machines.
Each of those operations will take place
at a workstation, which includes a machine or a worker, or both.
There will also be a storage area, called the buffer,
between those workstations.
Or the parts may be located at a workstation.
Or the pieces may be stored at the workstation.
The material in the buffer is referred to as work-in-process
inventory, or WIP, W-I-P. In other words,
work orders or parts travel from one queue to another,
and visit more than one station before they leave the system.
In some cases, the parts revisit the same station multiple times
for different operations.
This is especially true in semiconductor manufacturing.
There are two kinds of systems that we'll study.
First of all, there's open networks.
In open networks, customers enter and leave the system.
Lambda is known, and we must find l and w.
Closed networks are those in which the population
of the system is constant.
l is known, and we must find lambda and w.
Some examples of open networks include internet traffic.
Emergency rooms-- where you arrive,
triage decides what service you need, you go to a waiting room,
you get treatment, you get tests, and then you exit,
or you go to hospital admission.
A food court.
An airport-- you arrive, you go to a ticket counter,
you go to security, you go to passport control,
you go to your gate, and then, finally, you board the plane.
Another example is a factory in which
there's no centralized material flow
control after material enters.
Here's a food court.
Let's focus on the people that are
customers in the food court.
They enter on the left.
They go to their first food destination--
pizza or hamburgers or possibly frozen yogurt.
They wait in line.
They get their food.
And they get a tray that the food comes on,
and they carry the food on the tray to a seating area.
And they sit there, and they eat their food.
From there, they might go back to get more food
from a different restaurant, and go back to the seating area.
Or they might leave the system.
Of course, when they leave the system,
they drop off their trays.
So people are entering from outside,
and getting service, and then leaving.
And the rate of arrivals, of course,
equals the rate of departures-- at least in steady state
or over the long run.
For closed networks-- well, before we
go into other examples, let's just
think about those trays in the food court.
The trays are dispensed by the restaurants.
Customers use them, and then they drop them off someplace,
and they get washed and recycled back
to those very same restaurants.
So the number of trays in the system
stays constant, as long as nobody steals a tray.
Other examples include a factory with limited fixtures
or pallets.
Parts enter the system.
They get attached to an empty pallet.
The part and the pallet go into a buffer, which
is represented by a circle.
Then they go to other machines, which
are represented by squares, and then
travel to other buffers and other machines.
And they travel all throughout the system.
And then, at the final stage, the part
gets disassembled from the empty pallet.
The part leaves, and the pallet goes
into an empty pallet buffer, ready to get
attached to the next part.
So the number of parts in the system
may increase and decrease over time, but the number of pallets
always stays constant.
Another example is a factory in which the amount of material
is controlled by keeping the number of items in the factory
constant.
When the number of items in the factory
reaches a certain number, no additional items
are allowed to enter until one of those items leaves.
Queuing networks are often modeled as Jackson networks,
which are really generalizations of the kind of queuing models
that we talked about earlier.
Jackson networks are relatively easy to compute
performance measures with.
Those performance measures include capacity, average time
in the system, average queue lengths.
We can use them to provide intuition,
and we'll show an example later.
They're easy to optimize and to use for design.
They're valid, or a good approximation,
for a large class of systems.
However, not all.
An important limitation is that storage areas
must be assumed to be infinite, which means that blocking is
assumed not to happen.
Blocking occurs if a storage area which is finite
becomes full.
Then, any station that needs to put its parts into that area
is forced to be idle.
This reduces productivity and efficiency.
Frankly, the infinite buffer assumption
is made because it makes the math a lot easier.
This assumption leads to bad results
for systems with bottlenecks at locations
other than at the first station, because when there's
a bottleneck, there's going to be a large accumulation
of material.
Here's a sort of schematic diagram of an open Jackson
network.
Material arrives from outside the system at the A locations,
which stands for arrivals here, and departs from the system
at the D's.
The green squares are called nodes.
They represent machines or workstations.
They could be machines in parallel,
rather than just a single one.
And there's a storage area, or buffer, in each one.
Items arrive from outside the system
to node i according to a Poisson process with rate alpha i.
Alpha i must be positive for at least
one node, for at least one i.
When an item's service at node i is complete,
it goes to node j next with probability pij.
We define p i 0 as 1 minus the sum of the pij's, and if that's
positive, then items depart from the network at node i.
p i 0 must be positive for at least one i.
We will focus on the special case
in which each node has a single server
with exponential processing time.
The service rate of node i is mu i.
So the system is defined by the alphas--
the arrival rates in the network, the mus--
the service rates of the machines, and the pij's--
the routing probabilities.
The goal of the analysis is to determine
if the system is feasible--
that is, if the arrival rates are within the capacity
of the system.
Also to determine how much inventory
is in the system on the average, and how it's distributed.
And to determine the average waiting time at each node,
and the average time a part spends
in the system as a whole.
The stations need not have the same utilization.
It's possible that the rate of flow
of materials to some stations exceeds their capacity.
If there is at least one station like that,
the system is not feasible.
So let's define a new quantity called lambda.
That's the total arrival rate of items to node i.
This includes items entering the network
at node i and items coming to node i from all other nodes.
We need lambda in order to calculate the waiting
times and the inventories.
pij lambda j is the portion of the flow
that arrives at node j that goes on to node i.
Then, lambda i is equal to alpha i plus the sum of pji lambda j.
That's another way of saying that lambda i is
equal to the arriving flow from outside plus the sum of all
the flows that come from all other nodes in the network
to node i directly.
It's convenient to write this in matrix form.
So we'll define lambda as the vector of the lambda i's, alpha
the vector of the alpha i's, and capital P the matrix of pij.
In that case, lambda is equal to alpha plus P transpose lambda.
We can use this equation to determine lambda.
Solving for lambda, that becomes lambda equals 1 minus P
transpose the matrix inversed times alpha.
Notice that this equation does not
have the service rates in it.
There are no mus in this equation.
Now, to calculate the probability distribution
of all the distributions of material throughout the system,
we can write the following.
If lambda i is less than mu i for each i,
we define rho i as the fraction lambda i over mu i--
that's the utilization of station i--
and pi i of n i is equal to 1 minus rho i times rho i
to the n i.
This is the solution of an M/M/1 queue with arrival rate lambda
i calculated on the previous slide,
and service rate mu i specified by the problem data.
We're not deriving this here.
We're simply stating it.
If lambda i is greater than or equal to mu i for some i,
the demand is not feasible.
The system cannot handle the demand placed on it.
Pi of n1 n2 up to nk is the probability distribution,
the steady-state probability that there
are n i items at node i, i equals 1 through k.
The probability distribution for the entire system
is just the product of all the pi i's from the previous slide.
At each node i, n i bar is equal to rho i over 1 minus rho i.
The solution is in product form.
It says that the probability of the system
being in a given state is the product of the probabilities
of the queues at each state being
in the corresponding state at that queue.
This exact formula is the reason the Jackson network
model is of interest.
It is relatively easy to use to calculate the performance
of a complex system.
The product form solution actually
holds for some more general cases.
However, it has one major restriction.
It's restricted to models of systems with unlimited storage
space.
It cannot model blocking.
It's a good approximation for systems
where blocking is rare-- for example, when the arrival
rate of the material is much less than the capacity
of the system.
It will not work so well where blocking occurs often.