Consider a manufacturing company that buys raw material
from a supplier.
The company uses this material to make the products
they sell to customers.
How often should they order this raw material,
and how much should they order?
The motivation is the economy of scale in ordering.
We have to consider the trade-off
between the cost of ordering and the cost of holding inventory.
Each time an order is placed, the company
incurs a fixed cost in addition to the cost of the goods.
This motivates infrequent ordering.
The order must be large enough to satisfy demand
until the next order is placed.
This determines how much inventory must be stored.
Storage costs money.
Large orders lead to large inventories.
This motivates frequent ordering.
We will make a lot of assumptions now
that will lead to a very simple mathematical problem.
First of all, there is no randomness.
So demand is constant and predictable and so forth
and machines never break down.
Nothing random ever happens.
Also, there's no delay between the ordering and arrival
of goods.
There are no backlogs.
Since there's no randomness, there's
no reason why there should ever be a backlog.
Goods are required at an annual rate of lambda units per year.
Inventory is therefore depleted at the rate
of lambda units per year.
We're going to refer to lambda as the demand rate,
and it's constant.
It costs h dollars to store one unit for one year.
H is the holding cost in units of dollars per unit per year.
Holding cost is determined primarily
by the cost of warehouse space Holding cost is determined
primarily by the cost of warehouse space
and possibly by the finance cost and the loss of value
for products that spend a long time in storage.
If the company orders Q units, it
must pay s plus cQ for the order.
S is the ordering cost in dollars.
C is the unit cost in dollars per unit.
The ordering cost is determined by the vendor.
For example, the vendor may have to do an expensive set up
to make your product.
It may also be affected by your own administrative costs.
The graph on the left shows the cost of an order of Q items.
There's ordering cost, which is indicated.
And after that, the cost is linear in the number of items.
The graph on the right is the per unit cost.
It's the total cost of the batch divided
by the size of the batch.
You can see that for small batches, it's extremely high,
but then it drops off very rapidly.
A problem is to find a strategy for ordering
materials that will minimize the total cost per year.
There are two costs to consider-- the annual ordering
costs and the annual holding cost.
Please look at the graph on Slide 52
on paper or on another screen, if you have it,
while we work on this slide and the next couple.
At time 0, the inventory level 0.
Q units are ordered, and the inventory level
jumps instantaneously to Q because the order arrives
instantaneously.
Material is depleted at rate lambda.
Since the problem is totally deterministic,
we can wait until the inventory goes
to zero before we order next.
There is no danger that the inventory
will go to zero earlier than we expected to.
Because of the very simple assumptions,
we can assume that the optimal strategy does not
change over time.
Therefore, the policy is to order Q each time
the inventory goes to zero.
The same Q. We must determine the optimal Q.
The inventory is depleted at a constant rate,
and it takes T time units to get from the full inventory
to an empty inventory.
Since it's depleted at rate lambda,
that time is Q over lambda.
And the ordering times are 0 and T, and 2T, and 3T,
and so forth.
Since the inventory goes from Q to 0 at a constant rate,
the average inventory is just Q over 2.
The number of orders in a year is
1 over T, which is lambda over Q. Therefore,
the ordering cost in a year is s lambda over Q
The average inventory is Q over 2.
Therefore, the average inventory holding cost is hQ over 2.
Therefore, we must minimize the total annual cost
which is hQ over 2 plus s lambda over Q.
Notice that both terms have units of dollars per year.
The cost per item does not enter into this cost.
Consequently, it will not enter into the formula
for optimal order size.
Does this seem odd?
We take the derivative of that total cost with respect to Q
and set it to 0.
And that leads us to the EOQ formula--
the optimal queue is equal to the square root
of 2 s lambda over h.
We're going to show some graphs now.
In the base cases, lambda equals 3,000, s is 0.001
and h equals 6.
Notice that in this case, the optimal Q is equal to 1.
This graph shows the annual cost versus order size, "Q"
for different s's.
In each case there's a well-defined minimum cost
and that determines Q star.
This is the graph of Q star versus lambda.
The higher the demand rate, the larger
the optimal order size is.
This shows the optimal order size
as function of "s," the ordering cost.
Clearly as s goes up, Q star also goes up.
That's because we want to order less frequently,
and ordering less frequently means
that we have larger batches.
Here's the optimal order size as a function of "h,"
the holding costs.
This graph shows the larger the holding cost, the smaller
the optimal ordering size.
That's because we want to have smaller inventories,
and we can have that only by having smaller orders.
Let's go back to the question why
the per unit cost of raw material
doesn't enter into the EOQ formula.
Isn't the per unit cost of material important?
Of course it is, but not for this problem.
The cost of raw materials must be considered
when determining the cost of producing the product,
and they're a major factor in setting the sale
price of the finished product.
That will affect the demand of product.
The only cost we have to consider,
explicitly, are the cost of ordering and the holding cost.
The cost of raw material might enter this problem indirectly
through the cost of ordering or the holding cost.
For example, if the value of the raw material
diminishes rapidly while it's in storage,
the raw material cost, or it's rate of loss of value
may enter into the calculation of holding cost h.