The purpose of an operation in the manufacturing process
is to bring a work piece closer to a state in which it
can be sold.
The design of processes and machines
to implement those processes is obviously important,
but it's not the subject of this course.
We're interested in how the characteristics of operations
affect the flow of material through the production process.
We'll be concerned with discrete parts
manufacturing, not production that
involves the flow of fluids.
This leaves out oil refining and other chemical processes.
We'll start with a very basic view of a typical operation.
There are many kinds of processes,
but they have certain features in common.
For example, they all take a work piece into a work area.
The piece spends some time in there, and then it leaves.
Many processes also take consumables,
such as cooling fluid for metal cutting or chemicals
for semiconductor fabrication.
Most operations require a machine,
and some need a human operator.
Operations also generate waste.
For example, metal cutting operations create metal chips,
and also have used contaminated fluid to dispose of.
This is generic and typical.
There are operations that differ in some details.
For example, assembly processes take more than one kind of part
in and send a single part out.
One thing they have in common is that the operation cannot take
place until all the required items are present at the same
place at the same time.
The requirements include a place to put
the completed part and the mechanism
to dispose of the waste.
If there are no parts for the machine to work on,
we say that it is starved.
If the next destination for the parts is not available for some
reason-- for example, if a storage buffer is full--
we say the operation is blocked.
The operation could be prevented if the operator is not there,
or if the machine is under repair or maintenance.
The important point is that nothing happens
until everything is present.
If any one of these items is absent,
the operation must wait until the missing one arrives.
Whatever does not arrive last must wait.
Idleness is a loss of some of the productive capability
of a component of the factory.
This is undesirable.
One goal of manufacturing systems engineering
is to minimize unnecessary waiting.
But because of the complexity and variability of a factory,
it's impossible to eliminate all the waiting.
Therefore, we want the most valuable components
to wait the least.
There are different names for different things waiting.
Inventory is parts waiting.
If raw material is expensive, inventory
is expensive, so we emphasize minimizing inventory.
There are other reasons as well, which we'll discuss later.
If capital investment is expensive,
we emphasize maximizing machine utilization.
So when machines are waiting, we call that underutilization.
When operators are waiting, we'll
describe that as an idle workforce.
If workers must be highly skilled and expensively
trained, we emphasize keeping them busy.
Reductions in the availability or
increased variability in the availability
of any of these items increasing waiting in the rest of them
and reduces the performance of the system.
When an operation is prevented from taking place
for any reason, that stoppage can propagate and cause
idleness at other parts of the factory.
For example, if a machine is under repair for a long time,
work pieces can accumulate in the storage area
upstream of it.
If that buffer becomes full, one or more operations
upstream of that machine may become blocked and prevented
from working.
Similarly, if a machine is down long enough,
a storage area downstream may be depleted,
and this may cause starvation in downstream work stations.
Now we're going to describe some standard system architectures.
A flow line is a sequence of machines and buffers.
Parts arrive from outside the system at the first machine.
After a part's operation is completed at that machine,
it goes to a storage buffer and stays
there until the next machine is available.
It gets an operation of the second machine,
and then goes to the second buffer,
and then to the third machine, and so forth.
Since all of the parts require operations
on the same machines in the same sequence,
the parts are generally very similar or identical
to one another.
This is therefore used for low variety manufacturing.
High volume is often low variety.
The high volume justifies the investment
in machines that are dedicated to a small number of part
types, possibly just one.
Why are there buffers?
They are there because machines fail.
If there were no buffers, the failure of one machine
would stop all the others very quickly.
With buffers, if one machine stops,
the machine upstream can keep working
until the buffer between them fills up, and is
therefore blocked.
If the machine that's stopped starts up again
before the buffer is full, the upstream machine
does not have to stop.
Also, the machine downstream can keep
working until the buffer between them
becomes empty, which means that it's starved.
If work resumes before that buffer empties,
the downstream machine's work is not interrupted.
Stoppages can be due to failures, maintenance,
blockages, or starvations.
Blockages and starvations lead to the propagation
of the original disruption.
Consequently, larger buffers lead
to less propagation, and therefore higher production
rates.
However, larger buffers lead to greater cost of inventory
and the space allocated to holding inventory.
This means that there's a trade-off between inventory
costs and production rate.
We will examine that trade-off in the second part
of this course.
Let's see a system like this in action.
This is a representation of the kind of flow line
we were just talking about, where
we have a sequence of machines and buffers.
The machines are unreliable, so they go up and down.
When they're up, they're white.
When they're down, they're red.
The buffers can hold up to 25 parts.
And the little green squares inside them
represent the parts they have.
And you'll see the movement of parts in there.
What you should also see is that when a machine fails,
the upstream buffer starts to fill up,
and the downstream buffer, if it has any parts in it,
will start to empty.
So let's go.
We've made the machines a little bit more unreliable
than you'd probably see in a real factory,
just so that we can get to see some action going on.
In this model, all the machines have the same operation time.
And the time that we're counting is the number
of operations time since the beginning of the simulation.
You can see that this is a pretty inefficient system,
because we've already reached time 110,
and there are only 39 parts produced.
Factory seems to be having a run of bad luck with all
those machines down.
Oh.
Getting back up.
OK.
Maybe we've seen all we need to see.
For our purposes, an assembly system
can be thought of as a generalization of the flow line
that we just talked about.
The difference here is that assembly machines
take different parts from different buffers
to do their operations.
Consequently, they can be starved
if any one of the upstream buffers is empty.
Here's a very complex assembly.
You can see how many different operations.
Each of those little dots represent an operation.
And there's very, very many parts.
Some factories involve looping flow,
in which parts or other items visit the same machines more
than once.
Determining the performance of these systems
must take this into account.
Here, parts or fixtures travel in a closed loop.
The routes are determined.
The number of pallets in the loop is constant.
We saw this kind of loop in the HP example.
Parts are attached to pallets or fixtures
as they enter the system.
Essentially, the first operation is the assembly
of a part and a pallet.
This assembly visits the machines
and waits in the buffers between them
just like in the flow line.
The last machine is a disassembly.
The part exits the system and the pallet
is recycled back to the first machine.
The motivation for this is that the part only
has to be attached to the pallet once,
instead of being attached to fixturing at each station.
This reduces the danger of damage to the part.
In addition, the fixturing at each station
is simplified, because it is the same for all the stations.
This also makes it easier to deal with different part types.
This also limits inventory, because the number
of parts in the system is less than or equal to the number
of pallets.
Now, the number of pallets enters
into the trade-off between inventory and production rate.
A second kind of loop, which is called reentrant,
has parts returning to machines they have visited before
to get more operations.
This is a schematic of a system that produces two part types.
The first one that we're showing here
has a simple flow, like a flow line.
After the part gets its fourth operation,
it leaves the system.
The second part type has a more complex path.
After it gets its fourth operation,
it goes back to the first machine for a fifth operation,
and then to machines 2, 3, and 4 again.
Then it leaves.
The routes are determined.
The number of parts in the loop varies.
Semiconductor fabrication is highly reentrant.
Semiconductor chips have multiple layers,
and each layer gets similar operations.
It's cheaper to use one machine for all the similar operations
on different layers than to have different machines
for those operations on each layer.
The downside of this is that the management of the system
is much more complicated than the ones we've already seen.
Another extension of the flow line is a rework loop.
This is a common kind of material flow.
There's an inspection station.
Features of parts are measured to determine their quality
at that station.
If the quality is acceptable, the part moves on.
If the quality is not acceptable,
but the error is repairable, the part
goes back to get the operation redone,
and may have to get another operation first,
to undo the bad operation.
If the error is not acceptable and not repairable,
the part is rejected and scrapped.
There are actually two reasons for inspection.
One is to prevent bad parts from reaching customers.
The second is to detect where are other deterioration
on the machines that did the operations whose results
are inspected.
This may trigger a repair or maintenance
of the faulty machine.
In this kind of system, the routes are random.
The number of parts in the loop varies.
And the system is already described.
The part variety is low, and the volume is high.
This allows the factory to be organized according
to the sequence of operations.
Job shops are different.
They deliver a wide variety of parts, often in small batches.
It is not cost effective to dedicate a set of machines
to a small batch of parts that may not be ordered again.
The machines are not organized according to the process flow,
because there is no common process flow.
Often, instead, machines are grouped by department--
a mill department, a lathe department, and so forth.
There's a great variety of products.
Different products follow different paths.
And the management of this system is complex.