Everybody knows that storage and inventory
are important in businesses.
But in fact, let's step back a second
and observe that storage is really
fundamental in nature as well as management
and also engineering.
In nature, energy is stored.
Life can only exist if the acquisition of energy
can occur at a different time from the expenditure of energy.
In fact, I'm guessing that at least some of the people
watching this video are not eating.
Those people are using their stored energy.
In management, products are stored.
In engineering, energy is stored in springs, in batteries,
in capacitors, in inductors, and so forth.
Information is stored in RAM and hard disks.
Water is stored in dams and reservoirs.
Storage has cost as well as benefits.
We will discuss both in the set of slides.
The purpose of storage is to allow
systems to survive even when important events are
unsynchronized--
for example, the separation in time
from the acquisition or production of something
and its consumption, the occurrence of an event at one
location such as a machine failure or a power
surge which can prevent desired performance
or do damage at another.
Storage improves system performance
by decoupling parts of the system from one another.
Unsynchronization is what makes storage necessary.
Randomness causes unsynchronization,
but we will see that deterministic systems can
have unsynchronized components as well.
And such systems can require storage.
Storage allows production systems of energy of goods
to be built with capacity less than the peak demand.
In particular, it helps manage seasonality.
Factories or businesses who get their greatest revenue
from Christmas sales start production
during the summer or earlier.
Consequently, they have to store lots of inventory,
and they have to store it for a long time.
Their peak demand occurs in the last month before Christmas,
and that demand rate is much greater than the demand rate
during the rest of the year.
They would probably prefer to start production
in November if they could.
That would reduce their inventory costs,
and it would allow them to have much more accurate sales
forecasts.
So why don't they?
They don't, because if they started Christmas production
in November, they would need much greater production
capacity, much bigger factories, or many more factories.
They would have to produce at a much greater production rate
during last month, and most of those facilities
would be idle for most of the year.
That idle production capacity would be very expensive.
Similarly, the cost of power plants
depends mainly on their peak energy generation rate.
Energy demand varies during the day
and is not at its peak all day and night.
If plants could be built to produce constantly
at the daily average of demand rate,
they would be much less expensive.
But this is only possible if there were energy storage
facilities available.
Storage of energy will become much more important
as renewable energy replaces fossil fuels.
The sun and the wind generate useful energy only
intermittently.
For renewables to be effective, they
would have to generate energy at a greater rate than demand
while they're producing, and that temporary excess of what
they're producing over demand would be saved for periods
when they're not producing.
It reduces the propagation of disturbances,
and thus reduces the instability and the fragility
of complex, expensive systems.
As we've already discussed, if a machine is stopped
for a long time, it will cause neighboring machines
to be idle if there's little inventory or inventory space.
We will see this in greater detail later in the course.
Let's be a little specific about the benefits
and costs of inventory in factories-- first,
the benefits.
Storage allows economies of scale--
in particular, in volume purchasing.
Per item prices are always less for large orders
than for small batches, but if you
buy something in a large batch, you
need to store it before you can use all of it.
Reduced set-ups-- set-ups diminish the time
in which machines can produce.
This motivates infrequent set-ups.
However, to have infrequent set-ups,
you must have large batches, and that means you have storage.
It helps manage uncertainty, including
the random arrival of customers or orders
and unreliable deliveries of raw materials.
Suppose you knew the average daily demand for an item.
No day's demand will be exactly that average.
A reasonable production strategy would
be to make sure that each day you
have on hand the average demand plus a small quantity called
"safety stock."
If anything is unsold at the end of the day,
you can use it to meet the demand the next day.
Now the costs-- the first cost is financial.
Raw materials are paid for, but no revenue comes in
until the item is sold.
If you borrow money to pay for raw material,
you incur interest which you can't pay back until you
sell the goods you make.
The more inventory you hold, the longer it
takes to get it through the factory,
and the more you have to pay in interest.
Demand risk-- an item loses value or is unsold
due to obsolescence-- for example, newspapers,
technology, fashion goods.
In addition, there's holding cost and shrinkage.
"Shrinkage" means damage, or theft, or spoilage, or loss.
Here we're going to show how unsynchronized variability
causes inventory.
This is a picture of a tank that holds water.
Water comes in at a rate of 75 gallons a second,
and water can leave at a rate of 75 gallons a second.
If we start with an empty tank, the tank
is always empty except for a little bit
of splashing around the bottom.
But now let's add a little randomness.
We'll put a valve in the pipe carrying water in and one
in the pipe carrying water out.
The valves are open sometimes and closed other times,
but on the average, they carry the same volume
of water per time as in the previous slide.
When they're open, water can pass through them
at a rate of 100 gallons per second.
Of course, when they're closed, no water passes through them.
The average period when the valve is open is 15 minutes.
The average period when it's close to five minutes.
Consequently, the average flow rate through it
is 75 gallons per second.
Let's look at some of the possibilities that
can happen in this case.
First of all, both valves can be closed.
If they're both closed, no water comes in or goes out.
The amount of water that's in the tank
is staying constant during this period.
How it got to the level it got depends
on the past history of the valves being opened and closed.
The second case is where the first valve is open
and the second one is closed.
In that case, water enters the tank but can't get out,
so the water level in the tank rises.
On the contrary, we can have the first valve closed
and the second valve open in which case nothing comes in,
but water comes out as long as there's water in the tank.
When there's no more water in the tank, it's empty.
And finally, both valves can be open at the same time, in which
case 100 gallons per second goes in and 100 gallons per second
goes out.
The water level stays constant during that period.
So what can we observe from this illustration?
There was never any water in the tank
when the flow is constant in the first case.
Of course, there's a little bit of splashing,
but let's not worry about that.
There's sometimes water in the tank when the flow is variable.
Conclusions-- a very general conclusion first.
You can't always replace random variables with their averages
for the purpose of predicting the behavior of a system.
Sometimes you can.
It depends on the nature of the system,
the nature of the variability, and the quantity
you're trying to predict.
But the main point for us is that variability
causes inventory.
To be more precise, non-synchronization
Living things do not acquire energy
at the same time they expend it, therefore,
they must store energy in the form of fat or sugar.
Rivers are dammed and reservoirs are
created to control the flow of water
to reduce the variability of the water supply.
For solar and wind power to be successful,
energy storage is required for when the sun doesn't shine
and the wind doesn't blow.
To wrap up this video, let's list some of the topics
we're going to talk about--
first of all, the news vendor problem where we have demand
risk although no inventory dynamics.
There's the economic order quantity problem--
deals purely with economies of scale,
and the demand is deterministic.
The QR policy adds to the economic order quantity
problem, the supplier lead time, and random demand.
We'll describe a base stock policy
for managing a simple factory in order to avoid stockouts,
and there will be a few other topics.