Hi, everyone.
This is Jack here.
Welcome to Week 7.
This week, we will be introducing Matlab online.
So if you go to the Week 7 tab, there
is a drop-down where it says DET2TL.
That means Deterministic Two-Machine Line.
If you click on that, there will be an introduction
on how to use this tool.
So the first tab explains what are the inputs to this program.
Essentially, you have five inputs.
R1, which is the repair rate of machine 1.
P1 is the failure rate of machine 1.
R2, repair rate of machine 2.
P2 is the failure rate of machine 2.
N is the buffer size.
What this Matlab program does is, given these five inputs,
it will calculate what the production rate of the line is
and what is the average buffer level.
We're going to use this program to solve Practice Problem 2
and Graded Assignment 2.
So let me show you the program and how it works.
So on the second tab, this is a description
of what this code does.
Here is the script.
Now, the code itself is an m-file.
It's a function file that is uploaded to this interface.
It's DET2.
That's what the program is.
So the gray area--
the rows are highlighted in gray--
those are locked.
You cannot change these values.
But what's in white, you could change.
And you can feel free to add additional lines of code
down here.
It's just like an desktop version of Matlab.
So for those of you who are not familiar with Matlab,
I'm going to demonstrate how to run the code.
So we have some inputs here.
R1-- well everything is 0.01, other than P2, which is 0.05.
You could change these inputs.
These are what you put into the program.
So we could change P2 to 0.03 and N to 5--
15, and hit Run Script.
OK.
And we have our output.
Production rate is 0.1247, and M bar is 9.6.
So the average inventory is 9.6, and the production rate
is 0.1247 parts per time unit.
Now, we could change N to 20, for example.
So by changing N to 20, our production rate
should actually increase, because you're
decreasing the probability of starving and blocking.
So now it's 0.1285.
In the practice problem and the graded problem,
we're going to ask you to run an optimization.
By varying N, what is the optimal balance
between cost and profit?
So for those of you who are familiar with Matlab
you can feel free to do one of two things.
First, you could run a for loop and just index N
to get your optimal solution.
Or, the optimization toolbox is actually available.
You could use something like fminbound or whatever you want.
fminbound is recommended for single-variate optimization.
And for those of you who are not familiar with Matlab,
the homework assignment is quite simple.
We suggest that students think about,
what are some clever ways of guessing and reach N.
So you could do something like the golden search,
or for root finding, there's the bisectional method.
You could generate an estimate of the derivative
by taking differences, just small differences,
using finite difference to get a derivative approximation
and iterate until the difference becomes 0.
So these are just suggestions.
You could use whatever method you'd like.
And as always, leave me an email or leave a note
in the discussion down below if you have questions.
Now, this tool is embedded in the practice problem
and the graded problem as well.
So you don't have to reference back to this window
if you're doing a problem with a different window.
Great.
Let me know if you have any questions.
Oh, by the way, the semicolon is there
so the inputs don't get printed out anymore.
If you remove the semicolon in the output window,
R1 and P1 would just get printed again.