Inventory is a major issue in every factory.
We show how some inventory is inevitable
when variability is present in a system of flows.
Inventory is necessary for a factory
to meet some of its performance goals.
Such as having products available
when customers want them, or meeting a specified production
rate target.
However, it has costs.
We will describe some inventory models
that deal with issues such as, the trade off
between the risk of having too little inventory to satisfy
all customers, and having too much so that some items are
unsold.
We will look at economies of scale.
When is it worthwhile to buy or make more
than you expect to need immediately because of reduced
per item costs, even though doing so adds storage costs?