OK, let's talk about the densities and distributions
of continuous random variables.
Let's start with one dimensional systems.
In one dimension, capital F of x is the cumulative probability
distribution of X. If F of x is the probability that capital
X is less than little x.
Remember capital X is the random variable,
and little x is a value.
So it's the probability of being on the heavy line that's
indicated over here.
Little f of x is the density function of X
if capital F is the integral of little f.
Whenever capital F is differentiable, then little f
is the derivative of capital F.
So here are some important facts.
Little f of x delta x is approximately the probability
of x being between little x and little x plus delta
x if delta x is sufficiently small.
And that is if x is in this little tiny interval here.
Of course, capital F of b minus capital F of a
is just the integral of little f between a and b.
And the definition of expected value
is just the integral from minus infinity and plus
infinity of t times f of t.
Remember, the expected value or the mean or the average
has the same meaning as it does in the case
of the discrete random variables.
Now, there are certain important random variables
that we need to pay attention to.
First of all, there's the Gaussian
or normal random variable.
The density function is given by that formula there.
And this is the standard normal that has mean of 0
and variance of 1.
And we'll talk about the more general normal.
The normal distribution function,
which is again the probability that our random variable is
between minus infinity and little
x, that normal distribution function
is just the integral of f.
Unfortunately, there's no closed form expression for f of x.
So the best we can do is find it on tables or things like that.
And here are the graphs of the density function
above and the distribution function.
The distribution function has this very characteristic shape,
in which it goes to 0 when x is sufficiently negative.
It goes to 1 when x is sufficiently
large and positive.
And it increases monotonically between 0 and 1.
All distribution functions have the shape,
but the details are different.
The notation that people use is capital
N of mu comma sigma square is the normal distribution
with mean mu and variance sigma square.
Notation is not always uniform, so sometimes people
write N of mu and sigma rather than sigma square
for the same thing.
If X and Y are both normal, then aX
plus bY plus c is also normal.
If X is normal with mean mu and variance sigma square,
then X minus mu over sigma is normal with mean 0
and variance 1, the standard normal.
So this is why it's very easy to compute
the general mean from the specific standard normal.
And that's why you'll see N 0, 1,
the standard normal tabulated in books.
Related distributions are truncated normal distributions.
And things get a little bit messy,
but unfortunately this is what things often are in real life.
The normal distribution allows the random variable
to go negative.
But in some cases, you have situations
where the actual quantity that you're dealing with
can only be positive.
For example, in a few lectures when we talk about inventory,
we're going to talk about the news vendor problem,
and we're going to approximate the demand for newspapers
on a given day with a normal distribution.
But, of course, the demand for newspapers on any day
is never going to be negative.
You can truncate the normal in a couple of different ways.
One is to simply take all the probability that
would be assigned to negative numbers
and distribute them all around and distribute that probability
to the positive numbers, in which case
the truncated normal density is given by this formula,
just the normal density divided by 1 minus F of zero.
It's important to remember that the parameters mu and sigma are
the mean and standard deviation of the original normal, which
is being truncated, not the resulting
truncated normal distribution.
And those are a little more complicated to calculate.
The other kind of truncation is where you simply
assign all of the probability that would go to negative X.
Assign that to 0.
And so we have a probability mass at 0.
In that case, the normal density and normal distribution
is the same as the truncated normal density and distribution
for positive X, but not for negative X. Again, mu
and sigma are the parameters of the original normal
distribution, not the truncated distribution.
In both cases, for both kinds of truncations, the densities
as well as the distributions are close to the densities
and distributions of the original normal
when mu is much greater than sigma and not otherwise.
That's because if mu is much greater than sigma,
the probability of a normal random variable being negative
is very, very small.
Now, we have the law of large numbers, which
is one of the reasons why the normal distribution
is so important and why it's especially
important for statistics.
So we define X to be a sequence of independent,
identically distributed random variables--
that's often abbreviated iid--
that have finite mean mu.
And Sn is going to be the sum of the first n
of those random variables.
So Sn is just the sum from X1 to Xn.
Then, for every epsilon greater than 0, what this says
is that in the limit, as we sum a large number of numbers--
that's n going to infinity--
the probability that the average differs
from the mean of those random variables, the probability
of that difference is greater than epsilon and absolute value
goes to 0.
OK, what does that mean?
That means that as n goes to infinity,
S over n is unlikely to be further than any given
number from 0 and gets less and less likely
as n goes to infinity.
Eventually, when n goes to infinity,
that probability becomes 0.
So this says that that average, S of n over n,
gets close to mu.
So to summarize it, the average approaches the mean.
The central limit theorem is another theory
about the sum of independent identically distributed
random variables.
And it becomes particularly important for statistics again.
So this is a little bit more complicated looking.
But what it says is that we take that sum,
subtract off n times the mean and divide it by something.
And then when we do that, that probability distribution
approaches the standard normal distribution.
So what it says is that if we take some linear function
of the sum of those random variables,
we'll get a normal distribution.
Let's define An as Sn over n, which is
the average of the first n Xs.
So that statement of the theorem is
equivalent to saying that as n approaches infinity,
the probability distribution of the average
approaches the normal distribution
with a certain mean and variance.
This is important for statistics,
because we want to add up a large number of numbers
and take their average and find out
that that's close to the mean.
What this tells us is how many we
need to add up in order to get within a certain distance
from the mean with a given probability.
OK, here are some examples of coin flips again,
but it also shows us how we're approaching
the normal distribution.
So here, we're going back to our coin flips.
We have a fair coin, and we're taking more and more flips
of the coin.
And you can see that those distributions are starting
to look like normal distributions
as n gets larger and larger.
In this case, we're back to the same picture
that we showed some time earlier.
We have an unfair coin with a probability of 0.4,
and we did hundred coin flips.
And this certainly looks a lot like a normal distribution.
In these cases, we have a smaller probability
of getting heads.
And as a result, the probability distributions
look like a truncated normal distribution
as we take a larger and larger number of samples.
Here's what when we have a normal density
function in two dimensions.
Now we have two variables.
And the vertical axis is the density,
which is the probability of finding
the sample within a small rectangle
in that plane times the area of that rectangle.