This is the first of two videos on Kanban.
Some people who are only superficially
aware of the Toyota production system
think that kanban is the Toyota production system.
It is a key part, but it's not the whole system.
Kanban is an information system for controlling production
quantity and timing.
It's important to recognize that material is not the only thing
that flows in a factory.
Information flows as well.
The flow of information is important
for the efficient operation of a factory.
The information conveyed by kanbans
is about when a process is completed in an operation
and about when a process needs material to work on.
Kanban means card.
It was originally implemented as an actual card,
but it can have other forms.
It could be represented by a container for material
or it could be a virtual card in a computer network.
A withdrawal kanban describes the quantity
that a subsequent process must withdraw.
A production-ordering kanban describes the quantity
that a preceding process must produce.
We'll describe these in more detail later
and will mention others kanbans as well.
Kanbans circulate within factories
as low-level shop floor control and between factories.
In other production control systems,
schedules are issued to all processes.
We discussed the difference between pull and push systems
in the previous video.
In push control systems, schedules
are issued to all processes.
But push systems cannot easily adapt to demand fluctuations,
disruptions, and so forth.
This leads to excessive inventory.
Inventory can actually reduce some
of the effects of randomness and variable, but it has a cost.
It's better to reduce the randomness
and variability themselves.
Kanban is a pull system.
When demand changes occur, it's enough to notify
the final assembly.
All proceeding stages learn about schedule changes
through the kanban system.
It's not necessary to issue updated detailed schedules
at each stage.
Each stage notifies its upstream neighbor,
Kanbans coordinate production without disruption propagation
caused by scheduling changes.
Kanbans allow systems to operate based
on local real-time information.
The number of kanbans at each stage
determines the maximum inventory at that stage.
They can be one card for each part
or one card for a batch of parts.
This slide is very similar to one presented
in the first week of this course,
but we've added something new-- kanbans.
Now, in order for the operation to take place,
there must be a kanban present as well as everything else.
There must also be a place to put
the kanban after the operation is completed.
But this will not be an issue for now
because we will assume that the kanban buffers are infinite.
Kanbans function as a part of the control
system that prevents operations from taking place.
Why would we ever want to prevent an operation
from taking place?
Kanbans reduce production rates in a controlled way,
and as a result, reduce inventory.
In the following discussion of kanban systems,
each square is going to represent
an individual machine, a multi-machine work
cell, or a subprocess consisting of several cells.
It could be an entire factory.
Flow into and out of the square need not
be the same as that of any other square at the same time.
The movement of kanbans can be more complex
than described here.
The kanbans are used to signal when production is needed.
They can also have other information
on them describing the part that they're associated with.
We will discuss one-card systems now and two-card kanban systems
in the next video.
In this video, we have these squares that I mentioned,
which will be used to represent machines where operations
are taking place.
Here's a buffer.
This big circle is the work-in-process buffer,
a WIP buffer.
This is the kanban buffer up here.
We refer to the machine on the left as the first machine
or the upstream machine of the line.
The machine on the right is the second or downstream machine.
First, let's consider the dynamics
of the upstream machine.
The upstream machine is able to do an operation when
its previous operation or downtime is completed,
when there's a kanban in the kanban buffer
and a part is available to work on.
After the operation, the kanban is attached to the part
and they move to the WIP buffer together.
The upstream cycle repeats.
The upstream machine performs an operation,
and then does an assembly-- the card to the part.
It could equally go in the other direction.
The part and the kanban go into the buffer together.
The operation does not happen if there's
no part arriving from outside or, for our purposes,
more importantly, if the kanban buffer is empty.
Now, let's focus on the downstream machine.
When the previous operation or downtime
of the downstream machine is completed
and the machine is not blocked, the downstream machine
takes a part from the WIP buffer.
It removes the kanban and puts it in the kanban buffer.
It does the operation on the part and the part
is sent to its next production step,
and the downstream cycle repeats.
If the downstream buffer goes down,
it does not take any parts from the WIP buffer
and it does not add any kanbans to the kanban buffer
while it's down.
If the first machine remains operational,
it can continue to work.
It removes cards from the kanban buffer
and adds parts with kanbans attached to the WIP buffer.
The upstream machine can keep operating
until there are no more kanbans in the kanban buffer.
We have not considered the possibility
that the buffer could get full and block the first machine.
In fact, we have assumed that both the kanban
buffer and the WIP buffer are infinite.
The only thing that stops production, other than failures
and so forth, at the first machine
is the kanban buffer becoming empty.
When that happens, all the kanban cards
are attached to parts which are in the WIP buffer.
Suppose there are a total of n cards.
The buffer is then holding n parts, the most parts
it can ever hold if we operate the system the way
we've described.
So instead of having actual buffers,
this policy could be implemented by a finite buffer.
If we choose the buffer size to be n, the behavior of the line
would be the same as what we've described.
Many factories do this, some by painting areas on the shop
floor for WIP storage, others by reserving a specific amount
of shelf space.
When the painted area is full, the upstream machine
is blocked and has to wait.
Now, let's consider a long line consisting
of many machines and buffers connected in the same way.
If the last machine stops for a long enough time,
it can prevent the next to last from working.
If the stoppage lasts long enough,
the machine upstream of that can be
prevented from working in the same way, and so forth.
We can think of the last machine in the line
as representing demand.
If demand is reduced, we can treat it
as an intermediate stoppage of that machine.
In that case, if the last kanban buffer becomes empty,
it prevents the next to last machine from working and making
inventory that cannot be sold.
This propagates the intermittent stoppage upstream
and this prevents any stage from producing excess inventory.
The maximum amount of inventory that any machine could make
is limited by the number of kanbans that
are allocated to that stage.