We need to make some more assumptions about machine
failures in order to analyze systems.
These assumptions are important for machines and systems
in which a machine can be made idle
by another machine's failure.
The issue is what can happen when a machine is idle.
First of all, there's operation-dependent failures.
If we assume that, a machine can only fail while it's working,
not idle.
Idleness occurs due to starvation or blockage.
This is the usual assumption.
The other assumption is time-dependent failure.
A machine can fail, even if it's idle.
We are going to assume operation-dependent failures
unless we say otherwise.
Now we can start thinking about systems of machines.
My strategy is to start with assumptions
that make models easy to analyze and then
proceed to model systems that are progressively harder
to analyze.
This process will continue into part two of this course.
The first kind of system we will analyze
are lines with infinite buffers.
Of course, we live in a finite world,
so there are no lines with infinite buffers.
So why are we studying such lines?
There are two reasons.
First, the infinite buffer assumption
gives us an upper bound on the production
rate of a line with finite buffers.
It's easy to calculate that upper bound, as you'll see.
We can also learn something from the distribution
of the inventory of such a line that
may give us some insight into the distribution of inventory
in a real line.
And lines with infinite buffers are much easier
to study than lines with finite buffers.
We'll get to those finite buffer lines later.
When buffers are infinite, the only way
that one machine can interact with another
is through starvation.
There is no blockage.
Machine Mi is starved at time t if buffer Bi minus 1--
the buffer just upstream of it--
is empty at time t.
The assumptions are that a machine is not idle
if it's not starved.
In other words, a machine works whenever
it has something to work on and is operational.
The first machine is never starved.
The first machine always has something to work on.
These two assumptions and the assumption of infinite buffers
give us an upper bound for the production rate of a line.
If you have to meet a specified target production
rate with a given set of machines,
and you calculate that you won't be
able to meet that target with infinite buffers
in these assumptions, then you won't
be able to meet it with any real line.
The assumption that the first machine is never idle
may seem to rule out the possibility of modeling
a line with an unreliable supplier,
but we can get around that.
We could use the first machine in the model of the line
as a model for the supplier and the first buffer
as the raw material inventory.
Then machine 2 in the diagram would
represent the first actual machine in the line.
The production rate of the line is the production rate
of the slowest machine in the line called the bottleneck.
Slowest means least average production rate.
The production rate is therefore given by this formula--
P is the minimum of this expression over all
the machines in the line.
That expression is just the production rate
of an individual machine.
And Mi, where the minimum occurs, is the bottleneck.
We will assume that the bottleneck is unique.
There's only one machine that has at least average production
rate.
If all the taos equals 1, then that formula
reduces to this one.
And, of course, M is still the bottleneck.
When we have a bottleneck, the system is not in steady state.
An increasing amount of inventory
accumulates in the buffer upstream of the bottleneck.
In this picture, buffer 4 and machine 5
from a queuing system with unlimited storage
in which the arrival rate to the system
is greater than the rate that can be processed
by the server, machine 5.
We've seen that already when we studied M/M/1 queues.
This is why the system cannot be in steady state.
The amount of material in buffer 4 grows over time.
A finite amount of material appears
downstream of the bottleneck.
Since machine 5 is the bottleneck,
the rate of flow of parts leaving machine 5
is less than the capacity of machine 6.
Since the rate of flow arriving at the buffer
5 machine 6 system is within the capacity of the server, machine
6, the buffer level does not grow steadily over time.
If there were more machines downstream faster than machine
5, the arrival rate to each of those machines
would be less than their capacity.
Consequently, their buffer levels
would also not grow steadily over time.
Let's do an example.
We're going to simulate this 10-machine line
with a bottleneck.
The parameters of all the machines
other than the bottleneck, which is machine 10,
are r equals 0.1 and P equals 0.01.
For machine 10, r equals 0.1, and P equals 0.03.
Therefore, the efficiencies, or production rates,
of all the machines other than machine 10 are 0.909.
And the production rate of machine 10 is 0.769.
This is a graph of the levels of each of the buffers in the line
we're simulating.
The horizontal axis is of the time, measured
in units of operation times.
The vertical axis is the amount of inventory
in all of the buffers.
All the buffer levels except that of buffer 9 remain small.
Buffer 9, the buffer upstream of the bottleneck,
increases roughly linearly over time.
It's not exactly a straight line because of the random failures
in repairs.
The buffer level grows for the reasons discussed earlier
in slide 18.
So now let's ask, what is the rate of growth of n
9, the inventory in buffer 9?
I suggest that you think about this question
before moving on to the next slide, in which I
will reveal the answer.
So pause the video and give it some thought.
So the question is, what is the rate of growth
of n9, the inventory in B9?
To get the answer, we observe that the rate that parts
arrive at buffer 9 is 0.909.
The rate that parts leave, which is the rate that machine 10 can
process them, is 0.769.
Therefore, the rate of increase is 0.909 minus 0.769,
which is 0.14 parts per operation time.
So here's a question.
What happens when the buffers are large but finite?
Let's examine that question and temporarily depart
from the infinite buffer assumption.
If you would like to test your intuition again,
pause the video and see if you can come up with a hypothesis.
The answer is the last buffer gains material
until it becomes full.
Then, the next to last buffer gains material until it
becomes full.
This process keeps repeating until all the buffers are full.
Let's take a look at the graph on the next slide.
This is a graph of the simulation of the line.
All the buffer sizes are 5,000.
The machines are the same as before.
If you compare this graph with the one on slide 20,
keep in mind that both the horizontal and vertical scales
are very different.
So what happens?
First, buffer 9 gains material at rate 0.14 and then fills up.
It gets full at roughly 35,000 or so time steps.
When buffer 9 becomes full, buffer 8
starts gaining material, also at rate 0.14
and then fills up after another 35,000 or so time steps.
This continues until each buffer gets
full from the end of the line to the beginning.
Note that the buffers do not stay exactly full.
Because of failures upstream, they lose some material.
Then they become full again because of downstream failures.
But they always stay close to full.
When buffer 1 finally becomes full, machine 1 is blocked.
Parts are prevented from entering the system.
The production rate of this line is less than 0.769,
which was the production rate of the bottleneck,
because of the parts that don't get into it.
OK.
Let's get back to infinite buffers.
The second bottleneck is the slowest machine upstream
of the bottleneck.
It's not necessarily the second slowest machine in the line.
A machine downstream of the bottleneck
could be the second slowest.
We will assume that the bottleneck
and the second bottleneck are unique.
Machine 10 is the bottleneck.
Machine 5 is the second bottleneck in this picture.
From now on, when we have to, we'll
call the bottleneck the first bottleneck.
Since buffers 5 through 9 are infinite,
buffer 5 will never be full.
Consequently, what happens downstream of buffer 5
does not have any effect on what happens upstream of buffer 5.
Therefore, the part of the line from machine 1 to machine 5
is the infinite buffer line with a bottleneck at machine 5.
From what we've learned about lines with infinite buffers
and bottlenecks, the amount of material in buffer 4
increases steadily without limit.
So an increasing amount of inventory
accumulates just upstream of the second bottleneck.
A finite amount of inventory appears
between the second bottleneck and the machine
upstream of the first bottleneck.
Since machines 6, 7, 8, and 9 are all faster
than machine 5, the levels in buffers 6, 7, 8, and 9
do not increase steadily over time.
An increasing amount of inventory
accumulates in the buffer just upstream
of the first bottleneck.
Of course, we already knew that.
That's what happens.
That's what we've been describing earlier.
A finite amount of inventory appears
downstream of the first bottleneck-- again,
for the same reason.
If there were machines in buffers downstream of machine
10, they would be faster than machine 10.
So the amount of material in the buffers
would not increase over time.
So let's do a simulation of this.
Here, we have our line with two bottlenecks.
All the machines except machine 5 and 10
have the same parameters as most of the machines
in the last one, in which r was 0.01 and p was 0.01.
For machine 5, r is 0.01, and p is 0.02.
And for machine 10, r is 0.01 and p is 0.03 again.
Therefore, the production rates of all the machines
other than the first and second bottleneck are 0.909.
The production rate of machine 5 is 0,833,
and the production rate of machine 10--
the bottleneck-- is 0.769.
So here's the usual graph that we've been drawing.
It's drawn with the same scale as the first graph
that we showed, so you can compare them if you like.
Just to remind you, the production rate of machine 10
is less than that of machine 5.
But the level of buffer 4, the buffer upstream
of the second bottleneck, is greater
than the level of buffer 9, the buffer upstream
of the first bottleneck.
Does this seem counter-intuitive?
Why should this be?
Well, to look at the rates of growth of buffer 4
and buffer 9, the rate of growth of buffer 4
is 0.909 minus 0.833, by the same logic as we had earlier.
And that's 0.076.
Now, remember that the rate of flow into buffer 9
is not 0.909 anymore.
It's 0.833 because that's the rate that parts
are leaving machine 5.
So the rate of growth of buffer 9 is 0.833 minus 0.769,
which is 0.064 so that when t is large enough,
the level of buffer 4 is going to be greater
than the level of buffer 9.
So that, is in this case, the buffer
before the second bottleneck accumulates material
faster than the buffer before the first bottleneck.
But that's not a general rule.
The rate of growth of both of those first and second
bottleneck buffers depend on the parameters of the machines.
It's tempting to believe that the easiest
way to find the bottleneck of a line
is to look for the greatest accumulation of inventory.
Is that correct?
Evidently not.
Machine 10 was the bottleneck, and machine 5
was the second bottleneck.
But buffer 4 has more material in it than buffer 9.
So let's ask my improvement questions again.
If we want to increase the production rate of a line,
which machine should we improve?
What would happen to the production rate
if we improved any other machine?
I will answer the question in a moment.
But I strongly suggest that you stop the video before you hear
my answers, think about them, and come up
with your own answers.
OK.
I gave you my spoiler alert.
Here come the answers.
If we want to increase the production rate,
which machine should we improve?
The answer is the bottleneck.
The production rate of the line with infinite buffers
is that of the bottleneck.
So any increase of the production rate
of the bottleneck will increase the production rate of the line
by that same amount.
Second question.
What would happen to the production rate of the line
if we improved any other machine?
Stop me again if you want to think about this one.
The answer is nothing.
The line's production rate is that of the slowest machine.
Speeding up any other machine's production rate
has no effect on the line's production rate.
But these answers do not apply to lines with finite buffers.
Let's talk a little bit about simulation.
The simulations shown here were discrete-time rather than
discrete-event simulation.
I'll describe discrete-time simulation.
Discrete-time simulations are easier to program
but less general, less accurate, and slower
than discrete-event simulations.
Discrete-time simulations are easiest to write for systems
where all event times are geometrically distributed.
Commercial simulation code is always discrete-event
because it's faster and more flexible.
If you need to simulate a very simple system,
however, it's sometimes preferable to write
the simulation yourself.
Here's a very brief introduction to discrete-time simulation.
Assume that some event occurs according
to a geometric probability distribution,
and it has a mean time to occur of t time steps.
Then the probability that it occurs in any given time step
is p equals 1 over T. The discrete-time simulation logic
is at each time step, choose x--
a uniformly distributed random number between 0 and 1.
If x is less than p, the event has occurred.
Change the state of the system accordingly.
If x is greater than p, the event has not occurred.
Change the state according to this.
If x is chosen in this way, then the probability
that the event has occurred is p.
We'll discuss simulation a little more in the second part
of the course.