Hi, everyone.
Welcome to week. three recitation.
In this video, we'll go over practice problem two
from the MicroMaster's section.
OK.
So let me just redraw the transition diagram here.
So we have four states, state one, two, three, and four.
Now according to the problem, the transition
from state one to two is 0.01.
The transition from one to three is 0.005.
From three to one, it is 0.05.
From two to three, it is 0.005.
From two to four, it's 0.1.
From four to one, it is 0.07.
OK.
So once we have the transition diagram set up,
the first thing that I do is to set up the transition matrix.
So if you remember from the continuous time recitation
video, we said in a discrete state continuous time system,
each column is going to sum to 0.
So here are the four states-- one, two, three, four, one,
two, three, four.
OK.
First, the transition from one to two
is 0.01, one to three 0.005, one to four is 0.
So for this column to sum to 0, this is just 0.015.
In column two, we have 0.
The transition from two to two is just the sum of the columns.
From two to three, we have 0.005.
Two to four is just 0.1.
So right here, we have negative 0.105.
In the third column, we have 0.05, 0, negative 0.05, 0,
and lastly 0.07, 0, 0, negative 0.07.
OK.
Here is our transition matrix.
Now, we know that one of these equations is redundant,
and we're going to replace it with the normalization
equation.
So the normalization equation is just P1 plus P2 plus P3 plus P4
equals 1.
So technically this is what we are solving for--
P1, P2, P3, P4 equal to 0.
We're solving for the null space of the transition matrix.
Now, it doesn't matter which equation
we replace with the normalization equation.
Here, I'm just going to replace the last equation.
So our new matrix essentially is 0.015, 0.01, 0.005, 1, 0,
negative 0.105, 0.005, 0.1--
no, sorry, this is not 0.1.
This last part is just 1.
The third column--
0.05, 0, negative 0.05, and 1, 0.07, 0, 0, and 1.
And this multiplies by P1, P2, P3, P4 gives us 0, 0, 0, 1.
This last equation is just a normalization equation.
So let's call this matrix A. And let's call this vector B.
And this is the vector P.
So essentially in matrix formation,
we have A times P equals B. Now, P is what we are solving for.
So all we have to do is take the inverse,
P equals A inverse times B, and this vector P is our solution.
P is 0.7458, 0.0710, 0.0817, 0.1015.
The simplest way to solve this matrix multiplication
is to just use Matlab, but you can use a variety of software.
I believe you could use Excel, Mathematica.
Basically any mathematical software
should be able to do this.
This is pretty basic.
And you could check that sum of P equals 1.
So the sum of the probabilities adds up to 1,
and we know that's correct.
So just so we're clear, it's P1, P2, P3, and P4.
OK.
That will be it for this recitation.
If you have any questions, please send me an email
or leave your comments in the discussion section below.
Thank you.