We're now going to start talking about stochastic processes
and some specific ones that are important for understanding
complex systems and, specifically, manufacturing
systems.
Stochastic processes are random processes in which
time plays an important role.
We define X as a stochastic process if X of t
is a random variable for every t.
Here, t is a scalar.
It really means time for us.
It could be discrete or continuous.
We're going to talk about both cases.
X of t itself can be discrete or continuous,
a scalar or a vector.
A Markov process is a special stochastic process.
It's one in which the probability of finding X
at some value at time t plus delta t
depends only on the value of X at time t.
In this case, we don't require that delta t be a small number,
but we will later for some cases.
So another way of saying this, we'll define lower case X of s.
These are values of random variable capital X. So X of s,
where s is less than or equal to t,
is the history of the values of X before time t.
And we'll let A be a possible value of X.
So the statement is that the probability that X
of t plus delta t equals A--
given the whole history of X up to and including time t--
is the same as the probability of X( of t plus delta t being
A, given, only that X of t is equal to little x of t,
only at time t and we don't care about what happens before.
In other words, if we know what X was at time t,
we don't gain any more useful information
about X of t plus delta t, by also knowing what x
was at any time earlier than t.
Please keep in mind this is only the definition of a class
of mathematical models.
It is not a statement about reality.
In other words, not everything is a Markov process.
So here's an example.
Suppose I have $100 at time t equals 0.
At every time t greater than or equal to 1, the amount of money
I have is called N of t dollars.
Now, each time a possibly biased coin
is flipped, if it lands with H showing, then I gain $1.
So N of t plus delta t equals N of t plus 1.
Then N of t plus 1 equals N of t minus 1.
In other words, I lose $1.
So N of t is a Markov process.
Why?
The reason is that it doesn't matter
what N was at time t minus 1 and t minus 2
all the way back to t 0.
All that determines what N is at time t plus 1
is what N was at time t and the outcome of the coin flip.
There are four kinds of Markov processes.
Those with discrete state versus continuous state
and those with discrete time versus continuous time.
We're going to start off by talking about discrete state,
discrete time processes.
And later, we'll talk about discrete state,
continuous time processes.
So in discrete state, discrete time processes,
the states can be numbered 0, 1, 2, 3, and so forth.
Or if it's more convenient, we can have multiple indices.
The time can be numbered 0, 1, 2, 3, or 0, delta 2, delta
and so forth if more convenient.
So the time is essentially only integers.
The probability of a transition from j to i
in one time it is often written Pij, where
Pij is the probability that x of t plus 1 equals i,
given that X of t equals j.
And just as a notation note, some people
prefer to put the indices the other way around.
So what I called Pij is called Pji.
This is the transition graph of a discrete time Markov
chain with seven states.
The circles represent the states,
the arrows represent possible transitions.
Of course, we're only indicating transitions
with non-zero probabilities.
The labels on the arrows are the transition probabilities.
So we can see that if the system is in state 4 at time 12,
for example, then at time 13, it could be in state 1 or 2 or 6.
Or it could stay where it is in state 4.
Given that it's in state 4 at time 12,
then it could be in state 1 at time 13 with probability P14
or state 2 at time 13 with probability P24
or state 6 at time 13 with probability P64.
It might also be at state 4 at time 13
with probability P44, which is 1 minus P14 minus P24 minus P64.
That's the label on the self loop probability.
There are four possible transitions from state 4,
and the sum of those probabilities must be 1.
So the self loop probability is 1 minus the sum of the others.
The following is an animation that'll
give you some idea of what actually
happens with the system.
We're going to start in state 1 and then
we're going to watch it move.
It might go to state 2 at time equals 1
or it might go to state three, we don't know.
We can think of the way the transitions are determined
by imagining that there's a spinner
at every one of the states.
For example, here's the one which
might correspond to state 4.
The red area would correspond to the transition to state 1,
the purple to state 2, the tan to state 6,
and the yellow staying home at state 4.
So at every time step that you're in state 4,
you spin the spinner and it whizzes around
and it ends up at one of those random places.
And that determines where it goes next.
Here's the system at time 0.
And we're starting it off in state 1.
So at time 1, it's still in state 1.
But at time 2, it's gone to state 3.
At time 4, it's still in state 3, and so on.
So over time, it's going to jump around and go
from state to state.
It will probably visit every one of these states
if we wait long enough.
And if we wait a long enough time,
it will go back to the same states.
And what we're interested in in the long run
is how much time it spends in each one of these states.
Later on, we're going to use this
as a way of representing the failures in repairs
of a machine.
And to begin with, we'll have some very simple pictures where
there are only two states.
One state is up and the other one
is down, operational and under repair.
And we're going to model it as going back and forth
between those two states.
And then later on, we'll have even more complex systems.
The basic idea is a simple system that looks like this.
We'll also be dealing with infinite dimensional systems.
That is, where there's an infinite number of states.
And there, there's some other interesting phenomena
that come up that we have to take care of.
Here's another example.
We're going to flip coins and count
how many times we get heads.
So we'll define our state as H of t,
which is the number of heads that we observe
after there are t coin flips.
So let's assume that the probability of heads is p.
So here's the state space.
We start at time 0 and we flip a coin.
If the coin comes up heads, which
it does with probability p, we make the transition
from 0 to 1.
Otherwise with probability 1 minus p, we stay at 0.
When we get to 1, we do the same thing.
And then, we get to 2 and 3 and so on.
So the progression from 1 to 2 to 3
takes place at random times because we don't know what
the coin flip is going to show.
But what we do know is that over time,
eventually, we're going to reach all the states
and go off to infinity.
So we have an infinite space here.
Here's another one.
Remember the coin flip bets that we had at slide 5,
where I gained $1 or lost $1, depending on the coin flip.
Now, we'll allow the coin to be unfair.
So it has probability of heads as p.
And here's the state space.
Now, if we start with $100, for example, if we flip a heads,
we move up to $101.
If we flip tails, we move down to $99.
And we can bounce around along this whole state space.
Again, the state space is infinite,
although we can assume that we never get below 0.
But it's still infinite in the other direction.